Sunday, January 3

“Who has come to know the mind of Jehovah, so that he may instruct him?” But we do have the mind of Christ.—[1 Cor. 2:16].

Where are Jesus’ teachings recorded? The four Gospels record many of the things Jesus said and did on earth. The rest of the Christian Greek Scriptures—written by men who were inspired by holy spirit and who had “the mind of Christ”—further help us to understand Jesus’ thinking on matters. Jesus’ teachings cover all aspects of life. So the “law of the Christ” governs what we do at home, at work or at school, and in the congregation. ([Gal. 6:2]) We learn this law by reading the Christian Greek Scriptures and meditating on them. We obey this law by bringing our lives into harmony with the instructions, commands, and principles found in that inspired record. When we obey the law of the Christ, we are obeying our loving God, Jehovah, who is the Source of all that Jesus taught.—[John 8:28]. w19.05 3 ¶6-7

^ (1 Cor. 2:16) For “who has come to know the mind of Jehovah, so that he may instruct him?” But we do have the mind of Christ.

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (John 8:28) Jesus then said: “After you have lifted up the Son of man, then you will know that I am he and that I do nothing of my own initiative; but just as the Father taught me, I speak these things.

Monday, January 4

Wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse.—[2 Tim. 3:13].

It is sad when humans act in a way that pleases the Devil. However, Jehovah is never blind to Satan’s tactics. He is fully aware of the pain we experience, and he can provide the comfort we need. We are blessed to serve “the God of all comfort, who comforts us in all our trials so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.” (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Those who have been abandoned by parents or victimized by people close to them may especially need comfort. The psalmist David knew that Jehovah is the most reliable provider of comfort. ([Ps. 27:10]) David had faith that Jehovah takes in those who have been rejected by their loved ones. How? By using his faithful human servants. Our fellow worshippers of Jehovah are our spiritual family. For instance, Jesus spoke of those who joined him in worshipping Jehovah as his brothers, sisters, and mother.—Matt. 12:48-50. w19.05 15-16 ¶8-9

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

^ (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts us in all our trials so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.

^ (Ps. 27:10) Even if my own father and mother abandon me, Jehovah himself will take me in.

^ (Matt. 12:48-50) In reply he said to the one who spoke to him: “Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?” 49 And extending his hand toward his disciples, he said: “Look! My mother and my brothers! 50 For whoever does the will of my Father who is in heaven, that one is my brother and sister and mother.”

Wednesday, January 6

My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.—[John 4:34].

Jesus set an outstanding example in his attitude toward the ministry. He made talking about God’s Kingdom the main focus of his life. He walked hundreds of miles to preach to as many as possible. He seized every opportunity to speak to people in public places and in their homes. Jesus’ whole life revolved around the ministry. We can imitate Christ by creating opportunities to talk about the good news whenever and wherever possible. We are willing to sacrifice personal comfort to engage in the evangelizing work. (Mark 6:31-34;[1 Pet. 2:21]) Some in the congregation are able to serve as special, regular, or auxiliary pioneers. Others have learned to speak another language or have moved to an area where there is a need for more preachers. However, much of the evangelizing work is done by regular Kingdom publishers, who do the best they can. Whatever the case, Jehovah does not ask more of us than we can give. w19.04 4 ¶7-8

^ (John 4:34) Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.

^ (Mark 6:31-34) And he said to them: “Come, you yourselves, privately into an isolated place and rest up a little.” For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal. 32 So they set off in the boat for an isolated place to be by themselves. 33 But people saw them going and many got to know it, and from all the cities they ran together on foot and got there ahead of them. 34 Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

Thursday, January 7

May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be pleasing to you, O Jehovah.—[Ps. 19:14].

Ask yourself: ‘Is there a trace of envy or jealousy in my heart?’ ([1 Pet. 2:1]) ‘Do I feel a measure of pride because of my background, education, or financial status?’ ([Prov. 16:5]) ‘Do I look down on others who do not have the same things I have or who are from a different racial background?’ ([Jas. 2:2-4]) ‘Do I feel attracted to what Satan’s world offers?’ (1 John 2:15-17) ‘Do I feel drawn to immoral and violent entertainment?’ ([Ps. 97:10;][101:3;][Amos 5:15]) The answers to these personal questions may highlight areas that you need to work on. We are strongly influenced by those with whom we associate. ([Prov. 13:20]) At work or in school, we are likely surrounded by those who will not help us to develop godly thinking. However, we can find the best type of association at our Christian meetings. There is where we can be motivated, or stirred up, to “love and fine works.”—Heb. 10:24, 25, ftn. w19.06 12 ¶13-14

^ (Ps. 19:14) May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart Be pleasing to you, O Jehovah, my Rock and my Redeemer.

^ (1 Pet. 2:1) So rid yourselves of all badness and deceit and hypocrisy and envy and all backbiting.

^ (Prov. 16:5) Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

^ (Jas. 2:2-4) For if a man with gold rings on his fingers and in splendid clothing comes into your meeting, but a poor man in filthy clothing also enters, 3 do you look with favor on the one wearing the splendid clothing and say, “You take this seat here in a fine place,” and do you say to the poor one, “You keep standing” or, “Take that seat there under my footstool”? 4 If so, do you not have class distinctions among yourselves, and have you not become judges rendering wicked decisions?

^ (1 John 2:15-17) Do not love either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. 17 Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

^ (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

^ (Ps. 101:3) I will not set anything worthless* before my eyes. I hate the deeds of those who deviate from what is right; I will have nothing to do with them.*

Or “good-for-nothing.”

Or “Their deeds do not cling to me.”

^ (Amos 5:15) Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

^ (Prov. 13:20) The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

Monday, January 11

Be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain in connection with the Lord.—[1 Cor. 15:58].

You do not need to be physically strong in order to continue growing stronger spiritually. In fact, many whose physical strength has declined still maintain a fiery determination to keep progressing spiritually. ([2 Cor. 4:16]) Perhaps you have served Jehovah for many years and now find that failing health prevents you from doing as much as you once did. If so, do not despair. Be assured that Jehovah cherishes the faithful service you have accomplished in the past. ([Heb. 6:10]) And as for the present, remember that whole-souled devotion is not measured by how much we do in Jehovah’s service. Rather, we reveal the depth of our devotion by showing a positive spirit and by doing all that we physically can. ([Col. 3:23]) Jehovah understands our limitations and does not require more than we can give.—Mark 12:43, 44. w19.08 3 ¶6; 5 ¶11-12

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

^ (2 Cor. 4:16) Therefore, we do not give up, but even if the man we are outside is wasting away, certainly the man we are inside is being renewed from day to day.

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

^ (Mark 12:43, 44) So he called his disciples to him and said to them: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all the others who put money into the treasury chests. 44 For they all put in out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,* put in everything she had, all she had to live on.”

Or “poverty.”

Wednesday, January 13

The lamp of the body is the eye. If, then, your eye is focused, your whole body will be bright.—[Matt. 6:22].

What did Jesus mean? He meant that we need to keep our life simple or focused on a single goal, or purpose, not being distracted or sidetracked from it. Jesus himself set the example by focusing his life on the ministry, and he taught his disciples to keep focused on serving Jehovah and on His Kingdom. We imitate Jesus by living a life that centers on the Christian ministry, “seeking first the Kingdom and [God’s] righteousness.” ([Matt. 6:33]) One way to focus on our ministry is by simplifying our life so that we can spend more time helping others come to know and love Jehovah. For example, could we adjust our secular working hours so that we can spend more time in the ministry during the week? Could we reduce some recreational activities that may be very time-consuming? w19.04 5-6 ¶12-13

^ (Matt. 6:22) “The lamp of the body is the eye. If, then, your eye is focused, your whole body will be bright.*

Or “full of light.”

^ (Matt. 6:33) “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

Friday, January 15

The orders from Jehovah are righteous, causing the heart to rejoice; . . . in keeping them, there is a large reward.—[Ps. 19:8,][11].

Jehovah appointed David as head not only of his family but also of the entire nation of Israel. As king, David had a lot of power. At times, he misused that power and made serious mistakes. (2 Sam. 11:14, 15) But he showed his submission to Jehovah by accepting discipline. He poured out his heart to Jehovah in prayer. And he tried his best to obey Jehovah’s counsel. ([Ps. 51:1-4]) In addition, he was humble enough to accept good advice not only from men but also from women. (1 Sam. 19:11, 12;[25:32, 33]) David learned from his mistakes and centered his life on serving Jehovah. He knew the benefits of submitting to Jehovah. Today, we can see the contrast between those who submit to Jehovah and those who reject his loving counsel. Those who do submit to Jehovah “shout joyfully because of the good condition of the heart.”—Isa. 65:13, 14. w19.09 17 ¶15; 19 ¶21

^ (Ps. 19:8) The orders from Jehovah are righteous, causing the heart to rejoice; The commandment of Jehovah is clean, making the eyes shine.

^ (Ps. 19:11) By them your servant has been warned; In keeping them, there is a large reward.

^ (2 Sam. 11:14, 15) In the morning David wrote a letter to Joʹab and sent it by the hand of U·riʹah. 15 He wrote in the letter: “Put U·riʹah in the front lines where the fighting is fiercest. Then retreat from behind him, so that he will be struck down and die.”

^ (Ps. 51:1-4) Show me favor, O God, according to your loyal love. Blot out my transgressions according to your great mercy.  2 Thoroughly wash me from my error, And cleanse me from my sin.  3 For I am well-aware of my transgressions, And my sin is always before me.*  4 Against you—you above all*—I have sinned; What is bad in your eyes I have done. Therefore, you are righteous when you speak, You are right in your judgment.

Or “on my mind.”

Lit., “only you.”

^ (1 Sam. 19:11, 12) Saul later sent messengers to David’s house to watch it and to kill him in the morning, but David’s wife Miʹchal told him: “If you do not escape* tonight, tomorrow you will be a dead man.” 12 Immediately Miʹchal let David down through the window, so that he could run away and escape.

Or “If you do not let your soul escape.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:32, 33) At this David said to Abʹi·gail: “Praise Jehovah the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me! 33 And blessed be your good sense! May you be blessed for restraining me this day from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge* with my own hands.

Or “bringing salvation.”

^ (Isa. 65:13, 14) Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Look! My servants will eat, but you will go hungry. Look! My servants will drink, but you will go thirsty. Look! My servants will rejoice, but you will suffer shame. 14 Look! My servants will shout joyfully because of the good condition of the heart, But you will cry out because of the pain of heart And you will wail because of a broken spirit.

Sunday, January 17

Love Jehovah, all you who are loyal to him!—[Ps. 31:23].

Jehovah expects his worshippers to separate themselves from Babylon the Great. However, this requires more than our cutting ties with false religion. We must be determined to uphold true religion—the pure worship of Jehovah. Consider two ways that we can do that. First, we must remain firm for Jehovah’s righteous moral standards. We cannot accept the world’s values and standards. For example, we do not approve of sexual immorality of any kind, including marriage between people of the same sex and other homosexual lifestyles. (Matt. 19:4, 5; Rom. 1:26, 27) Second, we must continue worshipping with our fellow Christians. We do this wherever we can, whether in our Kingdom Halls or, when necessary, in private homes or even in secret. No matter what happens, we cannot let up in our routine of meeting together for worship. In fact, we need to meet together “all the more so as [we] see the day drawing near.”—Heb. 10:24, 25. w19.10 16 ¶6-7

^ (Ps. 31:23) Love Jehovah, all you who are loyal to him! Jehovah protects the faithful, But he repays exceedingly anyone showing haughtiness.

^ (Matt. 19:4, 5) In reply he said: “Have you not read that the one who created them from the beginning made them male and female 5 and said: ‘For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother and will stick to his wife, and the two will be one flesh’?

^ (Rom. 1:26, 27) That is why God gave them over to disgraceful sexual passion, for their females changed the natural use of themselves into one contrary to nature; 27 likewise also the males left the natural use of the female and became violently inflamed in their lust toward one another, males with males, working what is obscene and receiving in themselves the full penalty, which was due for their error.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

Wednesday, January 20

I give you my peace.—[John 14:27].

On his final day as a human, Jesus was troubled. Soon he would suffer a cruel death at the hands of lawless men. But it was more than his impending death that was giving Jesus concern. He deeply loved his Father and wanted to please him. Jesus knew that if he proved faithful under the coming difficult test, he would contribute to the vindication of Jehovah’s name. Jesus also loved people, and he knew that our future prospects for everlasting life would depend on his finishing his earthly course successfully. Even though Jesus was under great stress, he was at peace. He had “the peace of God,” the calmness and tranquility that result from a person’s precious relationship with Jehovah. That peace put Jesus’ mind and heart at rest. ([Phil. 4:6, 7]) None of us will ever face the kind of pressure that Jesus had to endure, but all who follow Jesus will face trials. (Matt. 16:24, 25;[John 15:20]) And like Jesus, we will feel troubled at times. w19.04 8 ¶1-3

^ (John 14:27) I leave you peace; I give you my peace. I do not give it to you the way that the world gives it. Do not let your hearts be troubled nor let them shrink out of fear.

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ (Matt. 16:24, 25) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and keep following me. 25 For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for my sake will find it.

^ (John 15:20) Keep in mind the word I said to you: A slave is not greater than his master. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have observed my word, they will also observe yours.

Wednesday, January 27

Do all things for God’s glory. Keep from becoming causes for stumbling.—1 Cor. 10:31, 32.

When deciding whether to share in a custom or tradition, we should think about how our decision may affect the consciences of others, especially fellow Christians. Never would we want to stumble someone! ([Mark 9:42]) Also, we want to avoid needlessly offending those who are not Witnesses. Love will move us to speak to them in a respectful way, which glorifies Jehovah. We certainly would not quarrel with people or ridicule their traditions. Remember, love is powerful! When we reflect it in a considerate and respectful manner, we may even soften the hearts of opposers. Make it known in your community that you are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses. ([Isa. 43:10]) You will likely find it easier to handle emotionally charged situations if your relatives and neighbors know that you worship Jehovah God. May we never be ashamed of the stand that we take in defense of the truth.—[Rom. 1:16]. w19.04 17-18 ¶14-16

^ (1 Cor. 10:31, 32) Therefore, whether you are eating or drinking or doing anything else, do all things for God’s glory. 32 Keep from becoming causes for stumbling to Jews as well as Greeks and to the congregation of God,

^ (Mark 9:42) But whoever stumbles one of these little ones who have faith, it would be better for him if a millstone that is turned by a donkey were put around his neck and he were pitched into the sea.

^ (Isa. 43:10) “You are my witnesses,” declares Jehovah, “Yes, my servant whom I have chosen, So that you may know and have faith in me* And understand that I am the same One. Before me no God was formed, And after me there has been none.

Or “and trust me.”

^ (Rom. 1:16) For I am not ashamed of the good news; it is, in fact, God’s power for salvation to everyone having faith, to the Jew first and also to the Greek.

Saturday, January 30

Fully accomplish your ministry.—[2 Tim. 4:5].

What does it mean to accomplish our ministry fully? Simply put, to accomplish our ministry fully, we must have as full a share as possible in the preaching and teaching work. But more is involved than the amount of time. Our motive is important to Jehovah. Because we love Jehovah and our neighbor, we work whole-souled in our Christian ministry. (Mark 12:30, 31;[Col. 3:23]) Serving God whole-souled means giving of ourselves, using our strength and energies to the best of our ability in his service. When we appreciate the privilege of doing the preaching work, we try to share the good news with as many people as we can. We may be limited in the amount of time we can devote to the preaching work. Yet, that is what we love to do. We strive to improve our ability to reach people’s hearts with the good news. We make the preaching work our priority. w19.04 2 ¶3; 3 ¶4, 6

^ (2 Tim. 4:5) You, though, keep your senses in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelizer,* fully accomplish your ministry.

Or “keep preaching the good news.”

^ (Mark 12:30, 31) and you must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’ 31 The second is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.”

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

Wednesday, February 3

On the testimony of two or three witnesses every matter may be established.—[Matt. 18:16].

Before the elders take judicial action, why are at least two witnesses required? This requirement is part of the Bible’s high standard of justice. When there is no confession of wrongdoing, two witnesses are required to establish the accusation and authorize the elders to take judicial action. ([Deut. 19:15;][1 Tim. 5:19]) If the individual denies the accusation, the elders consider the testimony of witnesses. If at least two people—the one making the accusation and someone else—can confirm the charge, a judicial committee is formed. The absence of a second witness does not mean that the one making the accusation is untruthful. Even if a charge of wrongdoing cannot be established by two witnesses, the elders recognize that a serious sin may have been committed. The elders provide ongoing support to any individuals who may have been hurt and remain alert to protect the congregation from potential danger.—[Acts 20:28]. w19.05 11 ¶15-16

^ (Matt. 18:16) But if he does not listen, take along with you one or two more, so that on the testimony* of two or three witnesses every matter* may be established.*

Lit., “mouth.”

Or “everything said.”

Lit., “might stand.”

^ (Deut. 19:15) “No single witness may convict* another for any error or any sin that he may commit. On the testimony* of two witnesses or on the testimony of three witnesses the matter should be established.

Lit., “rise up against.”

Lit., “mouth.”

^ (1 Tim. 5:19) Do not accept an accusation against an older man* except on the evidence of two or three witnesses.

Or “an elder.”

^ (Acts 20:28) Pay attention to yourselves and to all the flock, among which the holy spirit has appointed you overseers, to shepherd the congregation of God, which he purchased with the blood of his own Son.

Friday, February 5

We are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God.—[2 Cor. 10:5].

Satan is determined to change our thinking. He uses every type of reasoning to counteract the influence of the truth of God’s Word. Satan continues to ask the same question he asked Eve in the garden of Eden: “Did God really say that . . . ?” ([Gen. 3:1]) In the world under Satan’s control, we often hear challenging questions, such as these: ‘Does God really not approve of same-sex marriage? Does God really not want you to celebrate Christmas and birthdays? Does your God really expect you to refuse a blood transfusion? Does a loving God really expect you to avoid association with disfellowshipped loved ones?’ We need to be convinced of our beliefs. If we leave challenging questions unanswered in our minds, they can become serious doubts. Those doubts could eventually distort our thinking and destroy our faith. w19.06 12-13 ¶15-17

^ (2 Cor. 10:5) For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ;

^ (Gen. 3:1) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

Saturday, February 6

All of you have unity of mind, fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.—[1 Pet. 3:8].

Jehovah loves us deeply. ([John 3:16]) We want to imitate our loving Father. So we try to show “fellow feeling, brotherly affection, [and] tender compassion” to all but especially to those who are “related to us in the faith.” ([Gal. 6:10]) When members of our spiritual family face stressful challenges, we want to help them. How can we console someone whose marriage mate has died? An important first step is to speak to him or her, even though you may feel awkward or unsure of what to say. Paula, whose husband died suddenly, says: “I understand that death makes people uncomfortable. They worry that what they say might come out wrong. But worse than hearing something awkward is hearing nothing at all.” A grieving person probably does not expect us to say something profound. Paula says: “I appreciated it when friends would simply say, ‘I’m sorry for your loss.’” w19.06 20 ¶1; 23 ¶14

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (Gal. 6:10) So, then, as long as we have the opportunity,* let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

Lit., “appointed time.”

Monday, February 8

Make disciples of people of all the nations.—[Matt. 28:19].

How can we help nonreligious people to learn to love God and become disciples of Christ? We must recognize that a person’s reaction to our message may depend on where he was raised. For example, people with a European background may not respond the same way as may those who come from Asia. Why? In Europe, many know something about the Bible and are familiar with the idea that God created all things. But in Asia, the majority of people know little or nothing about the Bible, and they may not believe in a Creator. So be positive. Every year, there are nonreligious people who become Jehovah’s Witnesses. Many already had high moral standards and felt disgusted by religious hypocrisy. Others had low moral standards and many had bad habits that they needed to abandon. With Jehovah’s help, we can be sure that we will find those who are “rightly disposed for everlasting life.”—[Acts 13:48;] 1 Tim. 2:3, 4. w19.07 20-21 ¶3-4

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (1 Tim. 2:3, 4) This is fine and acceptable in the sight of our Savior, God, 4 whose will is that all sorts of people should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.

Tuesday, February 9

We do not give up.—[2 Cor. 4:16].

Whether our hope is everlasting life in heaven or on a paradise earth, we must keep pressing on toward that goal. No matter what our circumstances, we must not look at the things behind; nor should we let anything hinder our progress. ([Phil. 3:16]) The fulfillment of our expectations may seem to be delayed, or our physical strength may be declining. We may have endured hardship and persecution for many years. Whatever the case, “do not be anxious over anything.” Rather, let your petitions and supplications be made known to God, and he will give you a peace that is beyond your imagination. ([Phil. 4:6, 7]) Like a runner who exerts himself as he races down the homestretch, may we stay fully focused on the goal of finishing the race for life. To the extent that our strength and circumstances allow, may we exert ourselves and progress eagerly toward the wonderful things ahead. w19.08 7 ¶16-17

^ (2 Cor. 4:16) Therefore, we do not give up, but even if the man we are outside is wasting away, certainly the man we are inside is being renewed from day to day.

^ (Phil. 3:16) At any rate, to the extent we have made progress, let us go on walking orderly in this same course.

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Sunday, February 14

I saw . . . a great crowd . . . out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues.—[Rev. 7:9].

The prophet Zechariah had earlier foretold something similar. He wrote: “In those days ten men out of all the languages of the nations will take hold, yes, they will take firm hold of the robe of a Jew, saying: ‘We want to go with you, for we have heard that God is with you people.’” ([Zech. 8:23]) Jehovah’s Witnesses realize that for people of all languages to be gathered, the good news must be preached in many languages. We are now carrying out the greatest translation effort in history in hundreds of languages. Clearly, Jehovah is performing a modern-day miracle—gathering a great crowd from all nations. Thanks to the availability of spiritual food in more and more languages, this diverse group is united in worship. And the Witnesses are well-known for their zealous preaching and their brotherly love. How faith-strengthening that is!—[Matt. 24:14;][John 13:35]. w19.09 30-31 ¶16-17

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Zech. 8:23) “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘In those days ten men out of all the languages of the nations will take hold, yes, they will take firm hold of the robe* of a Jew,* saying: “We want to go with you, for we have heard that God is with you people.”’”

Or “extremity of the garment.”

Lit., “a Jewish man.”

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

Wednesday, February 17

Become imitators of God, as beloved children, and go on walking in love.—[Eph. 5:1, 2].

Jehovah proved his love for us by giving his Son as a ransom in our behalf. ([John 3:16]) How can we imitate Jehovah’s love? We view each of our brothers and sisters as valuable and precious, and we gladly welcome back “a lost sheep” who returns to Jehovah. ([Ps. 119:176;][Luke 15:7,][10]) We prove that we love our brothers and sisters by giving of ourselves, such as by helping them in times of need. ([1 John 3:17]) Jesus commanded his followers to show self-sacrificing love. (John 13:34, 35) Jesus’ commandment is new because it calls for a kind of love that was not required under the Law that God gave Israel: Love fellow believers as Jesus loved you. That requires a self-sacrificing love. We are to love our brothers and sisters even more than we love ourselves. We must love them to the point of being willing to give up our life for them, as Jesus did for us. w19.05 4 ¶11-13

^ (Eph. 5:1, 2) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children, 2 and go on walking in love, just as the Christ also loved us* and gave himself for us* as an offering and a sacrifice, a sweet fragrance to God.

Or possibly, “you.”

Or possibly, “you.”

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (Ps. 119:176) I have strayed like a lost sheep. Search for your servant, For I have not forgotten your commandments.

^ (Luke 15:7) I tell you that in the same way, there will be more joy in heaven over one sinner who repents than over 99 righteous ones who have no need of repentance.

^ (Luke 15:10) In the same way, I tell you, joy arises among the angels of God over one sinner who repents.”

^ (1 John 3:17) But whoever has the material possessions of this world and sees his brother in need and yet refuses to show him compassion, in what way does the love of God remain in him?

^ (John 13:34, 35) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another. 35 By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

Friday, February 19

Come . . . into an isolated place and rest up a little.—[Mark 6:31].

Jesus knew that at times he and the apostles needed some rest. However, many people back then and many today can be likened to the rich man in Jesus’ illustration. That man convinced himself: “Take it easy, eat, drink, enjoy yourself.” ([Luke 12:19;][2 Tim. 3:4]) He set his heart on rest and pleasures. In contrast, Jesus and the apostles did not center their lives on pleasing themselves. Today, we try to imitate Jesus by using the time we have off from work not only to rest but also to do good by witnessing to others and attending Christian meetings. In fact, to us, disciple-making and meeting attendance are so important that we make every effort to engage regularly in those sacred activities. (Heb. 10:24, 25) Even when we are on vacation, we keep to our regular spiritual routine of attending meetings wherever we are, and we look for opportunities to have conversations with those whom we meet.—[2 Tim. 4:2]. w19.12 7 ¶16-17

^ (Mark 6:31) And he said to them: “Come, you yourselves, privately into an isolated place and rest up a little.” For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal.

^ (Luke 12:19) and I will say to myself: “You have many good things stored up for many years; take it easy, eat, drink, enjoy yourself.”’

^ (2 Tim. 3:4) betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God,

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (2 Tim. 4:2) Preach the word; be at it urgently in favorable times and difficult times; reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all patience and art of teaching.

Sunday, February 21

The plans of the diligent surely lead to success.—[Prov. 21:5].

Jesus likened our time to “the days of Noah,” and there is no doubt that we are living in “critical times hard to deal with.” ([Matt. 24:37;][2 Tim. 3:1]) With that reality in mind, some couples have concluded that they would like to postpone having children so that they can devote more time to sharing in the Christian ministry. When deciding whether to have children and how many children to have, wise couples “calculate the expense.” (Luke 14:28, 29) Experienced parents confirm that raising children not only costs money but also costs time and energy. Thus, it is important for a couple to consider such questions as: ‘Would both of us have to work to supply the family’s basic needs? Do we agree on what our “basic needs” are? If we both would have to work, who would look after our children? Who would influence their thinking and actions?’ Couples who calmly discuss those questions take to heart the words of today’s text. w19.12 23-24 ¶6-7

^ (Prov. 21:5) The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.

Or “advantage.”

^ (Matt. 24:37) For just as the days of Noah were, so the presence of the Son of man will be.

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ (Luke 14:28, 29) For example, who of you wanting to build a tower does not first sit down and calculate the expense to see if he has enough to complete it? 29 Otherwise, he might lay its foundation but not be able to finish it, and all the onlookers would start to ridicule him,

Friday, February 26

Pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.—[Rom. 14:19].

Peace cannot survive if envy is allowed to thrive. We need to weed out envy from our own heart and avoid planting feelings of envy in others. What specifically can we do to help others fight envy, and how can we promote peace? Our attitude and actions can have a big influence on others. The world wants us to make a “showy display” of the things we own. ([1 John 2:16]) But that attitude promotes envy. We can avoid nurturing envy in others if we choose not to talk constantly about the things we own or plan to buy. Another way we can avoid promoting envy is by being modest about the privileges we have in the congregation. If we draw attention to the privileges that we have, we create fertile ground in which envy can grow. By contrast, when we show genuine personal interest in others and acknowledge the good that they do, we help them feel content and we promote unity and peace in the congregation. w20.02 18 ¶15-16

^ (Rom. 14:19) So, then, let us pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.

^ (1 John 2:16) because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

Saturday, February 27

His invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made.—[Rom. 1:20].

You can learn about Jehovah through his creation. ([Rev. 4:11]) Meditate on the wisdom evident in the designs of plants and animals. Learn a little about the wonderful way your body is made. ([Ps. 139:14]) And think about the power that Jehovah packed into our sun, realizing that it is just one of billions of stars. ([Isa. 40:26]) As you do, your respect for Jehovah will deepen. However, knowing that Jehovah is wise and powerful is only part of the foundation of your relationship with him. To build a strong love for Jehovah, you need to know more about him. You need to be convinced that Jehovah cares for you personally. Remember that “if you search for him, he will let himself be found by you.” (1 Chron. 28:9) Jehovah says, “I have drawn you to me.” ([Jer. 31:3]) The more you appreciate all that Jehovah has done for you, the deeper your love for him will be. w20.03 4 ¶6-7

^ (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Ps. 139:14) I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well.

Or “My soul knows.”

^ (Isa. 40:26) “Lift up your eyes to heaven and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who brings out their army by number; He calls them all by name. Because of his vast dynamic energy and his awe-inspiring power, Not one of them is missing.

^ (1 Chron. 28:9) “And you, Solʹo·mon my son, know the God of your father and serve him with a complete* heart and with a delightful* soul,* for Jehovah searches through all hearts, and he discerns every inclination of the thoughts. If you search for him, he will let himself be found by you, but if you leave him, he will reject you forever.

Or “completely devoted.”

Or “willing.”

See Glossary.

^ (Jer. 31:3) From far away Jehovah appeared to me and said: “I have loved you with an everlasting love. That is why I have drawn you to me with loyal love.*

Or “have continued to show loyal love to you.”

March

Monday, March 1

“Separate yourselves,” says Jehovah, “and quit touching the unclean thing.”—[2 Cor. 6:17].

Love for God and his Word strengthens us to obey Jehovah even when well-meaning relatives or friends try to pressure us to share in unscriptural practices regarding the dead. They may try to shame us, perhaps by saying that we did not love or respect the deceased. Or they might say that our behavior will cause the dead person to harm the living in some way. In a Caribbean nation, many believe that after a person dies, his “ghost” may stay around and punish those who mistreated him. The “ghost” may even “wreak havoc on a community,” says one reference. It is a custom in Africa to cover mirrors in the home of the deceased and turn pictures to face the wall. The reason? Some claim that the dead must not see themselves! As Jehovah’s servants, we certainly do not believe any myths or take part in any practices that promote Satan’s lies!—1 Cor. 10:21, 22. w19.04 16 ¶11-12

^ (2 Cor. 6:17) “‘Therefore, get out from among them, and separate yourselves,’ says Jehovah, ‘and quit touching the unclean thing’”; “‘and I will take you in.’”

^ (1 Cor. 10:21, 22) You cannot be drinking the cup of Jehovah and the cup of demons; you cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah” and the table of demons. 22 Or ‘are we inciting Jehovah to jealousy’? We are not stronger than he is, are we?

Tuesday, March 2

All things . . . that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them.—[Matt. 7:12].

Jesus taught principles that would help his followers to treat others fairly. Think, for example, about the Golden Rule. We all want to be treated fairly. Therefore, we should behave fairly toward others. If we do, they may be moved to treat us with fairness. But what if we have been treated unjustly? Jesus also taught his followers to trust that Jehovah will “cause justice to be done for [those] who cry out to him day and night.” ([Luke 18:6, 7]) That statement is, in effect, a promise: Our just God is aware of the trials we are facing in these last days, and he will cause justice to be done for us in his due time. ([2 Thess. 1:6]) When we follow the principles that Jesus taught, we will treat others in a just way. And if we have been a victim of injustice in Satan’s world, we can take comfort in knowing that Jehovah will cause justice to be done for us. w19.05 5 ¶18-19

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

^ (Luke 18:6, 7) Then the Lord said: “Hear what the judge, although unrighteous, said! 7 Certainly, then, will not God cause justice to be done for his chosen ones who cry out to him day and night, while he is patient toward them?

^ (2 Thess. 1:6) This takes into account that it is righteous on God’s part to repay tribulation to those who make tribulation for you.

Wednesday, March 3

[Be] always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.—[1 Pet. 3:15].

Are you a young person in school? Your classmates may all believe in the theory of evolution. You would like to defend the Bible’s teaching, but perhaps you do not feel qualified to do so. That calls for a study project! Your aim could be twofold: (1) to strengthen your own conviction that God created all things and (2) to improve in your ability to defend the truth. ([Rom. 1:20]) You might first ask yourself, ‘What arguments have my classmates used in support of evolution?’ Then using our publications, do careful research. Defending your beliefs may not be as hard as you think. Most people believe in evolution simply because someone they respect told them that it is true. If you find just a point or two that you can share, you may provide a satisfactory answer to a sincere inquirer.—[Col. 4:6]. w19.05 29 ¶13

^ (1 Pet. 3:15) But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.

^ (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

^ (Col. 4:6) Let your words always be gracious, seasoned with salt, so that you will know how you should answer each person.

Thursday, March 4

As a mother comforts her son, so I will keep comforting you.—[Isa. 66:13].

When the prophet Elijah was on the run for his life, he was so discouraged that he wished for death. Jehovah sent a mighty angel to visit that discouraged man. The angel provided very practical help. He gave Elijah a hot meal and encouraged him to eat. ([1 Ki. 19:5-8]) That account illustrates a useful truth: Sometimes a simple act of practical kindness can do a great deal of good. Perhaps a meal, a modest gift, or a thoughtful card would assure a downhearted brother or sister of our love and concern. If we feel uncomfortable discussing very personal or painful subjects, perhaps we can still give such practical help. Jehovah miraculously gave Elijah the help he needed to go all the way to Mount Horeb, far out of the reach of those who sought to do him harm. What lesson may we draw? If we want to offer comfort to victims of abuse, we may need first to help them feel safe, whether at their home or at the Kingdom Hall. w19.05 16 ¶11; 17 ¶13-14

^ (Isa. 66:13) As a mother comforts her son, So I will keep comforting you; And over Jerusalem you will be comforted.

^ (1 Ki. 19:5-8) Then he lay down and fell asleep under the broom tree. But suddenly an angel touched him and said to him: “Get up and eat.” 6 When he looked, there at his head was a round loaf on heated stones and a jug of water. He ate and drank and lay down again. 7 Later the angel of Jehovah came back a second time and touched him and said: “Get up and eat, for the journey will be too much for you.” 8 So he got up and ate and drank, and in the strength of that nourishment he went on for 40 days and 40 nights until he reached Horʹeb, the mountain of the true God.

Friday, March 5

The land will wail, . . . the family of Nathan’s house by itself.—[Zech. 12:12].

Suppose that you are reading the 12th chapter of Zechariah’s prophecy, which foretells the death of the Messiah. ([Zech. 12:10]) When you come to [verse 12], you read that “the family of Nathan’s house” would grieve bitterly at the Messiah’s death. Instead of quickly passing over that detail, you pause and ask yourself: ‘What is the connection between the house of Nathan and the Messiah?’ You do a little “detective” work. A marginal reference leads you to 2 Samuel 5:13, 14, where you learn that Nathan was one of King David’s sons. A second marginal reference, [Luke 3:23,][31], reveals that Jesus was a direct descendant of Nathan through Mary. Suddenly, you are intrigued! You knew that Jesus was foretold to be a descendant of David. ([Matt. 22:42]) But David had more than 20 sons. Is it not amazing that Zechariah pinpoints the household of Nathan in particular as having a reason to mourn the death of Jesus? w19.05 30 ¶17

^ (Zech. 12:12) And the land will wail, each family by itself; the family of David’s house by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of Nathan’s house by itself, and their women by themselves;

^ (Zech. 12:10) “I will pour out on the house of David and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of favor and supplication, and they will look to the one whom they pierced, and they will wail over him as they would wail over an only son; and they will grieve bitterly over him as they would grieve over a firstborn son.

^ (Zech. 12:12) And the land will wail, each family by itself; the family of David’s house by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of Nathan’s house by itself, and their women by themselves;

^ (2 Sam. 5:13, 14) David took more concubines and wives in Jerusalem after he came from Hebʹron, and more sons and daughters were born to David. 14 These are the names of those born to him in Jerusalem: Sham·muʹa, Shoʹbab, Nathan, Solʹo·mon,

^ (Luke 3:23) When Jesus began his work, he was about 30 years old, being the son, as the opinion was, of Joseph, son of Heʹli,

^ (Luke 3:31) son of Meʹle·a, son of Menʹna, son of Matʹta·tha, son of Nathan, son of David,

^ (Matt. 22:42) “What do you think about the Christ? Whose son is he?” They said to him: “David’s.”

Sunday, March 7

The form of worship that is clean and undefiled from the standpoint of our God and Father is this: to look after orphans and widows in their tribulation.—[Jas. 1:27].

Just as Ruth stuck with the widowed Naomi, we need to provide ongoing support for those who lose a loved one in death. (Ruth 1:16, 17) Paula says: “Right after my husband died, I got a lot of support. As time passed, people’s lives seemed to go back to normal. However, my life had changed completely. It is a huge help when others realize that a grieving person needs support in the months—even years—following the death.” Of course, each person is different. Some seem to adjust to their new circumstances relatively quickly. For others, however, every activity they once shared with their loved one is a painful reminder of their loss. The ways people grieve vary from person to person. Let us remember that Jehovah gives us the honor and responsibility to care for those who have lost their mate in death. w19.06 24 ¶16

^ (Jas. 1:27) The form of worship* that is clean and undefiled from the standpoint of our God and Father is this: to look after orphans and widows in their tribulation, and to keep oneself without spot from the world.

Or “religion.”

^ (Ruth 1:16, 17) But Ruth said: “Do not plead with me to abandon you, to turn back from accompanying you; for where you go I will go, and where you spend the night, I will spend the night. Your people will be my people, and your God my God. 17 Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May Jehovah do so to me and add to it if anything but death should separate me from you.”

Monday, March 8

I will guard my mouth with a muzzle as long as anyone wicked is in my presence.—[Ps. 39:1].

During a ban, we must recognize when it is “time to be silent.” ([Eccl. 3:7]) We must safeguard sensitive information, such as the names of our brothers and sisters, the locations where we meet, how we carry out our ministry, and how we receive spiritual food. We would not reveal these facts to the secular authorities; nor would we share them with well-meaning friends or relatives in our country or in other countries. If we did fall into this trap, we would put the safety of our brothers at risk. Do not allow minor issues to divide us. Satan knows that a divided house cannot stand. (Mark 3:24, 25) He will constantly try to cause divisions among us. In that way, he hopes that we will start fighting one another instead of fighting him. Even mature Christians need to be on guard not to fall into this trap. If we work hard to overcome differences with our brothers, we will avoid the trap of disunity.—Col. 3:13, 14. w19.07 11-12 ¶14-16

^ (Ps. 39:1) I said: “I will guard my step To avoid sinning with my tongue. I will guard my mouth with a muzzle As long as anyone wicked is in my presence.”

^ (Eccl. 3:7) A time to rip apart and a time to sew together; A time to be silent and a time to speak;

^ (Mark 3:24, 25) If a kingdom becomes divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand; 25 and if a house becomes divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand.

^ (Col. 3:13, 14) Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same. 14 But besides all these things, clothe yourselves with love, for it is a perfect bond of union.

See App. A5.

Thursday, March 11

This is what I continue praying, that your love may abound still more and more.—[Phil. 1:9].

When the apostle Paul, Silas, Luke, and Timothy arrived in the Roman colony of Philippi, they found many people who were interested in the Kingdom message. These four zealous brothers helped form a congregation, and all the disciples began meeting together, likely at the home of a hospitable believer named Lydia. ([Acts 16:40]) The young congregation soon faced a challenge. Satan stirred up enemies of the truth who fiercely opposed the preaching activity of these loyal Christians. Paul and Silas were arrested, beaten with rods, and imprisoned. After they were released from prison, they visited the new disciples and encouraged them. Then Paul, Silas, and Timothy left the city while Luke apparently remained there. How did the newly formed congregation fare? With the help of Jehovah’s spirit, the new believers forged ahead in Jehovah’s service. ([Phil. 2:12]) Paul had every reason to be proud of them! w19.08 8 ¶1-2

^ (Phil. 1:9) And this is what I continue praying, that your love may abound still more and more with accurate knowledge and full discernment;

^ (Acts 16:40) But they came out of the prison and went to the home of Lydʹi·a; and when they saw the brothers, they encouraged them and departed.

^ (Phil. 2:12) Consequently, my beloved ones, just as you have always obeyed, not only during my presence but now much more readily during my absence, keep working out your own salvation with fear and trembling.

Friday, March 12

The borrower is a slave to the lender.—[Prov. 22:7].

Have you moved recently? A move can be surprisingly costly, and it is easy to get into debt. To minimize the debt, beware of buying on credit things you do not really need. ([Prov. 22:3]) When we are under emotional pressure, as when caring for sick loved ones, we may find it difficult to decide how much debt to take on. In such situations, remember that “prayer and supplication” can help you to make wise decisions. In response to your prayers, Jehovah can grant you the peace that will “guard your hearts and your mental powers,” helping you to think things through calmly. (Phil. 4:6, 7;[1 Pet. 5:7]) Maintain good relationships. Share your feelings and experiences with good friends, especially those who may have experienced similar joys and challenges. Doing so can promote emotional healing. (Eccl. 4:9, 10) The friends you made before you moved will remain your friends. w19.08 22 ¶9-10

^ (Prov. 22:7) The rich one rules the poor, And the borrower is a slave to the lender.

^ (Prov. 22:3) The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*

Or “penalty.”

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:7) while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

^ (Eccl. 4:9, 10) Two are better than one because they have a good reward* for their hard work. 10 For if one of them falls, the other can help his partner up. But what will happen to the one who falls with no one to help him up?

Or “greater benefit.”

Monday, March 15

I have other sheep, which are not of this fold.—[John 10:16].

Throughout the Scriptures, we read of men and women of faith who were deeply influenced by holy spirit; yet they are not part of the 144,000. John the Baptist is one example. ([Matt. 11:11]) David is another. ([Acts 2:34]) They and countless others will be resurrected to life on a paradise earth. All of them—along with the great crowd—will have the opportunity to demonstrate their loyalty to Jehovah and his sovereignty. Never before in human history has God united millions of people from all nations. Whether our hope is to live in heaven or on earth, we need to help as many as possible to become part of the great crowd of “other sheep.” Soon, Jehovah will bring the foretold great tribulation that will destroy the governments and religions that have afflicted mankind. What an outstanding privilege lies before all members of the great crowd—to serve Jehovah on earth forever!—[Rev. 7:14]. w19.09 31 ¶18-19

^ (John 10:16) “And I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; those too I must bring in, and they will listen to my voice, and they will become one flock, one shepherd.

^ (Matt. 11:11) Truly I say to you, among those born of women, there has not been raised up anyone greater than John the Baptist, but a lesser person in the Kingdom of the heavens is greater than he is.

^ (Acts 2:34) For David did not ascend to the heavens, but he himself says, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

Tuesday, March 16

In the last days ridiculers will come with their ridicule.—[2 Pet. 3:3].

As Satan’s system nears its end, we can expect to face ever more difficult tests of loyalty to God and his Kingdom. We will likely continue to be the target of ridicule. This may especially happen as our neutrality is tested more and more. We must strengthen our loyalty now so that we will remain loyal during the great tribulation. During the great tribulation, a change will take place regarding the brothers who take the lead on earth. At some point, all anointed ones who are still on earth will be gathered to heaven to share in the war of Armageddon. ([Matt. 24:31;] Rev. 2:26, 27) This means that the Governing Body will no longer be with us on earth. However, the great crowd will remain organized. Capable brothers from among the other sheep will take the lead. We will need to show our loyalty by supporting these brothers and by following their God-given direction. Our survival will depend on it! w19.10 17 ¶13-14

^ (2 Pet. 3:3) First of all know this, that in the last days ridiculers will come with their ridicule, proceeding according to their own desires

^ (Matt. 24:31) And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

^ (Rev. 2:26, 27) And to the one who conquers and observes my deeds down to the end, I will give authority over the nations, 27 and he will shepherd the people with an iron rod so that they will be broken to pieces like clay vessels, just as I have received from my Father.

Wednesday, March 17

Where you go I will go . . . Where you die I will die.—Ruth 1:16, 17.

Naomi was a loyal woman who loved Jehovah. But after the death of her husband and two sons, she wanted to change her name from Naomi to “Mara,” meaning “Bitter.” ([Ruth 1:3,][5,][20], ftn., [21]) Naomi’s daughter-in-law Ruth stuck with her through her trials. Ruth not only provided practical help but also spoke consolingly to Naomi. Ruth expressed her love and support for Naomi in simple, sincere words. When a member of our spiritual family loses a marriage mate in death, he or she needs our support. A married couple can be likened to two trees that have grown up next to each other. Over the years, the roots of the trees intertwine. When one tree is uprooted and dies, the other tree can seriously be affected. Similarly, when someone loses a spouse to the enemy death, he or she may feel strong emotions for a long time. w19.06 23 ¶12-13

^ (Ruth 1:16, 17) But Ruth said: “Do not plead with me to abandon you, to turn back from accompanying you; for where you go I will go, and where you spend the night, I will spend the night. Your people will be my people, and your God my God. 17 Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May Jehovah do so to me and add to it if anything but death should separate me from you.”

^ (Ruth 1:3) After some time E·limʹe·lech, Na·oʹmi’s husband, died, and she was left with her two sons.

^ (Ruth 1:5) Then the two sons, Mahʹlon and Chilʹi·on, also died, and the woman was left without her two children and her husband.

^ (Ruth 1:20) She would say to the women: “Do not call me Na·oʹmi.* Call me Maʹra,* for the Almighty has made life very bitter for me.

Meaning “My Pleasantness.”

Meaning “Bitter.”

^ (Ruth 1:21) I was full when I went, but Jehovah made me return empty-handed. Why should you call me Na·oʹmi, when it is Jehovah who opposed me and the Almighty who caused me calamity?”

Sunday, March 21

Children are an inheritance from Jehovah.—[Ps. 127:3], ftn.

A child requires and deserves considerable time and energy from each parent. So if a couple have a number of children who are close in age, the parents may find it challenging to give each child the needed attention. Some couples who had a number of young children confessed that they felt overwhelmed. A mother may struggle with feeling drained physically and emotionally. Could that have an impact on her being able to study, pray, and share in the ministry regularly? A related challenge is being able to pay attention during Christian meetings and to benefit from them. Of course, a loving husband will do what he can to support his wife when their children need attention, both at meetings and at home. For example, he could help his wife with household chores. He will work hard to ensure that all benefit from a regular Family Worship program. And Christian fathers will regularly accompany the family in field service. w19.12 24 ¶8

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

Tuesday, March 23

Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice.—[Prov. 27:11].

When faced with tests, Jesus prayed “with strong outcries and tears.” ([Heb. 5:7]) His fervent prayers flowed from a loyal heart and strengthened his desire to remain obedient. To Jehovah, Jesus’ prayers were like the aroma of sweet-smelling incense. Jesus’ entire life course deeply pleased his Father and vindicated His sovereignty. We can imitate Jesus by doing our best to live a life of integrity and of loyalty to Jehovah’s ways and laws. When faced with tests, we pray fervently for Jehovah’s help because we want to please him. We realize that Jehovah will not accept our prayers if we are involved in conduct that he condemns. However, if we live according to Jehovah’s standards, we can be confident that our heartfelt prayers will be like sweet-smelling incense to Jehovah. And we can be sure that our integrity and loyal obedience please our heavenly Father. w19.11 21-22 ¶7-8

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 9) Luke 19:29-44

^ (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ (Heb. 5:7) During his life on earth,* Christ offered up supplications and also petitions, with strong outcries and tears, to the One who was able to save him out of death, and he was favorably heard for his godly fear.

Lit., “In the days of his flesh.”

Wednesday, March 24

Who really is the faithful and discreet slave?—[Matt. 24:45].

In 1919, Jesus appointed a small group of anointed brothers as “the faithful and discreet slave.” That slave takes the lead in the preaching work and gives Christ’s followers “food at the proper time.” Satan and his world have done much to make the work of that faithful slave challenging, even impossible, to carry out from a human standpoint. Despite two world wars, relentless persecution, global economic crises, and unjust treatment, the faithful and discreet slave has continued to provide spiritual food for Christ’s followers on earth. Think of the abundance of spiritual food available today, free of charge, in more than 900 languages! It is undeniable evidence of divine backing. Consider further proof of Jehovah’s blessing: the preaching work. The good news truly is being preached “in all the inhabited earth.”—[Matt. 24:14]. w19.11 24 ¶15-16

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 10) Luke 19:45-48; Matthew 21:18, 19;[21:12, 13]

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Luke 19:45-48) Then he entered the temple and started to throw out those who were selling, 46 saying to them: “It is written, ‘My house will be a house of prayer,’ but you have made it a cave of robbers.” 47 He continued teaching daily in the temple. But the chief priests and the scribes and the principal ones of the people were seeking to kill him; 48 but they did not find any way to do this, for the people one and all kept hanging on to him to hear him.

^ (Matt. 21:18, 19) While returning to the city early in the morning, he felt hungry. 19 He caught sight of a fig tree by the road and went to it, but he found nothing on it except leaves, and he said to it: “Let no fruit come from you ever again.” And the fig tree withered instantly.

^ (Matt. 21:12, 13) Jesus entered the temple and threw out all those selling and buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves. 13 And he said to them: “It is written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer,’ but you are making it a cave of robbers.”

Memorial Date
After Sundown
Saturday, March 27

The spirit itself bears witness with our spirit that we are God’s children.—[Rom. 8:16].

How does a person know that he or she has the heavenly calling? The answer is clearly seen in the apostle Paul’s words to those in Rome who were “called to be holy ones.” In addition to the words of today’s text, he told them: “You did not receive a spirit of slavery causing fear again, but you received a spirit of adoption as sons, by which spirit we cry out: ‘Abba, Father!’” ([Rom. 1:7;][8:15]) So by means of his holy spirit, God makes it clear to anointed ones that they have this heavenly calling. (1 Thess. 2:12) Jehovah leaves no doubt whatsoever in the minds and hearts of those who receive his invitation to go to heaven. ([1 John 2:20,][27]) Anointed Christians do not need anyone to confirm that they are anointed. w20.01 22 ¶7-8

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 13) Luke 22:7-13; Mark 14:12-16 (Events after sunset: Nisan 14) Luke 22:14-65

^ (Rom. 8:16) The spirit itself bears witness with our spirit that we are God’s children.

^ (Rom. 1:7) to all those who are in Rome as God’s beloved ones, called to be holy ones: May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^ (Rom. 8:15) For you did not receive a spirit of slavery causing fear again, but you received a spirit of adoption as sons, by which spirit we cry out: “Abba, Father!”

^ (1 Thess. 2:12) so that you would go on walking worthily of God, who is calling you to his Kingdom and glory.

^ (1 John 2:20) And you have an anointing from the holy one, and all of you have knowledge.

^ (1 John 2:27) And as for you, the anointing that you received from him remains in you, and you do not need anyone to be teaching you; but the anointing from him is teaching you about all things and is true and is no lie. Just as it has taught you, remain in union with him.

^ (Luke 22:7-13) The day of the Unleavened Bread now arrived, on which the Passover sacrifice must be offered; 8 so Jesus sent Peter and John, saying: “Go and get the Passover ready for us to eat.” 9 They said to him: “Where do you want us to get it ready?” 10 He said to them: “Look! When you enter into the city, a man carrying an earthenware water jar will meet you. Follow him into the house that he enters. 11 And say to the landlord of the house, ‘The Teacher says to you: “Where is the guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’ 12 And that man will show you a large, furnished upper room. Get it ready there.” 13 So they left and found it just as he had told them, and they prepared for the Passover.

^ (Mark 14:12-16) Now on the first day of the Unleavened Bread, when they customarily offered up the Passover sacrifice, his disciples said to him: “Where do you want us to go and prepare for you to eat the Passover?” 13 With that he sent two of his disciples and said to them: “Go into the city, and a man carrying an earthenware water jar will meet you. Follow him, 14 and wherever he goes inside, say to the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’ 15 And he will show you a large upper room, furnished and ready. Prepare it for us there.” 16 So the disciples went out, and they entered the city and found it just as he said to them, and they prepared for the Passover.

Sunday, March 28

No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends.—[John 15:13].

“The law of the Christ” is built on the best possible foundation—love. ([Gal. 6:2]) Jesus was motivated by love in everything he did. Pity, or tender compassion, is an expression of love. Moved by such pity, Jesus taught the crowds, healed the sick, fed the hungry, and raised the dead. ([Matt. 14:14;][15:32-38;][Mark 6:34;] Luke 7:11-15) Jesus willingly put the needs of others ahead of his own. Above all, he showed great love by surrendering his life in behalf of others. We can imitate Jesus by putting the needs of others ahead of our own. We can also imitate him by cultivating tender compassion for people in our territory. When such compassion moves us to preach and teach the good news, we are obeying the law of the Christ. w19.05 4 ¶8-10

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 14) Luke 22:66-71

^ (John 15:13) No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends.

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (Matt. 14:14) When he came ashore, he saw a large crowd, and he felt pity for them, and he cured their sick ones.

^ (Matt. 15:32-38) But Jesus called his disciples to him and said: “I feel pity for the crowd, because they have already stayed with me for three days and they have had nothing to eat. I do not want to send them away hungry,* for they may give out on the road.” 33 However, the disciples said to him: “Where in this isolated place are we going to get enough bread to satisfy a crowd of this size?” 34 At this Jesus said to them: “How many loaves do you have?” They said: “Seven, and a few small fish.” 35 So after instructing the crowd to recline on the ground, 36 he took the seven loaves and the fish, and after offering thanks, he broke them and began giving them to the disciples, and the disciples gave them to the crowds. 37 And all ate and were satisfied, and they took up seven large baskets full of leftover fragments. 38 Now those eating were 4,000 men, as well as women and young children.

Or “without food; fasting.”

^ (Mark 6:34) Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

^ (Luke 7:11-15) Soon afterward he traveled to a city called Naʹin, and his disciples and a large crowd were traveling with him. 12 As he got near the gate of the city, why look! there was a dead man being carried out, the only son of his mother. Besides, she was a widow. A considerable crowd from the city was also with her. 13 When the Lord caught sight of her, he was moved with pity for her, and he said to her: “Stop weeping.” 14 With that he approached and touched the bier,* and the bearers stood still. Then he said: “Young man, I say to you, get up!”* 15 And the dead man sat up and started to speak, and Jesus gave him to his mother.

Or “funeral stretcher.”

Or “wake up!”

^ (Luke 22:66-71) And when it became day, the assembly of elders of the people, both chief priests and scribes, gathered together, and they led him into their Sanʹhe·drin hall and said: 67 “If you are the Christ, tell us.” But he said to them: “Even if I told you, you would not believe it at all. 68 Moreover, if I questioned you, you would not answer. 69 However, from now on the Son of man will be seated at the powerful right hand of God.” 70 At this they all said: “Are you, therefore, the Son of God?” He said to them: “You yourselves are saying that I am.” 71 They said: “Why do we need further testimony? For we ourselves have heard it out of his own mouth.”

Tuesday, March 30

You were sealed by means of him with the promised holy spirit, which is a token in advance of our inheritance.—Eph. 1:13, 14; ftn.

Jehovah uses his holy spirit to make it absolutely clear to all who are anointed Christians that he has chosen them. In this way, the holy spirit is “a token [a pledge or promise]” given to assure them that in the future they will live forever in heaven and not on earth. (2 Cor. 1:21, 22) If a Christian is anointed, will he automatically receive his heavenly reward? No. He is sure that he has been chosen to go to heaven. However, he must remember this admonition: “Brothers, be all the more diligent to make your calling and choosing sure for yourselves, for if you keep on doing these things, you will by no means ever fail.” ([2 Pet. 1:10]) So even though an anointed Christian has been called to go to heaven, he will get his reward only if he remains faithful.—Phil. 3:12-14;[Heb. 3:1;][Rev. 2:10]. w20.01 21-22 ¶5-6

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 16) Luke 24:1-12

^ (Eph. 1:13, 14) But you also hoped in him after you heard the word of truth, the good news about your salvation. After you believed, you were sealed by means of him with the promised holy spirit, 14 which is a token in advance* of our inheritance, for the purpose of releasing God’s own possession by a ransom, to his glorious praise.

Or “a down payment (earnest money); a guarantee (pledge) of what is to come.”

^ (2 Cor. 1:21, 22) But the one who guarantees that you and we belong to Christ and the one who anointed us is God. 22 He has also put his seal on us and has given us the token of what is to come, that is, the spirit, in our hearts.

^ (2 Pet. 1:10) Therefore, brothers, be all the more diligent to make your calling and choosing sure for yourselves, for if you keep on doing these things, you will by no means ever fail.

^ (Phil. 3:12-14) Not that I have already received it or am already made perfect, but I am pressing on to see if I may also lay hold on that for which Christ Jesus selected me.* 13 Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having taken hold of it; but one thing is certain: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, 14 I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus.

Lit., “laid hold on me.”

^ (Heb. 3:1) Consequently, holy brothers, partakers of the heavenly calling,* consider the apostle and high priest whom we acknowledge*—Jesus.

Or “invitation.”

Or “confess.”

^ (Rev. 2:10) Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of you into prison so that you may be fully put to the test, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life.

Saturday, April 3

Those whom Jehovah loves he disciplines.—[Heb. 12:6].

As part of our training, our loving Father disciplines us when necessary. He does so in many ways. For instance, something we read in his Word or hear at our meetings may correct us. Or perhaps the help we need comes from the elders. Regardless of the form it takes, Jehovah’s discipline is always motivated by love. ([Jer. 30:11]) Jehovah supports us through trials. Just as a caring human father supports his children during difficult times, our heavenly Father sustains us through trials. He uses his holy spirit to protect us from spiritual harm. ([Luke 11:13]) Jehovah also protects us emotionally. For example, he gives us a marvelous hope. That hope for the future helps us to endure difficulties. Consider this: No matter what bad things happen to us, our loving Father will undo any injury we suffer. Whatever trials we are facing, these are only temporary, but the blessings Jehovah gives are everlasting.—2 Cor. 4:16-18. w20.02 5 ¶14-15

^ (Heb. 12:6) for those whom Jehovah* loves he disciplines, in fact, he scourges* everyone whom he receives as a son.”

See App. A5.

Or “punishes.”

^ (Jer. 30:11) “For I am with you,” declares Jehovah, “to save you. But I will make an extermination among all the nations to which I scattered you; However, you I will not exterminate. I will discipline* you to the proper degree, And I will by no means leave you unpunished.”

Or “correct.”

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ (2 Cor. 4:16-18) Therefore, we do not give up, but even if the man we are outside is wasting away, certainly the man we are inside is being renewed from day to day. 17 For though the tribulation is momentary and light, it works out for us a glory that is of more and more surpassing greatness* and is everlasting; 18 while we keep our eyes, not on the things seen, but on the things unseen. For the things seen are temporary, but the things unseen are everlasting.

Lit., “weight.”

Sunday, April 4

The spirit that has taken up residence within us keeps enviously longing.—[Jas. 4:5].

We can win the battle against envy! Consider the example of Joseph’s brothers. Years after they had mistreated Joseph, they met him in Egypt. Before Joseph revealed his real identity to his brothers, he tested them to find out if they had changed. He arranged a meal at which he gave the youngest brother, Benjamin, significantly more attention than he gave the others. (Gen. 43:33, 34) Yet, there is no indication that his brothers became envious of Benjamin. Instead, they showed genuine concern for their brother and for their father, Jacob. (Gen. 44:30-34) Because Joseph’s brothers had let go of envy, they were able to help restore peace in their family. ([Gen. 45:4,][15]) Similarly, if we uproot any feelings of envy, we will help to keep our family and our congregation peaceful. Jehovah wants us to fight envy and to pursue peace. If we cultivate humility, contentment, and appreciation, we will leave no room for envy. w20.02 19 ¶17-18

^ (Jas. 4:5) Or do you think that for no reason the scripture says: “The spirit that has taken up residence within us keeps enviously longing”?

^ (Gen. 43:33, 34) The brothers* were seated before him, the firstborn according to his right as firstborn and the youngest according to his youth, and they kept looking at one another in amazement. 34 He kept sending portions of food from his table to theirs, but he increased Benjamin’s portion five times the size of the portions of all the others. So they continued banqueting and drinking with him to the full.

Lit., “They.”

^ (Gen. 44:30-34) “And now if I return to your slave my father without the boy along with us, since his own life* is bound up with this one’s life,* 31 then as soon as he sees that the boy is not there, he will die, and your slaves will indeed bring down the gray hairs of your slave our father to the Grave* in grief. 32 Your slave gave a guarantee to my father for the boy, saying, ‘If I fail to bring him back to you, then I will have sinned against my father forever.’ 33 So now, please, let your slave stay instead of the boy as my master’s slave, in order that the boy may return with his brothers. 34 How can I return to my father without the boy along with me? I could not bear looking on when this calamity befalls my father!”

Or “soul.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Gen. 45:4) So Joseph said to his brothers: “Come close to me, please.” With that they came close to him. Then he said: “I am Joseph your brother, whom you sold into Egypt.

^ (Gen. 45:15) And he kissed all his brothers and wept over them, and after that his brothers spoke with him.

Wednesday, April 7

All those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted.—[2 Tim. 3:12].

In 2018, more than 223,000 publishers of the good news lived in lands where our spiritual activities were banned or severely restricted. This is not surprising. True Christians expect to be persecuted. No matter where we live, secular authorities may suddenly and unexpectedly ban us from worshipping our loving God, Jehovah. If a government bans our worship, we might wrongly conclude that we do not have God’s blessing. But remember, persecution does not mean that Jehovah is unhappy with us. Take, for example, the apostle Paul. He certainly had God’s approval. He had the privilege of writing 14 letters of the Christian Greek Scriptures, and he was an apostle to the nations. Yet, he faced intense persecution. (2 Cor. 11:23-27) We learn from the apostle Paul’s experience that Jehovah allows his faithful servants to be persecuted. w19.07 8 ¶1, 3

^ (2 Tim. 3:12) In fact, all those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted.

^ (2 Cor. 11:23-27) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths. 24 Five times I received 40 strokes less one from the Jews, 25 three times I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, three times I experienced shipwreck, a night and a day I have spent in the open sea; 26 in journeys often, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from my own people, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers among false brothers, 27 in labor and toil, in sleepless nights often, in hunger and thirst, frequently without food, in cold and lacking clothing.

Friday, April 9

Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak.—[Jas. 1:19].

When dealing with a distressed person, are we a good listener? It involves more than staying still and saying nothing. We can show sympathy and tender compassion while listening. At times, a few tactful, warm words may show how we feel. You might say: “I am so sorry that happened to you!” Perhaps you could ask a question or two to make sure you understand what the anguished friend is saying. You might ask, “Can you please help me understand what you mean?” or “When you said that, I concluded . . . Did I get it right?” Such loving expressions may assure the person that you are truly listening, trying to make sure that you understand. ([1 Cor. 13:4,][7]) Be careful, though, to remain “slow to speak.” Do not interrupt to give advice or to correct the person’s thinking. And be patient! Rather than trying to provide solutions, we offer sympathy and tender compassion.—[1 Pet. 3:8]. w19.05 17-18 ¶15-17

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

^ (1 Cor. 13:4) Love is patient and kind. Love is not jealous. It does not brag, does not get puffed up,

^ (1 Cor. 13:7) It bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

Monday, April 12

I am . . . under great stress.—[1 Sam. 1:15].

Sometimes, we must face a number of stressful problems at the same time. Consider the following examples. A Witness named John, who suffers from multiple sclerosis, was devastated when his wife abandoned him after 19 years of marriage. Then his two daughters stopped serving Jehovah. A couple named Bob and Linda faced a different set of challenges. They both lost their jobs, and then they lost their home. In addition to those problems, Linda was diagnosed with a potentially fatal heart-related illness, and another disease began to damage her immune system. We can be sure that our Creator and loving Father, Jehovah, understands how stress affects us. And he wants to help us deal with the challenges we face. ([Phil. 4:6, 7]) God’s Word contains many accounts that describe the challenges his servants endured. It also records how Jehovah helped them deal with those stressful situations. w19.06 14 ¶2-3

^ (1 Sam. 1:15) At this Hanʹnah answered: “No, my lord! I am a woman under great stress;* I have not drunk wine or anything alcoholic, but I am pouring out my soul* before Jehovah.

Or “a woman hard-pressed in spirit.”

See Glossary.

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Wednesday, April 14

Jehovah is my helper; I will not be afraid.—[Heb. 13:6].

Many years ago, The Watchtower observed: “The person who knows God best will trust him the most in time of test.” How true! To face persecution successfully, we must love Jehovah and trust in him completely. (Matt. 22:36-38;[Jas. 5:11]) Read the Bible daily with the goal of drawing closer to Jehovah. ([Jas. 4:8]) As you read, focus on Jehovah’s tender qualities. Feel his love and affection expressed in the things he says and does. ([Ex. 34:6]) Some may struggle to believe that God loves them because they have never been shown love. If you face that challenge, try making a list each day of ways that Jehovah has shown mercy and kindness to you. (Ps. 78:38, 39;[Rom. 8:32]) As you consider your own experiences and meditate on what you have read in God’s Word, you will likely be able to list many things that Jehovah has done for you. The more you appreciate what Jehovah does, the stronger your bond with him will be.—[Ps. 116:1, 2]. w19.07 2-3 ¶4-5

^ (Heb. 13:6) So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

^ (Matt. 22:36-38) “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment.

^ (Jas. 5:11) Look! We consider happy* those who have endured. You have heard of the endurance of Job and have seen the outcome Jehovah* gave, that Jehovah* is very tender in affection* and merciful.

Or “blessed.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

Or “very compassionate.”

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Ex. 34:6) Jehovah was passing before him and declaring: “Jehovah, Jehovah, a God merciful and compassionate,* slow to anger and abundant in loyal love* and truth,*

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

Or “faithfulness.”

^ (Ps. 78:38, 39) But he was merciful; He would forgive* their error and not bring them to ruin. He often held back his anger Instead of stirring up all his wrath. 39 For he remembered that they were flesh, A wind that blows past and does not return.*

Lit., “cover.”

Or possibly, “That the spirit is going forth and does not come back.”

^ (Rom. 8:32) Since he did not even spare his own Son but handed him over for us all, will he not also, along with him, kindly give us all other things?

^ (Ps. 116:1, 2) I love Jehovah Because he hears* my voice, my pleas for help.  2 For he inclines his ear* to me, And I will call on him as long as I live.*

Or possibly, “I love because Jehovah hears.”

Or “bends down to listen.”

Lit., “in my days.”

Friday, April 16

The thoughts of a man’s heart are like deep waters, but the discerning man draws them out.—[Prov. 20:5].

When preaching, we must try to understand the factors that have influenced the people we meet. The apostle Paul grew up among Jews. He surely had to adapt his preaching to Gentiles, people who knew little or nothing about Jehovah and the Scriptures. We might have to do some research so that we can empathize with and understand the people in our territory. (1 Cor. 9:20-23) Our goal is to find “deserving” ones. ([Matt. 10:11]) To be effective, we must invite people to express their opinions and then listen attentively. A brother in England asks people for their opinion about how to have a happy marriage, how to raise children, or how to cope with injustice. After listening to their comments, he says, “What do you think of this advice written nearly 2,000 years ago?” Then, without saying the word “Bible,” he shows them well-chosen scriptures on his phone. w19.07 21-22 ¶7-8

^ (Prov. 20:5) The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

^ (1 Cor. 9:20-23) To the Jews I became as a Jew in order to gain Jews; to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, in order to gain those under law. 21 To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ, in order to gain those without law. 22 To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some. 23 But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

^ (Matt. 10:11) “Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving, and stay there until you leave.

Wednesday, April 21

Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you.—[Jas. 4:8].

Meetings help us to draw closer to Jehovah. Our attitude toward attending meetings is a good indicator of how successful we will be at dealing with persecution in the future. (Heb. 10:24, 25) Why so? If we allow small obstacles to keep us from attending meetings now, what will happen in the future if we have to risk our safety to meet with fellow believers? On the other hand, if we develop a firm resolve to attend meetings, we will not give in when opposers try to stop us from gathering together. Now is the time to develop a love for our meetings. When we love to attend meetings, no opposition, not even a government ban, will stop us from obeying God rather than men. ([Acts 5:29]) Memorize your favorite scriptures. ([Matt. 13:52]) Your memory may not be perfect, but Jehovah can use his powerful holy spirit to bring those scriptures back to your mind. ([John 14:26]) Those scriptures will help you to stay close to Jehovah—and to endure faithfully. w19.07 3 ¶5; 4 ¶8-9

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Acts 5:29) In answer Peter and the other apostles said: “We must obey God as ruler rather than men.

^ (Matt. 13:52) Then he said to them: “That being the case, every public instructor who is taught about the Kingdom of the heavens is like a man, the master of the house, who brings out of his treasure store things both new and old.”

^ (John 14:26) But the helper, the holy spirit, which the Father will send in my name, that one will teach you all things and bring back to your minds all the things I told you.

Saturday, April 24

The whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.—[1 John 5:19].

The Devil controls this system of things, and he uses it to appeal to our natural human desires and fleshly weaknesses. ([Eph. 2:1-3]) His goal is to divide our affections so that we are not exclusively devoted to Jehovah. After writing about the end of Satan’s world and the new world to come, the apostle Peter stated: “Beloved ones, since you are awaiting these things, do your utmost to be found finally by him spotless and unblemished and in peace.” ([2 Pet. 3:14]) When we obey that counsel and do our best to remain morally and spiritually clean, we prove that we are exclusively devoted to Jehovah. Satan and his system will continue to tempt us to change our priorities. ([Luke 4:13]) But despite any challenges we face, we will not allow anyone or anything to take Jehovah’s place in our heart. We are determined to give Jehovah what he alone deserves—our exclusive devotion! w19.10 27 ¶4; 31 ¶18-19

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (Eph. 2:1-3) Furthermore, God made you alive, though you were dead in your trespasses and sins, 2 in which you at one time walked according to the system of things* of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience. 3 Yes, among them we all at one time conducted ourselves in harmony with the desires of our flesh, carrying out the will of the flesh and of our thoughts, and we were naturally children of wrath just as the rest.

Or “the course.”

^ (2 Pet. 3:14) Therefore, beloved ones, since you are awaiting these things, do your utmost to be found finally by him spotless and unblemished and in peace.

^ (Luke 4:13) So the Devil, having finished all the temptation, departed from him until another convenient time.

Sunday, April 25

I was troubled by my sin.—[Ps. 38:18].

Some types of anxiety are good. For example, we are properly concerned about pleasing Jehovah and Jesus. ([1 Cor. 7:32]) If we commit a serious sin, we are anxious to restore our friendship with God. We are also anxious to please our marriage mate and to care for the welfare of our family members and fellow believers. ([1 Cor. 7:33;] 2 Cor. 11:28) On the other hand, undue anxiety may cause us to constantly worry about having enough food and clothing. (Matt. 6:31, 32) To ease that worry, we might focus on gaining material possessions. If we allow that to happen, our faith in Jehovah will become weak and we will suffer serious spiritual harm. ([Mark 4:19;][1 Tim. 6:10]) Or we might fall victim to becoming overly concerned about gaining the approval of others. We may then fear being ridiculed or persecuted by men more than we fear displeasing Jehovah. To protect ourselves from that danger, we must beg Jehovah to give us the faith and courage we need to face the challenge.—[Prov. 29:25;][Luke 17:5]. w19.11 15 ¶6-7

^ (Ps. 38:18) I confessed my error; I was troubled by my sin.

^ (1 Cor. 7:32) Indeed, I want you to be free from anxiety. The unmarried man is anxious for the things of the Lord, how he may gain the Lord’s approval.

^ (1 Cor. 7:33) But the married man is anxious for the things of the world, how he may gain the approval of his wife,

^ (2 Cor. 11:28) Besides those things of an external kind, there is what rushes in on me from day to day:* the anxiety for all the congregations.

Or “the daily pressure on me.”

^ (Matt. 6:31, 32) So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things.

^ (Mark 4:19) but the anxieties of this system of things and the deceptive power of riches* and the desires for everything else make inroads and choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful.

Or “the seductiveness (deceptive pleasure) of being wealthy.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:10) For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ (Prov. 29:25) Trembling at* men is* a snare, But the one trusting in Jehovah will be protected.

Or “Fear of.”

Or “lays.”

^ (Luke 17:5) Now the apostles said to the Lord: “Give us more faith.”

Wednesday, April 28

We mustered up boldness by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.—[1 Thess. 2:2].

To face persecution, you need courage. If you feel that you lack that quality, what can you do? Remember that true courage does not depend on your size, strength, or ability. Consider the example of young David when he faced Goliath. Compared with that giant, David was smaller, weaker, and poorly armed. David did not even have a sword. Yet, he was full of courage. David boldly ran to fight that arrogant giant. Why was David so courageous? He firmly believed that Jehovah was with him. (1 Sam. 17:37,[45-47]) David did not concentrate on how big Goliath was compared with him. Instead, he focused on how tiny Goliath was compared to Jehovah. What do we learn from this account? We will feel courageous if we are confident that Jehovah is with us and if we are certain that our opposers are tiny in comparison to Almighty God.—2 Chron. 20:15;[Ps. 16:8]. w19.07 5 ¶11-13

^ (1 Thess. 2:2) For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness* by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.*

Or “courage.”

Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

^ (1 Sam. 17:37) Then David added: “Jehovah, who rescued me from the claws of the lion and the bear, he is the one who will rescue me from the hand of this Phi·lisʹtine.” At this Saul said to David: “Go, and may Jehovah be with you.”

^ (1 Sam. 17:45-47) David replied to the Phi·lisʹtine: “You are coming against me with sword and spear and javelin, but I am coming against you in the name of Jehovah of armies, the God of the battle line of Israel, whom you have taunted.* 46 This very day Jehovah will surrender you into my hand, and I will strike you down and cut off your head; and on this day I will give the corpses of the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines to the birds of the heavens and to the wild beasts of the earth; and people of all the earth will know that there is a God in Israel. 47 And all those gathered here* will know that it is not with the sword or the spear that Jehovah saves, for the battle belongs to Jehovah, and he will give all of you into our hand.”

Or “challenged.”

Lit., “all this congregation.”

^ (2 Chron. 20:15) He said: “Pay attention, all Judah and you inhabitants of Jerusalem and King Je·hoshʹa·phat! Here is what Jehovah says to you, ‘Do not be afraid or be terrified because of this large crowd, for the battle is not yours but God’s.

^ (Ps. 16:8) I keep Jehovah before me constantly. Because he is at my right hand, I will never be shaken.*

Or “will never stagger (totter).”

Friday, April 30

It is to us God has revealed them.—[1 Cor. 2:10].

Perhaps you are wondering if you have been anointed by holy spirit. If so, think about these important questions: Do you have a burning desire to do Jehovah’s will? Do you feel that you are especially zealous in the preaching work? Are you a keen student of God’s Word who loves to learn about “the deep things of God”? Do you feel that Jehovah has given you wonderful results in the preaching work? Do you have a deep inner feeling of responsibility to help others spiritually? Have you seen proof that Jehovah has helped you in many specific ways in your life? If you answer these questions with a resounding yes, does this prove that you now have the heavenly calling? No, it does not. Why not? Because all of God’s servants can feel this way. In fact, if you are wondering whether you have been anointed by holy spirit, such doubt in itself would mean that you have not been. Those called by Jehovah do not wonder whether they have been anointed or not! They know! w20.01 23 ¶14

^ (1 Cor. 2:10) For it is to us God has revealed them through his spirit, for the spirit searches into all things, even the deep things of God.

Monday, May 3

When anxieties overwhelmed me, you comforted and soothed me.—[Ps. 94:19].

Have you ever been plagued by anxiety? Perhaps it was because of what others have said or done or because of what you have said or done. For example, you may have made a mistake, and you worry that Jehovah will never forgive you. To make matters worse, you may believe that because you are overwhelmed by anxiety, you must lack faith—you must be a bad person. Consider, though, a few Scriptural examples. Hannah, the prophet Samuel’s mother, was a woman of great faith. Yet, she was overcome by anxiety when a member of her household treated her badly. ([1 Sam. 1:7]) The apostle Paul had strong faith, but he was overwhelmed with “anxiety for all the congregations.” ([2 Cor. 11:28]) King David had such strong faith that Jehovah developed a special fondness for him. ([Acts 13:22]) Even so, David made mistakes that caused him to suffer bouts of crushing anxiety. ([Ps. 38:4]) Jehovah comforted and soothed each one of them. w20.02 20 ¶1-2

^ (Ps. 94:19) When anxieties* overwhelmed me,* You comforted and soothed me.*

Or “disquieting thoughts.”

Or “became many inside of me.”

Or “Your consolations soothed my soul.”

^ (1 Sam. 1:7) That is what she would do year after year; whenever Hanʹnah went up to the house of Jehovah, her rival would taunt her so much that she would weep and not eat.

^ (2 Cor. 11:28) Besides those things of an external kind, there is what rushes in on me from day to day:* the anxiety for all the congregations.

Or “the daily pressure on me.”

^ (Acts 13:22) After removing him, he raised up for them David as king, about whom he bore witness and said: ‘I have found David the son of Jesʹse a man agreeable to my heart; he will do all the things I desire.’

^ (Ps. 38:4) For my errors loom over my head; Like a heavy burden, they are too much for me to bear.

Saturday, May 8

Watch that among you there is no one who is sexually immoral.—[Heb. 12:16].

Jehovah God hates all forms of wickedness. ([Ps. 5:4-6]) How he must hate child sexual abuse—an especially repugnant wicked deed! In imitation of Jehovah, we as his Witnesses abhor child abuse and do not tolerate it in the Christian congregation. ([Rom. 12:9]) Any act of child abuse is absolutely opposed to “the law of the Christ”! ([Gal. 6:2]) All that Jesus taught both by word and by example is built on love and promotes justice. Governed by this law, true Christians treat children in a way that makes them feel safe and genuinely loved. But child abuse is a selfish, unjust act that makes a child feel unsafe and unloved. Sadly, true Christians have been affected by it. Why? “Wicked men and impostors” abound, and some may try to enter the congregation. ([2 Tim. 3:13]) In addition, some professing to be a part of the congregation have succumbed to perverted fleshly desires and have sexually abused children. w19.05 8 ¶1-3

^ (Heb. 12:16) and watch that among you there is no one who is sexually immoral* nor anyone who does not appreciate sacred things, like Eʹsau, who gave up his rights as firstborn in exchange for one meal.

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

^ (Ps. 5:4-6) For you are not a God who takes pleasure in wickedness; No one bad may remain with you.  5 No arrogant person may stand in your presence. You hate all those who behave wickedly;  6 You will destroy those who speak lies. Jehovah detests violent and deceptive people.*

Or “a man of bloodshed and deception.”

^ (Rom. 12:9) Let your love be without hypocrisy. Abhor what is wicked; cling to what is good.

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

Tuesday, May 11

It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life away.—[1 Ki. 19:4].

Elijah became afraid when Queen Jezebel threatened to kill him. So he fled to the area of Beer-sheba. He became so discouraged that “he asked that he might die.” What made him feel that way? Elijah was an imperfect man, “a man with feelings like ours.” ([Jas. 5:17]) Perhaps he felt overwhelmed by stress and physical exhaustion. It seems that Elijah thought that his efforts to promote pure worship had been futile, that nothing in Israel had improved, and that he was the only one still serving Jehovah. (1 Ki. 18:3, 4,[13;][19:10,][14]) Jehovah understood Elijah’s feelings and did not scold him for expressing them. Instead, he helped Elijah regain strength. ([1 Ki. 19:5-7]) Later, Jehovah kindly adjusted Elijah’s thinking by demonstrating His awesome power. Jehovah then pointed out that he still had 7,000 in Israel who refused to worship Baal. (1 Ki. 19:11-18) In practical ways, Jehovah showed Elijah that He loved him. w19.06 15-16 ¶5-6

^ (1 Ki. 19:4) He went a day’s journey into the wilderness and came and sat down under a broom tree, and he asked that he* might die. He said: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life* away, for I am no better than my forefathers.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Jas. 5:17) E·liʹjah was a man with feelings like ours, and yet when he prayed earnestly for it not to rain, it did not rain on the land for three years and six months.

^ (1 Ki. 18:3, 4) Meanwhile, Aʹhab called O·ba·diʹah, who was over the household. (Now O·ba·diʹah greatly feared Jehovah, 4 and when Jezʹe·bel was doing away with* Jehovah’s prophets, O·ba·diʹah took 100 prophets and hid them 50 to a cave, and he supplied them with bread and water.)

Lit., “cutting off.”

^ (1 Ki. 18:13) Has my lord not been told what I did when Jezʹe·bel was killing the prophets of Jehovah, how I hid 100 of the prophets of Jehovah by groups of 50 in a cave and kept supplying them bread and water?

^ (1 Ki. 19:10) To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life* away.”

Or “soul.”

^ (1 Ki. 19:14) To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life* away.”

Or “soul.”

^ (1 Ki. 19:5-7) Then he lay down and fell asleep under the broom tree. But suddenly an angel touched him and said to him: “Get up and eat.” 6 When he looked, there at his head was a round loaf on heated stones and a jug of water. He ate and drank and lay down again. 7 Later the angel of Jehovah came back a second time and touched him and said: “Get up and eat, for the journey will be too much for you.”

^ (1 Ki. 19:11-18) But He said: “Go out and stand on the mountain before Jehovah.” And look! Jehovah was passing by, and a great and strong wind was splitting mountains and breaking crags before Jehovah, but Jehovah was not in the wind. After the wind, there was an earthquake, but Jehovah was not in the earthquake. 12 After the earthquake, there was a fire, but Jehovah was not in the fire. After the fire, there was a calm, low voice. 13 As soon as E·liʹjah heard it, he wrapped his face in his official garment and went out and stood at the entrance of the cave. Then a voice asked him: “What are you doing here, E·liʹjah?” 14 To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life* away.” 15 Jehovah said to him: “Return, and go to the wilderness of Damascus. When you arrive, anoint Hazʹa·el as king over Syria. 16 And you should anoint Jeʹhu the grandson of Nimʹshi as king over Israel, and you should anoint E·liʹsha* the son of Shaʹphat from Aʹbel-me·hoʹlah as prophet to take your place. 17 Anyone escaping from Hazʹa·el’s sword, Jeʹhu will put to death; and anyone escaping from Jeʹhu’s sword, E·liʹsha will put to death. 18 And I still have left 7,000 in Israel, all whose knees have not bent down to Baʹal and whose mouths have not kissed him.”

Or “soul.”

Meaning “God Is Salvation.”

Thursday, May 13

All those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted.—[2 Tim. 3:12].

On the night before our Lord Jesus was put to death, he said that all who choose to be his disciples will be hated. ([John 17:14]) Up until now, faithful Christian Witnesses of Jehovah have been persecuted by those who oppose true worship. As the end of this system of things draws closer, we expect our enemies to oppose us even more. ([Matt. 24:9]) How can we prepare ourselves now to face persecution? We do not need to imagine all the things that could happen to us. If we did, we could be overwhelmed with fear and anxiety. We could allow imagined threats to defeat us even before any real test comes. ([Prov. 12:25;][17:22]) Fear is a powerful weapon that our “adversary, the Devil,” tries to use against us. (1 Pet. 5:8, 9) It is vital, then, that we strengthen our bond with Jehovah and do it now. w19.07 2 ¶1-3

^ (2 Tim. 3:12) In fact, all those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted.

^ (John 17:14) I have given your word to them, but the world has hated them, because they are no part of the world, just as I am no part of the world.

^ (Matt. 24:9) “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name.

^ (Prov. 12:25) Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up.

Or “depresses him.”

^ (Prov. 17:22) A joyful heart is good medicine,* But a crushed spirit saps one’s strength.*

Or “good for healing.”

Or “dries up the bones.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:8, 9) Keep your senses, be watchful! Your adversary, the Devil, walks about like a roaring lion, seeking to devour someone.* 9 But take your stand against him, firm in the faith, knowing that the same kind of sufferings are being experienced by the entire association of your brothers* in the world.

Or “looking for someone to devour.”

Lit., “by your brotherhood.”

Friday, May 14

Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations.—[Matt. 28:19].

The apostles must have been full of anticipation as they gathered on a mountainside. Jesus had, after his resurrection, arranged for them to meet him at that location. ([Matt. 28:16]) That was perhaps the occasion when “he appeared to more than 500 brothers at one time.” ([1 Cor. 15:6]) Why had Jesus called his disciples to this meeting? To give them an exciting mission: “Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations.” (Matt. 28:18-20) The disciples who heard Jesus’ words became part of the first-century Christian congregation. The primary mission of that congregation was to make more disciples of Christ. Today, there are tens of thousands of true Christian congregations throughout the earth, and the primary mission of those congregations remains the same. w19.07 14 ¶1-2

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Matt. 28:16) However, the 11 disciples went to Galʹi·lee to the mountain where Jesus had arranged for them to meet.

^ (1 Cor. 15:6) After that he appeared to more than 500 brothers at one time, most of whom are still with us, though some have fallen asleep in death.

^ (Matt. 28:18-20) Jesus approached and spoke to them, saying: “All authority has been given me in heaven and on the earth. 19 Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Saturday, May 15

The earth remains forever.—[Eccl. 1:4].

A traveling overseer in Norway says that people who are not inclined to talk about God are often willing to talk about world conditions. After greeting people, he says: “What do you think about our prospects for a better future? Does our best hope lie with politicians, scientists, or someone else?” After listening carefully, he reads or quotes a scripture that points to a bright future. Some are intrigued by the Bible’s promise that the earth will last forever and that good people will live on it eternally. ([Ps. 37:29]) We do well to use a variety of approaches with those we meet. Why? Because what attracts one may repel another. Some do not mind discussing God or the Bible, while others respond better to a more indirect approach. In either case, we should take the opportunity to speak to all sorts of people. ([Rom. 1:14-16]) Jehovah is the one who makes the truth grow in the hearts of those who are righteously inclined.—1 Cor. 3:6, 7. w19.07 22-23 ¶10-11

^ (Eccl. 1:4) A generation is going, and a generation is coming, But the earth remains* forever.

Lit., “is standing.”

^ (Ps. 37:29) The righteous will possess the earth, And they will live forever on it.

^ (Rom. 1:14-16) Both to Greeks and to foreigners, both to wise and to senseless ones, I am a debtor; 15 so I am eager to declare the good news also to you there in Rome. 16 For I am not ashamed of the good news; it is, in fact, God’s power for salvation to everyone having faith, to the Jew first and also to the Greek.

^ (1 Cor. 3:6, 7) I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow, 7 so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow.

Monday, May 17

Go on carrying the burdens of one another.—[Gal. 6:2].

Commendably, many congregations and individuals do what they can to enable those in full-time service to remain in their assignments. They do so by encouraging them to continue their work, by giving them financial or other material support, or by helping them to care for their family members back home. If those in full-time service receive a new assignment to your congregation, do not view the change of assignment as an indication that they somehow failed or were disciplined. Instead, help them to make the transition easier. Give them a warm welcome and commend them for the work they have done, even if poor health limits what they can do at present. Get to know them. Learn from their wealth of knowledge, training, and experience. Initially, those receiving a new assignment may need your help to obtain housing, transportation, work, and other basic necessities. w19.08 23-24 ¶12-13

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

Wednesday, May 19

Keep in expectation of it! For it will without fail come true.—[Hab. 2:3].

We naturally long for the good things that Jehovah has promised. However, when the fulfillment of our expectations appears to be delayed, it may dampen our enthusiasm. We could even lose heart. ([Prov. 13:12]) This happened at the beginning of the 20th century. At that time, many anointed Christians expected to receive their heavenly reward in 1914. When that did not happen, how did faithful ones deal with their delayed expectations? They did not give up the race for life, because their primary focus was on faithfully doing God’s will, not on gaining their reward. They were determined to run the race with endurance. No doubt you long to see Jehovah vindicate his name and sovereignty and fulfill all his promises. Be assured that these things will happen in Jehovah’s due time. Until then, may we keep busy serving our God, never allowing postponed expectations to discourage us or slow us down. w19.08 4-5 ¶9-10

^ (Hab. 2:3) For the vision is yet for its appointed time, And it is rushing toward its end,* and it will not lie. Even if it should delay,* keep in expectation of it!* For it will without fail come true. It will not be late!

Or “fulfillment.”

Or “if it seems to delay.”

Or “wait eagerly for it!”

^ (Prov. 13:12) Expectation* postponed makes the heart sick, But a desire realized is a tree of life.

Or “Hope.”

Thursday, May 20

I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart.—[Matt. 11:29].

Ask yourself: ‘Do I have a reputation for being mild-tempered and humble? Do I willingly do menial jobs to serve others? Am I kind to others?’ Jesus created a peaceful, inviting environment for his fellow workers, and he enjoyed training them. ([Luke 10:1,][19-21]) He encouraged his disciples to ask questions, and he wanted to hear their opinions. (Matt. 16:13-16) Much like plants in a greenhouse, the disciples flourished. They absorbed the lessons that Jesus taught and produced fruit in the form of good works. Do you have a position of authority? If so, ask yourself: ‘What kind of environment do I create at work or at home? Do I promote peace? Do I encourage others to ask questions? And am I willing to hear their opinions?’ Never would we want to be like the Pharisees, who resented those who questioned them and persecuted those who expressed an opinion contrary to their own.—[Mark 3:1-6;] John 9:29-34. w19.09 20 ¶1; 23 ¶9-11

^ (Matt. 11:29) Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (Luke 10:1) After these things the Lord designated 70 others and sent them out by twos ahead of him into every city and place where he himself was to go.

^ (Luke 10:19-21) Look! I have given you the authority to trample underfoot serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing at all will harm you. 20 Nevertheless, do not rejoice because the spirits are made subject to you, but rejoice because your names have been written in the heavens.” 21 In that very hour he became overjoyed in the holy spirit and said: “I publicly praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have carefully hidden these things from wise and intellectual ones and have revealed them to young children. Yes, O Father, because this is the way you approved.

^ (Matt. 16:13-16) When he had come into the region of Caes·a·reʹa Phi·lipʹpi, Jesus asked his disciples: “Who are men saying the Son of man is?” 14 They said: “Some say John the Baptist, others E·liʹjah, and still others Jeremiah or one of the prophets.” 15 He said to them: “You, though, who do you say I am?” 16 Simon Peter answered: “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”

^ (Mark 3:1-6) Once again he entered into a synagogue, and a man with a withered* hand was there. 2 So they were watching him closely to see whether he would cure the man on the Sabbath, in order to accuse him. 3 He said to the man with the withered* hand: “Get up and come to the center.” 4 Next he said to them: “Is it lawful on the Sabbath to do good or to do harm, to save a life or to kill?” But they kept silent. 5 After looking around at them with indignation, being thoroughly grieved at the insensibility of their hearts, he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored. 6 At that the Pharisees went out and immediately began holding council with the party followers of Herod against him, in order to kill him.

Or “paralyzed.” Lit., “dried-up.”

Or “paralyzed.” Lit., “dried-up.”

^ (John 9:29-34) We know that God has spoken to Moses, but as for this man, we do not know where he is from.” 30 The man answered them: “This is certainly amazing, that you do not know where he is from, and yet he opened my eyes. 31 We know that God does not listen to sinners, but if anyone is God-fearing and does his will, he listens to this one. 32 From of old it has never been heard that anyone opened the eyes of one born blind. 33 If this man were not from God, he could do nothing at all.” 34 In answer they said to him: “You were altogether born in sin, and yet are you teaching us?” And they threw him out!

Friday, May 21

Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them.—[1 Thess. 5:3].

World leaders sometimes use similar expressions when they talk about stabilizing relationships between nations. However, the announcement of “peace and security” that the Bible describes will be different. Why? When this happens, people may think that world leaders have succeeded in making the world a safer, more secure place. But in reality, “sudden destruction” will follow as the “great tribulation” unfolds. ([Matt. 24:21]) We do not know what will lead up to the declaration or how it will be made. And we do not know whether it will involve just one proclamation or a series of announcements. Whatever happens, we do know this: We should not be fooled into thinking that world leaders can actually achieve world peace. Rather, it is the signal that “Jehovah’s day” is about to begin!—[1 Thess. 5:2]. w19.10 8-9 ¶3-4

^ (1 Thess. 5:3) Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape.

^ (Matt. 24:21) for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again.

^ (1 Thess. 5:2) For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night.

See App. A5.

Saturday, May 22

During that time your people will escape.—[Dan. 12:1].

The war of Armageddon will be the grand finale to the conclusion of this system of things. However, we have nothing to fear. Why? Because this will be God’s fight. ([Prov. 1:33;] Ezek. 38:18-20;[Zech. 14:3]) At Jehovah’s signal, Jesus Christ will lead the charge. He will have alongside him the resurrected anointed ones and myriads of angels. Together, they will war against Satan, his demons, and their earthly forces. ([Rev. 6:2;][17:14]) Jehovah has guaranteed: “No weapon formed against you will have any success.” ([Isa. 54:17]) “A great crowd” of Jehovah’s faithful worshippers will “come out of the great tribulation” alive! Then they will continue to render him sacred service. ([Rev. 7:9,][13-17]) How the Bible fills us with confidence about the future! We know that “Jehovah protects the faithful.” ([Ps. 31:23]) All who love and praise Jehovah will delight to see him vindicate his holy name.—[Ezek. 38:23]. w19.10 18-19 ¶17-18

^ (Dan. 12:1) “During that time Miʹcha·el* will stand up,* the great prince who is standing in behalf of your people.* And there will occur a time of distress such as has not occurred since there came to be a nation until that time. And during that time your people will escape, everyone who is found written down in the book.

Meaning “Who Is Like God?”

Or “arise.”

Lit., “the sons of your people.”

^ (Prov. 1:33) But the one listening to me will dwell in security And be undisturbed by the dread of calamity.”

^ (Ezek. 38:18-20) “‘On that day, the day when Gog invades the land of Israel,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘my great rage will flare up. 19 In my zeal, in the fire of my fury, I will speak; and in that day there will be a great earthquake in the land of Israel. 20 Because of me the fish of the sea, the birds of the sky, the wild beasts of the field, all the reptiles that creep on the ground, and all humans on the surface of the earth will tremble, and the mountains will be thrown down, and the cliffs will fall, and every wall will collapse to the ground.’

^ (Zech. 14:3) “Jehovah will go out and war against those nations as when he fights in the day of a battle.

^ (Rev. 6:2) And I saw, and look! a white horse, and the one seated on it had a bow; and a crown was given him, and he went out conquering and to complete his conquest.

^ (Rev. 17:14) These will battle with the Lamb, but because he is Lord of lords and King of kings, the Lamb will conquer them. Also, those with him who are called and chosen and faithful will do so.”

^ (Isa. 54:17) No weapon formed against you will have any success, And you will condemn any tongue that rises up against you in the judgment. This is the heritage* of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness is from me,” declares Jehovah.

Or “inheritance.”

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Rev. 7:13-17) In response one of the elders said to me: “These who are dressed in the white robes, who are they and where did they come from?” 14 So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. 15 That is why they are before the throne of God, and they are rendering him sacred service day and night in his temple; and the One seated on the throne will spread his tent over them. 16 They will hunger no more nor thirst anymore, neither will the sun beat down on them nor any scorching heat, 17 because the Lamb, who is in the midst* of the throne, will shepherd them and will guide them to springs* of waters of life. And God will wipe out every tear from their eyes.”

Or “at the center.”

Or “fountains.”

^ (Ps. 31:23) Love Jehovah, all you who are loyal to him! Jehovah protects the faithful, But he repays exceedingly anyone showing haughtiness.

^ (Ezek. 38:23) And I will certainly magnify myself and sanctify myself and make myself known before the eyes of many nations; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

Sunday, May 23

A true friend shows love at all times.—[Prov. 17:17].

As we move deeper into “the last days,” we may face severe adversities. ([2 Tim. 3:1]) For example, after an election campaign, a country in western Africa was torn apart by social unrest and mob violence. For over six months, our brothers and sisters could not move about freely because they were in a combat zone. What helped them to cope with such hardships? Some found refuge in the homes of brothers living in a safer area. One brother reported: “In such a situation, I appreciated having friends around me. We were able to encourage one another.” When “the great tribulation” strikes, we will appreciate having good friends who love us. ([Rev. 7:14]) So it is urgent that we build strong bonds of friendship now. (1 Pet. 4:7, 8) Why? Because our enemies will try to divide us by means of lies and misinformation. They will try to turn us against one another. But their efforts will be wasted. They will be unable to break our bonds of love. w19.11 2 ¶1-2; 7 ¶19

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

^ (1 Pet. 4:7, 8) But the end of all things has drawn close. Therefore, be sound in mind, and be vigilant* with a view to prayers. 8 Above all things, have intense love for one another, because love covers a multitude of sins.

Or “alert; awake.”

Monday, May 24

You will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.—[Eph. 6:16].

Satan, “the father of the lie,” uses those under his control to spread lies about Jehovah and about our brothers and sisters. ([John 8:44]) For instance, apostates publish lies and distort facts about Jehovah’s organization on websites and through television and other media. Those lies are among Satan’s “burning arrows.” How should we respond if someone confronts us with such lies? We reject them! Why? Because we have faith in Jehovah and we trust our brothers. In fact, we avoid all contact with apostates. We do not allow anyone or anything, including curiosity, to draw us into arguing with them nor to weaken our faith. Have you resisted the urge to listen to and argue with apostates about the lies they spread? That is commendable. But we must remain on guard because Satan has other weapons that he tries to use against us. w19.11 15 ¶8; 16 ¶11

^ (Eph. 6:16) Besides all of this, take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.*

Or “missiles; darts.”

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

Wednesday, May 26

Carry on as citizens in a manner worthy of the good news about the Christ.—[Phil. 1:27], ftn.

The apostle Paul was confident that he would finish the race and reach his goal. As an anointed Christian, he looked forward to gaining “the prize of the upward call of God.” However, to reach that goal, he realized that he had to keep “pressing on.” ([Phil. 3:14]) Paul shared with the Philippians an interesting comparison to help them keep focused on their goal. Paul reminded the Philippians of their heavenly citizenship. ([Phil. 3:20]) Why did such citizenship matter? In those days, Roman citizenship was highly prized. However, anointed Christians had a much better citizenship, one that would bring far greater advantages. Roman citizenship paled in comparison! Anointed Christians today set a fine example as they press on toward their goal of everlasting life in heaven. w19.08 6 ¶14-15

^ (Phil. 1:27) Only behave* in a manner worthy of the good news about the Christ, so that whether I come and see you or I am absent, I may hear about you and learn that you are standing firm in one spirit, with one soul,* striving side by side for the faith of the good news,

Or “carry on as citizens.”

Or “with one accord.”

^ (Phil. 3:14) I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus.

^ (Phil. 3:20) But our citizenship exists in the heavens, and we are eagerly waiting for a savior from there, the Lord Jesus Christ,

Friday, May 28

Bad associations spoil useful habits.—[1 Cor. 15:33].

Parents, help your children to choose good associates. Both mother and father need to know whom their children are associating with and what they are doing. That includes knowing whom their children are communicating with through social media and on their mobile phone. Those associates can impact how the children think and act. Many parents exert themselves to arrange opportunities for their children to associate with those who set a good example in serving God. For instance, N’Déni and Bomine, a couple in Côte d’Ivoire, often invited the circuit overseer to stay in their home. N’Déni relates: “This had a very good effect on our son. He began pioneering and now serves as a substitute circuit overseer.” The earlier parents begin training their children, the better. ([Prov. 22:6]) Consider Timothy. Timothy’s mother, Eunice, and his grandmother Lois trained him “from infancy.”—[2 Tim. 1:5;][3:15]. w19.12 25 ¶14; 26 ¶16-17

^ (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (Prov. 22:6) Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.

Or “child; youth.”

^ (2 Tim. 1:5) For I recall your unhypocritical faith, which dwelled first in your grandmother Loʹis and your mother Euʹnice, but which I am confident is also in you.

^ (2 Tim. 3:15) and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.

Sunday, May 30

He will be filled with holy spirit even from before birth.—[Luke 1:15].

Throughout the Bible, there are many examples of men of faith who received holy spirit; yet, they did not have the hope of living in heaven. David was guided by holy spirit. ([1 Sam. 16:13]) Holy spirit helped him to understand the deep things about Jehovah and also directed him to write parts of the Bible. ([Mark 12:36]) Even so, the apostle Peter said that David “did not ascend to the heavens.” ([Acts 2:34]) John the Baptist was “filled with holy spirit.” ([Luke 1:13-16]) Jesus said that there was no man greater than John, but then he said that John would not be included in the heavenly Kingdom. (Matt. 11:10, 11) Jehovah used his holy spirit to give these men the power to do amazing things, but he did not use that spirit to choose them to live in heaven. Does this mean that they were less faithful? No. It simply means that Jehovah will bring them back to life in Paradise on earth.—John 5:28, 29;[Acts 24:15]. w20.01 25 ¶15

^ (Luke 1:15) for he will be great in the sight of Jehovah. But he must drink no wine or any alcoholic drink at all, and he will be filled with holy spirit even from before birth,*

Or “right from his mother’s womb.”

^ (1 Sam. 16:13) So Samuel took the horn of oil and anointed him in the presence of his brothers. And the spirit of Jehovah began to empower David from that day forward. Samuel later rose and went his way to Raʹmah.

^ (Mark 12:36) By the holy spirit, David himself said, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies beneath your feet.”’

^ (Acts 2:34) For David did not ascend to the heavens, but he himself says, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand

^ (Luke 1:13-16) However, the angel said to him: “Do not be afraid, Zech·a·riʹah, because your supplication has been favorably heard, and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son, and you are to name him John. 14 You will have joy and great gladness, and many will rejoice over his birth, 15 for he will be great in the sight of Jehovah. But he must drink no wine or any alcoholic drink at all, and he will be filled with holy spirit even from before birth,* 16 and he will turn back many of the sons of Israel to Jehovah their God.

Or “right from his mother’s womb.”

^ (Matt. 11:10, 11) This is the one about whom it is written: ‘Look! I am sending my messenger* ahead of you,* who will prepare your way ahead of you!’ 11 Truly I say to you, among those born of women, there has not been raised up anyone greater than John the Baptist, but a lesser person in the Kingdom of the heavens is greater than he is.

Or “angel.”

Lit., “before your face.”

^ (John 5:28, 29) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice 29 and come out, those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced vile things to a resurrection of judgment.

^ (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

Wednesday, June 2

Let your words always be gracious, seasoned with salt, so that you will know how you should answer each person.—[Col. 4:6].

Soon, Jehovah will bring this system to an end. Only those who are “rightly disposed for everlasting life” will survive. ([Acts 13:48]) So it is natural that we would also want our relatives to serve Jehovah with us. Our loving Father, Jehovah, “does not desire anyone to be destroyed but desires all to attain to repentance.” ([2 Pet. 3:9]) We need to keep in mind that there is a right way and a wrong way to share the message of salvation. Although we may be tactful when witnessing to a stranger, we may be too blunt when talking with our relatives. Many of us may look back with regret on our initial attempt to witness to our relatives and wish we had dealt with them differently. It is good to remember the apostle Paul’s advice, mentioned in today’s text, when we approach our relatives. Otherwise, we might end up alienating them rather than persuading them. w19.08 14-15 ¶3-5

^ (Col. 4:6) Let your words always be gracious, seasoned with salt, so that you will know how you should answer each person.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (2 Pet. 3:9) Jehovah* is not slow concerning his promise, as some people consider slowness, but he is patient with you because he does not desire anyone to be destroyed but desires all to attain to repentance.

See App. A5.

Friday, June 4

Pray constantly.—1 Thess. 5:17.

Jesus prayed often throughout the last day of his life on earth. When he instituted the commemoration of his death, he prayed over the bread and the wine. (1 Cor. 11:23-25) Before leaving the place where they had held the Passover, he prayed with the disciples. (John 17:1-26) When he and the disciples arrived at the Mount of Olives that night, he prayed repeatedly. (Matt. 26:36-39,[42,][44]) And the very last words Jesus spoke before dying were uttered in prayer. ([Luke 23:46]) Through prayer, Jesus included Jehovah in every major event on that momentous day. One reason why Jesus could endure his trial was that he turned to his Father in prayer. The apostles, on the other hand, failed to persevere in prayer that night. As a result, their courage weakened when the hour of test arrived. (Matt. 26:40, 41,[43,][45,][56]) When we face trials, we will remain faithful only if we follow Jesus’ example and “pray continually.” w19.04 9 ¶4-5

^ (1 Thess. 5:17) Pray constantly.

^ (1 Cor. 11:23-25) For I received from the Lord what I also handed on to you, that the Lord Jesus on the night on which he was going to be betrayed took a loaf, 24 and after giving thanks, he broke it and said: “This means my body, which is in your behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.” 25 He did the same with the cup also, after they had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood. Keep doing this, whenever you drink it, in remembrance of me.”

^ (Matt. 26:36-39) Then Jesus came with them to the spot called Geth·semʹa·ne, and he said to the disciples: “Sit down here while I go over there and pray.” 37 And taking along Peter and the two sons of Zebʹe·dee, he began to feel grieved and to be greatly troubled. 38 Then he said to them: “I am deeply grieved, even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch with me.” 39 And going a little way forward, he fell facedown, praying: “My Father, if it is possible, let this cup pass away from me. Yet, not as I will, but as you will.”

^ (Matt. 26:42) Again, a second time, he went off and prayed: “My Father, if it is not possible for this to pass away unless I drink it, let your will take place.”

^ (Matt. 26:44) So leaving them, he again went off and prayed for a third time, saying once more the same thing.

^ (Luke 23:46) And Jesus called out with a loud voice and said: “Father, into your hands I entrust my spirit.” After he said this, he expired.

^ (Matt. 26:40, 41) He returned to the disciples and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Could you not so much as keep on the watch for one hour with me? 41 Keep on the watch and pray continually, so that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager,* but the flesh is weak.”

Or “willing.”

^ (Matt. 26:43) And he came again and found them sleeping, for their eyes were heavy.

^ (Matt. 26:45) Then he returned to the disciples and said to them: “At such a time as this, you are sleeping and resting! Look! The hour has drawn near for the Son of man to be betrayed into the hands of sinners.

^ (Matt. 26:56) But all of this has taken place for the writings* of the prophets to be fulfilled.” Then all the disciples abandoned him and fled.

Or “scriptures.”

Tuesday, June 8

Stand firm against the crafty acts of the Devil.—[Eph. 6:11].

Satan deceived the Israelites into believing that to prosper, they had to adopt the practices of their pagan neighbors. Those neighbors believed that certain rituals were needed to get their gods to act and bring the needed rain. Those who lacked faith in Jehovah believed that this was the only way to avoid a prolonged drought, so they performed pagan rituals in honor of the false god Baal. Satan also appealed to immoral desires. The pagan nations worshipped their gods by engaging in grossly immoral acts. This perverted form of worship included both female and male temple prostitution. Homosexuality and other forms of sexual immorality not only were tolerated but became normal! (Deut. 23:17, 18;[1 Ki. 14:24]) The pagans believed that these rituals encouraged their gods to make the land fertile. Many Israelites were attracted by the pagans’ sexually immoral rituals and allowed themselves to be lured into serving false gods. w19.06 2 ¶3; 4 ¶7-8

^ (Eph. 6:11) Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts* of the Devil;

Or “the schemes.”

^ (Deut. 23:17, 18) “None of the daughters of Israel may become a temple prostitute, neither may anyone of the sons of Israel become a temple prostitute. 18 You must not bring the price paid to a female prostitute or the price paid to* a male prostitute* into the house of Jehovah your God to fulfill a vow, for both of them are something detestable to Jehovah your God.

Or “the earnings of.”

Lit., “a dog.”

^ (1 Ki. 14:24) There were also male temple prostitutes in the land. They acted according to all the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out before the Israelites.

Wednesday, June 9

God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name.—[Heb. 6:10].

Thousands of Bethel family members and others have received new assignments. These faithful brothers and sisters may find it challenging to leave a cherished assignment. If you are one of them, what can help you to deal with the change? Remain close to Jehovah by reading the Scriptures daily and pondering on them. Also, continue to be fully involved in preaching the good news in your new congregation. Jehovah remembers those who continue to serve him faithfully, even if they cannot do all they did before. Keep your life simple. Do not let the anxieties of Satan’s world “choke” your spiritual activity. ([Matt. 13:22]) Reject pressure from the world or from well-meaning friends or relatives to seek financial security in Satan’s system. (1 John 2:15-17) Trust in Jehovah, who promises to provide for all our spiritual, emotional, and material needs “at the right time.”—[Heb. 4:16;][13:5, 6]. w19.08 20 ¶4; 21-22 ¶7-8

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Matt. 13:22) As for the one sown among the thorns, this is the one hearing the word, but the anxiety of this system of things and the deceptive power of riches* choke the word, and it* becomes unfruitful.

Or “the seductiveness (deceptive pleasure) of being wealthy.”

Or possibly, “he,” that is, “the one hearing the word.”

^ (1 John 2:15-17) Do not love either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. 17 Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

^ (Heb. 4:16) Let us, then, approach the throne of undeserved kindness with freeness of speech, so that we may receive mercy and find undeserved kindness to help us at the right time.

^ (Heb. 13:5, 6) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.” 6 So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

Friday, June 11

You will be hated by all the nations on account of my name.—[Matt. 24:9].

When persecuted, pray to Jehovah, “pour out your heart like water,” and tell your loving Father about all your fears and anxieties. ([Lam. 2:19]) The more you pray this way, the closer you will feel to Jehovah. (Rom. 8:38, 39) Be convinced that the blessings of God’s Kingdom will come true. ([Num. 23:19]) If your faith in such promises is weak, it will be easier for Satan and his agents to terrify you. ([Prov. 24:10;][Heb. 2:15]) Make it a study project to examine God’s promises about his Kingdom and the reasons why you can be certain that they will come true. How will that help? Consider the example of Stanley Jones, who was imprisoned for seven years because of his faith. What helped him to endure faithfully? He said: “Being fortified with a knowledge of God’s kingdom, being sure of it, never doubting it for a moment, I couldn’t be moved.” If you have strong faith in God’s promises, you will not give in to fear.—Prov. 3:25, 26. w19.07 2 ¶1; 3 ¶6-7

^ (Matt. 24:9) “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name.

^ (Lam. 2:19) Rise up! Cry out during the night, at the start of the watches. Pour out your heart like water before the face of Jehovah. Raise your hands to him for the lives* of your children, Who are fainting away at every street corner* because of famine.

Or “souls.”

Lit., “at the head of all streets.”

^ (Rom. 8:38, 39) For I am convinced that neither death nor life nor angels nor governments nor things now here nor things to come nor powers 39 nor height nor depth nor any other creation will be able to separate us from God’s love that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

^ (Num. 23:19) God is not a mere man who tells lies, Nor a son of man who changes his mind.* When he says something, will he not do it? When he speaks, will he not carry it out?

Or “who feels regret.”

^ (Prov. 24:10) If you become discouraged in the day of distress,* Your strength will be meager.

Or “in times of trouble.”

^ (Heb. 2:15) and that he might set free* all those who were held in slavery all their lives by their fear of death.

Or “emancipate.”

^ (Prov. 3:25, 26) You will not fear any sudden terror Nor the storm that is coming on the wicked. 26 For Jehovah will prove to be your source of confidence; He will keep your foot from being caught.

Saturday, June 12

Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving, and stay there until you leave.—[Matt. 10:11].

Why is the disciple-making work so important? Because only disciples of Christ can be friends of God. In addition, those who follow Christ improve their lives now and have the hope of enjoying endless life in the future. ([John 14:6;][17:3]) Certainly, Jesus has entrusted us with an important responsibility, but we do not do this work by ourselves. The apostle Paul wrote about himself and certain close associates: “We are God’s fellow workers.” ([1 Cor. 3:9]) What a privilege Jehovah and Christ have given to imperfect humans! Also, the disciple-making work can bring us much joy. We take the first step in making disciples when we “search out” those with the right heart condition. We prove that we truly are Jehovah’s Witnesses by witnessing to all whom we meet. We prove that we are genuine Christians by following Christ’s command to preach. w19.07 15 ¶3-5

^ (Matt. 10:11) “Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving, and stay there until you leave.

^ (John 14:6) Jesus said to him: “I am the way and the truth and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me.

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you, the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

Tuesday, June 15

I urge Euodia and I urge Syntyche to be of the same mind in the Lord.—[Phil. 4:2].

Like Euodia and Syntyche, we may face a major obstacle to cultivating a close bond of love with others—the tendency to focus on imperfections. All of us make mistakes every day. If we stay focused on the imperfections of others, our love for them will cool. For example, if a brother forgets to help us clean the Kingdom Hall, we may become irritated. If we then begin to list all the other mistakes we know our brother has made, our irritation will grow and our love for him will diminish. If you find yourself in a similar situation, it would be good to reflect on this fact: Jehovah sees our imperfections as well as those of our brother. Yet, in spite of these imperfections, he still loves our brother and he still loves us. For that reason, we need to imitate Jehovah’s love and keep a positive view of our brothers. When we work hard to love our brothers, we strengthen our bond of unity with them.—[Phil. 2:1, 2]. w19.08 9-10 ¶7-8

^ (Phil. 4:2) I urge Eu·oʹdi·a and I urge Synʹty·che to be of the same mind in the Lord.

^ (Phil. 2:1, 2) If, then, there is any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any spiritual fellowship,* if any tender affection and compassion, 2 make my joy full by being of the same mind and having the same love, being completely united,* having the one thought in mind.

Lit., “any sharing of spirit.”

Or “being joined together in soul.”

Wednesday, June 16

Jehovah . . . takes note of the humble.—[Ps. 138:6].

Jehovah loves humble people. Only those who are truly humble can have a warm, personal relationship with him. On the other hand, “the haughty he knows only from a distance.” All of us want to please Jehovah and experience his warm love, so we have good reasons to learn to cultivate humility. Humility is lowliness of mind and freedom from pride or arrogance. The Bible indicates that a humble person has a proper view of his relationship with Jehovah God and with his fellow man. The humble person acknowledges that everyone is superior to him in some way. ([Phil. 2:3, 4]) Some people only appear to be humble. They may have an unassuming personality. Or they may show deference or politeness because of their culture and upbringing. But deep down, they may actually be very prideful. Sooner or later, they will reveal what they truly are at heart.—[Luke 6:45]. w19.09 2 ¶1, 3-4

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (Phil. 2:3, 4) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you, 4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Luke 6:45) A good man brings good out of the good treasure of his heart, but a wicked man brings what is wicked out of his wicked treasure; for out of the heart’s abundance his mouth speaks.

Thursday, June 17

He brings vengeance on those . . . who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus.—[2 Thess. 1:8].

“The good news about our Lord Jesus” includes all the truths that Jesus taught. We obey the good news when we apply it in our lives. That obedience includes keeping Kingdom interests in first place, living by God’s righteous standards, and announcing God’s Kingdom. ([Matt. 6:33;][24:14]) It also includes supporting Christ’s anointed brothers as they care for their weighty responsibilities. (Matt. 25:31-40) Soon they will be able to return the kindness shown them by those of the “other sheep.” ([John 10:16]) How so? Before the war of Armageddon begins, all of the 144,000 will have been raised to heaven as immortal spirits. They will then be part of the heavenly armies that will crush Gog and safeguard “a great crowd” of sheeplike ones. (Rev. 2:26, 27;[7:9, 10]) Yes, what a privilege the great crowd will have had to support Jehovah’s anointed servants while these were still on earth! w19.09 12-13 ¶16-18

^ (2 Thess. 1:8) in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus.

^ (Matt. 6:33) “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Matt. 25:31-40) “When the Son of man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit down on his glorious throne. 32 All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats. 33 And he will put the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on his left. 34 “Then the King will say to those on his right: ‘Come, you who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founding of the world. 35 For I became hungry and you gave me something to eat; I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink. I was a stranger and you received me hospitably; 36 naked and you clothed me. I fell sick and you looked after me. I was in prison and you visited me.’ 37 Then the righteous ones will answer him with the words: ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink? 38 When did we see you a stranger and receive you hospitably, or naked and clothe you? 39 When did we see you sick or in prison and visit you?’ 40 In reply the King will say to them, ‘Truly I say to you, to the extent that you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’

^ (John 10:16) “And I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; those too I must bring in, and they will listen to my voice, and they will become one flock, one shepherd.

^ (Rev. 2:26, 27) And to the one who conquers and observes my deeds down to the end, I will give authority over the nations, 27 and he will shepherd the people with an iron rod so that they will be broken to pieces like clay vessels, just as I have received from my Father.

^ (Rev. 7:9, 10) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

Or “languages.”

Friday, June 18

You will find refreshment.—[Matt. 11:29].

Why is it refreshing for us to do the work Jesus has given us? Because we have the best overseers. Jehovah, our Supreme Overseer, is not a thankless or harsh master. He appreciates the work we do. ([Heb. 6:10]) And he gives us the power that we need to carry our load of responsibility. ([2 Cor. 4:7;][Gal. 6:5], ftn.) Jesus, our King, leads by example. ([John 13:15]) And the elders who shepherd us try to imitate Jesus, “the great shepherd.” ([Heb. 13:20;][1 Pet. 5:2]) They strive to be kind, encouraging, and courageous as they feed and protect us. Also, we have the best companions. No other people have a sense of purpose or a bond of love like ours. Just think: We have the privilege of working with people who have the highest moral standards but who are not self-righteous. They consider others superior to them. They view us not only as fellow workers but also as friends. And that bond is so close that they are willing to give their lives for us! w19.09 20 ¶1; 23 ¶12-14

^ (Matt. 11:29) Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (2 Cor. 4:7) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels, so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us.

^ (Gal. 6:5) For each one will carry his own load.*

Or “load of responsibility.”

^ (John 13:15) For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do.

^ (Heb. 13:20) Now may the God of peace, who brought up from the dead the great shepherd of the sheep, our Lord Jesus, with the blood of an everlasting covenant,

^ (1 Pet. 5:2) Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly;

Or “carefully watching over it.”

Monday, June 21

God . . . energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.—[Phil. 2:13].

Jehovah can become whatever is necessary in order to accomplish his purpose. For instance, Jehovah has become a Teacher, a Comforter, and an Evangelizer, just to name a few of his many roles. ([Isa. 48:17;][2 Cor. 7:6;][Gal. 3:8]) Still, he often uses humans to carry out his purposes. ([Matt. 24:14;][28:19, 20;] 2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Jehovah can also give any of us the wisdom and strength we need in order to become whatever is necessary to fulfill his will. This is all part of the meaning of Jehovah’s name, as it is suggested by a number of scholars. All of us want to be useful to Jehovah, but some may doubt that Jehovah is using them. Why? Because they feel limited by their age, circumstances, or abilities. On the other hand, others may be quite satisfied with what they are already doing and fail to see the need to make further progress. w19.10 20 ¶1-2

^ (Phil. 2:13) For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.

^ (Isa. 48:17) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk.

Or “for your own good.”

^ (2 Cor. 7:6) But God, who comforts those who are downhearted, comforted us by the presence of Titus;

^ (Gal. 3:8) Now the scripture, foreseeing that God would declare people of the nations righteous through faith, declared the good news beforehand to Abraham, namely: “By means of you all the nations will be blessed.”

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts us in all our trials so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.

Tuesday, June 22

The love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things.—[1 Tim. 6:10].

Materialism can cause us to become distracted and neglect our shield of faith. The apostle Paul said: “No man serving as a soldier involves himself in the commercial businesses of life, in order to gain the approval of the one who enrolled him.” ([2 Tim. 2:4]) In fact, Roman soldiers were not allowed to get involved in any trade. Like good soldiers, we do not become distracted from our primary goal—gaining the approval of our Commanders, Jehovah and Christ. We view that as being more valuable than gaining anything Satan’s world has to offer. We make sure that we have the time and energy we need to serve Jehovah and to keep our shield of faith and the rest of our spiritual armor in good condition. We must never let down our guard! Why? The apostle Paul warned that “those who are determined to be rich” will be “led astray from the faith.”—1 Tim. 6:9, 10. w19.11 17 ¶12, 14-15

^ (1 Tim. 6:10) For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ (2 Tim. 2:4) No man serving as a soldier involves himself* in the commercial businesses* of life, in order to gain the approval of the one who enrolled him as a soldier.

Lit., “gets entangled.”

Or possibly, “the everyday activities.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

Friday, June 25

These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.—[Rev. 7:14].

A prophetic description of life on earth is found at Isaiah 65:21-23. That life will not be a life of idleness. Rather, the Bible indicates that God’s people at that time will be doing useful, satisfying work. At the end of that period, we can be sure that “the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.” ([Rom. 8:21]) Just as Jehovah arranged for the Israelites to balance work and rest, so it will be for his people in the coming Thousand Year Rule of Christ. There will certainly be time for spiritual activities. Worship of God is essential to happiness today, and it will be so in the new world. Yes, we have good reason to rejoice over the good work and spiritual activity that we can expect when believing mankind enjoys life during Christ’s Millennial Reign. w19.12 12 ¶15; 13 ¶17-18

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

^ (Isa. 65:21-23) They will build houses and live in them, And they will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 22 They will not build for someone else to inhabit, Nor will they plant for others to eat. For the days of my people will be like the days of a tree, And the work of their hands my chosen ones will enjoy to the full. 23 They will not toil* for nothing,* Nor will they bear children for distress, Because they are the offspring* made up of those blessed by Jehovah, And their descendants with them.

Or “work hard.”

Or “in vain.”

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Rom. 8:21) that* the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.

Or “because.”

Tuesday, June 29

Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you.—[Jas. 4:8].

Jehovah wants us to draw close to him and to communicate with him. He urges us to “persevere in prayer,” and he makes himself available at all times. ([Rom. 12:12]) He is never too busy or too tired to listen to us. In turn, we listen to him by reading his Word, the Bible, along with publications that help us to understand it. We also listen to him by paying close attention at Christian meetings. Regular communication with Jehovah helps us remain close to him. Jehovah wants us to pour out our hearts to him in prayer. ([Ps. 62:8]) We do well to ask ourselves this question: ‘Do my prayers tend to be like superficial, reprinted messages, or are they like heartfelt, handwritten letters?’ No doubt you love Jehovah deeply, and you want to keep your relationship with him strong. To do that, you must communicate with him regularly. Confide in him. Share your joys and your pains with him. Be confident that you can go to him for help. w20.02 9 ¶4-5

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Rom. 12:12) Rejoice in the hope. Endure under tribulation. Persevere in prayer.

^ (Ps. 62:8) Trust in him at all times, O people. Pour out your hearts before him. God is a refuge for us. (Selah)

Friday, July 2

There is . . . a time to speak.—[Eccl. 3:1,][7].

Speech is a gift from Jehovah. (Ex. 4:10, 11;[Rev. 4:11]) In his Word, he helps us to understand how to use that gift properly. We should always be ready to speak about Jehovah and the Kingdom. ([Matt. 24:14;][Rom. 10:14]) In so doing, we imitate Jesus. One of the main reasons why Jesus came to earth was to tell others the truth about his Father. ([John 18:37]) But we must remember that how we speak is also important. So when talking to others about Jehovah, we must do so with “a mild temper and deep respect,” and we should show consideration for the other person’s feelings and beliefs. ([1 Pet. 3:15]) Then we will do more than just talk; we will teach and possibly reach the person’s heart. Elders should not hesitate to speak up if they see that a brother or a sister needs counsel. Of course, they would choose the right time to speak so that they do not needlessly embarrass the person. w20.03 18-19 ¶2-4

^ (Eccl. 3:1) There is an appointed time for everything, A time for every activity under the heavens:

^ (Eccl. 3:7) A time to rip apart and a time to sew together; A time to be silent and a time to speak;

^ (Ex. 4:10, 11) Moses now said to Jehovah: “Pardon me, Jehovah, but I have never been a fluent speaker, neither in the past nor since you have spoken to your servant, for I am slow of speech* and slow of tongue.” 11 Jehovah said to him: “Who made a mouth for man, or who makes them speechless, deaf, clear-sighted, or blind? Is it not I, Jehovah?

Lit., “heavy of mouth.”

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Rom. 10:14) However, how will they call on him if they have not put faith in him? How, in turn, will they put faith in him about whom they have not heard? How, in turn, will they hear without someone to preach?

^ (John 18:37) So Pilate said to him: “Well, then, are you a king?” Jesus answered: “You yourself are saying that I am a king. For this I have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth. Everyone who is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.”

^ (1 Pet. 3:15) But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.

Monday, July 5

Should they inquire of the dead in behalf of the living?—[Isa. 8:19].

God’s Word is like a sharp sword that can cut through the lies that Satan promotes. ([Eph. 6:17]) For example, God’s Word exposes the lie that the dead can communicate with the living. ([Ps. 146:4]) It also reminds us that only Jehovah can reliably predict the future. ([Isa. 45:21;][46:10]) If we read God’s Word and meditate on it regularly, we will be equipped to reject and hate the lies that wicked spirits want us to believe. So refuse to do anything connected with spiritism. As true Christians, we never practice spiritism of any kind. For example, we do not visit spirit mediums or try to communicate with the dead in any other way. We avoid funeral customs that are based on the belief that the dead are still alive somewhere. And we do not use astrology or fortune-telling to try to learn about the future. We know that all such practices are very dangerous and that they could put us in direct contact with Satan and the demons. w19.04 21-22 ¶8-9

^ (Isa. 8:19) And if they say to you: “Inquire of the spirit mediums or of the fortune-tellers who chirp and mutter,” is it not of their God that a people should inquire? Should they inquire of the dead in behalf of the living?

^ (Eph. 6:17) Also, accept the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word,

^ (Ps. 146:4) His spirit* goes out, he returns to the ground; On that very day his thoughts perish.

Or “breath.”

^ (Isa. 45:21) Make your report, present your case. Let them consult together in unity. Who foretold this long ago And declared it from times past? Is it not I, Jehovah? There is no other God but me; A righteous God and a Savior, there is none besides me.

^ (Isa. 46:10) From the beginning I foretell the outcome, And from long ago the things that have not yet been done. I say, ‘My decision* will stand, And I will do whatever I please.’

Or “purpose; counsel.”

Tuesday, July 6

God, in keeping with the desires of their hearts, gave them up to uncleanness.—[Rom. 1:24].

People who adopt the wisdom of this world ridicule the Bible’s moral standards, claiming that they are unrealistic. Such people might ask, ‘Why would God create us with sexual desires and then tell us not to act on them?’ That question is founded on the flawed belief that humans must act on every urge they feel. But the Bible states otherwise. It dignifies us by teaching that we can choose to control improper impulses. ([Col. 3:5]) In addition, Jehovah has provided the gift of marriage, an arrangement in which proper sexual desires can be honorably satisfied. (1 Cor. 7:8, 9) In contrast with the wisdom of this world, the Bible promotes a healthy view of sexuality. It acknowledges that sex can be a source of pleasure. (Prov. 5:18, 19) However, the Bible says: “Each one of you should know how to control his own body in holiness and honor, not with greedy, uncontrolled sexual passion.”—1 Thess. 4:4, 5. w19.05 22-23 ¶7-9

^ (Rom. 1:24) Therefore, God, in keeping with the desires of their hearts, gave them up to uncleanness, so that their bodies might be dishonored among them.

^ (Col. 3:5) Deaden, therefore, your body members that are on the earth as respects sexual immorality,* uncleanness, uncontrolled sexual passion, hurtful desire, and greediness, which is idolatry.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ (1 Cor. 7:8, 9) Now I say to those who are unmarried and to the widows that it is better for them if they remain as I am. 9 But if they do not have self-control, let them marry, for it is better to marry than to be inflamed with passion.

^ (Prov. 5:18, 19) May your own fountain* be blessed, And may you rejoice with the wife of your youth, 19 A loving doe, a graceful mountain goat.* Let her breasts satisfy* you at all times. May you be captivated by her love constantly.

Or “water source.”

Or “ibex.”

Or “intoxicate.”

^ (1 Thess. 4:4, 5) Each one of you should know how to control his own body* in holiness and honor, 5 not with greedy, uncontrolled sexual passion like the nations have that do not know God.

Lit., “vessel.”

Friday, July 9

A true friend shows love at all times and is a brother who is born for times of distress.—[Prov. 17:17].

Elijah served Jehovah during difficult times and faced serious challenges. When Jehovah told Elijah to delegate responsibility to Elisha, He provided Elijah with a much-needed companion, who no doubt helped him bear his emotional burdens. Likewise, when we confide in a trusted friend, he or she can help us carry our emotional burdens. ([2 Ki. 2:2]) If you feel that you do not have anyone to confide in, pray to Jehovah to help you find a mature Christian who can provide you with emotional support. Jehovah helped Elijah to cope with stress and to serve faithfully for many years. Elijah’s experience gives us hope. We may go through periods of severe stress that drain us physically and emotionally. Yet, if we rely on Jehovah, he will give us the power we need to keep serving him.—Isa. 40:28, 29. w19.06 15 ¶4; 16 ¶9-10

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (2 Ki. 2:2) E·liʹjah said to E·liʹsha: “Stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to Bethʹel.” But E·liʹsha said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are* living, I will not leave you.” So they went down to Bethʹel.

Or “your soul is.”

^ (Isa. 40:28, 29) Do you not know? Have you not heard? Jehovah, the Creator of the ends of the earth, is a God for all eternity. He never tires out or grows weary. His understanding is unsearchable.* 29 He gives power to the tired one And full might to those lacking strength.*

Or “cannot be fathomed.”

Or “dynamic energy.”

Saturday, July 10

Trembling at men is a snare, but the one trusting in Jehovah will be protected.—[Prov. 29:25].

We can build up our courage now by publicly preaching the good news of God’s Kingdom. Why so? Because preaching teaches us to trust in Jehovah and overcome any fear of man. Just as our muscles are strengthened when we exercise, our courage is strengthened when we preach from house to house, in public places, informally, and in business territory. If we develop the courage to preach now, we will be well-prepared to keep preaching even if our work is banned. (1 Thess. 2:1, 2) We can learn much from the example of a faithful sister who displayed remarkable courage. Nancy Yuen stood no more than five feet (1.5 m) tall, but she was not easily intimidated. She refused to stop preaching the good news of God’s Kingdom. As a result, she was imprisoned for some 20 years in Communist China. The officials who interrogated her said that she was “the most stubborn person” in their country! w19.07 5 ¶13-14

^ (Prov. 29:25) Trembling at* men is* a snare, But the one trusting in Jehovah will be protected.

Or “Fear of.”

Or “lays.”

^ (1 Thess. 2:1, 2) You yourselves surely know, brothers, that our visit to you has not been without results. 2 For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness* by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.*

Or “courage.”

Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

Tuesday, July 13

Make sure of the more important things.—[Phil. 1:10].

These important things include the sanctification of Jehovah’s name, the fulfillment of his purposes, and the peace and unity of the congregation. (Matt. 6:9, 10;[John 13:35]) When we build our life around these important things, we prove that we love Jehovah. The apostle Paul also said that we must “be flawless.” This does not mean that we must be perfect. Jehovah will view us as flawless if we do our very best to deepen our love and make sure of the more important things. One way in which we show our love is by doing our utmost to avoid stumbling others. The instruction to avoid stumbling others is really a warning. How might we stumble someone? We could do so by our choice of entertainment, our choice of clothing, or even our choice of employment. What we do may not be wrong in itself. But if the choices we make offend someone else’s conscience and he or she is stumbled, that matters.—[Matt. 18:6]. w19.08 10 ¶9-11

^ (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ (Matt. 6:9, 10) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified. 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Matt. 18:6) But whoever stumbles one of these little ones who have faith in me, it would be better for him to have hung around his neck a millstone that is turned by a donkey and to be sunk in the open sea.

Wednesday, July 14

These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.—[Rev. 7:14].

Since 1935, Jehovah’s Witnesses have understood that the great crowd of John’s vision is made up of a group of faithful Christians who have the prospect of living forever on earth. ([Rev. 7:9, 10]) In order to survive the great tribulation, the great crowd would have to be educated in Jehovah’s ways before the Millennium begins. They would need to show strong faith in order to “succeed in escaping all these things that must occur” before Christ’s Thousand Year Reign. (Luke 21:34-36) Those of the great crowd rejoice in their hope. They understand that Jehovah determines where his faithful worshippers will serve him, whether in heaven or on earth. Both the anointed and the great crowd recognize that their reward is possible only because of Jehovah’s undeserved kindness as expressed through the ransom sacrifice of Jesus Christ.—[Rom. 3:24]. w19.09 28 ¶10; 29 ¶12-13

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

^ (Rev. 7:9, 10) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

Or “languages.”

^ (Luke 21:34-36) “But pay attention to yourselves that your hearts never become weighed down with overeating and heavy drinking and anxieties of life,* and suddenly that day be instantly upon you 35 as a snare. For it will come upon all those dwelling on the face of the whole earth. 36 Keep awake, then, all the time making supplication that you may succeed in escaping all these things that must occur and in standing before the Son of man.”

Or “anxieties over livelihood; worries of daily life.”

^ (Rom. 3:24) and it is as a free gift that they are being declared righteous by his undeserved kindness through the release by the ransom paid by Christ Jesus.

Thursday, July 15

The joy of Jehovah is your strength.—[Neh. 8:10], ftn.

Do you have a new assignment? Make it a success. Do not consider a change to be a failure or a step backward. Look for Jehovah’s hand in your life and keep preaching. Imitate the faithful Christians of the first century. Wherever they were, they “went through the land declaring the good news of the word.” ([Acts 8:1,][4]) Your efforts to keep on preaching may yield good results. For example, pioneers who were expelled from one country moved to a neighboring land where there also was a great need in their language. Within months, new rapidly growing groups were formed. We must find our joy primarily in Jehovah. Therefore, keep walking with Jehovah, looking to him for wisdom, guidance, and support. Remember that you came to love your former assignment because you put your heart into helping the people there. Put your heart into your present assignment and see how Jehovah helps you to love it too.—[Eccl. 7:10]. w19.08 24-25 ¶15-16

^ (Neh. 8:10) He said to them: “Go, eat the choice things* and drink what is sweet, and send portions of food to those who have nothing prepared; for this day is holy to our Lord, and do not feel sad, for the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.”*

Lit., “fatty things.”

Or “strength.”

^ (Acts 8:1) Saul, for his part, approved of his murder. On that day great persecution arose against the congregation that was in Jerusalem; all except the apostles were scattered throughout the regions of Ju·deʹa and Sa·marʹi·a.

^ (Acts 8:4) However, those who had been scattered went through the land declaring the good news of the word.

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

Saturday, July 17

My yoke is kindly, and my load is light.—[Matt. 11:30].

Satan loads people down with burdens they cannot carry. For example, he wants us to believe that Jehovah will not forgive us for our sins and that we are unlovable. What a crushing burden, and what a terrible lie! ([John 8:44]) When we “come to” Christ, our sins are forgiven. ([Matt. 11:28]) And the truth is that Jehovah loves all of us deeply. ([Rom. 8:32,][38, 39]) The load that Jesus asks us to carry is different from other loads that we must bear. For example, at the end of a day of secular work, many feel not only exhausted but also unfulfilled. By contrast, after spending time serving Jehovah and Christ, we feel a deep sense of satisfaction. We may be exhausted and have to push ourselves to attend a congregation meeting that night. But often we come home from that meeting refreshed and energized. The same is true when we make the effort to preach and to do our personal Bible study. The reward we receive is far greater than the energy we expend! w19.09 20 ¶1; 23-24 ¶15-16

^ (Matt. 11:30) For my yoke is kindly,* and my load is light.”

Or “easy to bear; pleasant.”

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Matt. 11:28) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

^ (Rom. 8:32) Since he did not even spare his own Son but handed him over for us all, will he not also, along with him, kindly give us all other things?

^ (Rom. 8:38, 39) For I am convinced that neither death nor life nor angels nor governments nor things now here nor things to come nor powers 39 nor height nor depth nor any other creation will be able to separate us from God’s love that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Monday, July 19

In everything you are being enriched for every sort of generosity, which produces through us an expression of thanks to God.—[2 Cor. 9:11].

Jehovah used Barzillai to provide for King David. David and the people were “hungry and tired and thirsty” while fleeing from David’s son, Absalom. Along with others, Barzillai, an old man at this point, risked his life to provide for David and those with him. Barzillai did not conclude that because of his advanced age, he was no longer useful to Jehovah. Rather, he generously used what he had to help God’s servants in need. (2 Sam. 17:27-29) What is the lesson for us? Regardless of our age, Jehovah can use us to fill the needs of fellow believers, either locally or in another land, who lack basic provisions. (Prov. 3:27, 28;[19:17]) Even if we cannot care for them directly, we may be able to contribute to the worldwide work so that funds are available to offer relief when and where it is needed.—2 Cor. 8:14, 15. w19.10 21 ¶6

^ (2 Cor. 9:11) In everything you are being enriched for every sort of generosity, which produces through us an expression of thanks to God;

^ (2 Sam. 17:27-29) As soon as David came to Ma·ha·naʹim, Shoʹbi the son of Naʹhash from Rabʹbah of the Amʹmon·ites, Maʹchir the son of Amʹmi·el from Lo-deʹbar, and Bar·zilʹlai the Gilʹe·ad·ite from Ro·geʹlim 28 brought beds, basins, clay pots, wheat, barley, flour, roasted grain, broad beans, lentils, parched grain, 29 honey, butter, sheep, and cheese.* They brought all of this out for David and the people with him to eat, for they said: “The people are hungry and tired and thirsty in the wilderness.”

Lit., “curds of cattle.”

^ (Prov. 3:27, 28) Do not withhold good from those to whom you should give it* If it is within your power* to help. 28 Do not say to your neighbor, “Go away; come back later! I will give it to you tomorrow,” If you can give it now.

Or “to whom it is owing.”

Or “within the power of your hand.”

^ (Prov. 19:17) The one showing favor to the lowly is lending to Jehovah, And He will repay* him for what he does.

Or “reward.”

^ (2 Cor. 8:14, 15) but that by means of an equalizing, your surplus at the present time might offset their need, so that their surplus might also offset your deficiency, that there may be an equalizing. 15 Just as it is written: “The person with much did not have too much, and the person with little did not have too little.”

Tuesday, July 20

There are companions ready to crush one another, but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.—[Prov. 18:24].

We may find it difficult to open up to others because someone might have hurt us in the past. ([Prov. 18:19]) Or we may feel that we lack the time and energy to cultivate close relationships. However, we should not give up. If we want our brothers to stand by us when trials come, we must learn to trust them now with our thoughts and feelings. That is an important step toward becoming true friends. ([1 Pet. 1:22]) Jesus showed that he trusted his friends by communicating openly with them. ([John 15:15]) We can imitate him by sharing our joys, concerns, and disappointments with others. Listen carefully as someone talks to you, and you may learn that you have many thoughts, feelings, and goals in common. If you take the initiative to have warm and open conversations with others, your friendships with them are likely to grow.—[Prov. 27:9]. w19.11 4 ¶8-9

^ (Prov. 18:24) There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

^ (Prov. 18:19) A brother offended is more unyielding than a fortified city, And there are disputes like the bars of a fortress.

^ (1 Pet. 1:22) Now that you have purified yourselves* by your obedience to the truth with unhypocritical brotherly affection as the result, love one another intensely from the heart.

Or “your souls.”

^ (John 15:15) I no longer call you slaves, because a slave does not know what his master does. But I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all the things I have heard from my Father.

^ (Prov. 27:9) Oil and incense make the heart rejoice; So does sweet friendship springing from sincere counsel.*

Or “from counsel of the soul.”

Thursday, July 22

Some have been led astray from the faith.—[1 Tim. 6:10].

The expression “led astray” indicates that we could become distracted by trying to acquire unnecessary possessions. We could then expose our heart to “many senseless and harmful desires.” ([1 Tim. 6:9]) Rather than allowing those desires into our heart, we must see them for what they are—weapons that can harm us. Suppose we have the financial means to buy many material things. Are we doing something wrong if we purchase things that we want but do not actually need? Not necessarily. But reflect on these questions: Even if we can afford to buy something, do we really have the time and energy to use and maintain the item? Also, might we become overly attached to our possessions? Could our attachment to material things cause us to act like the young man who turned down Jesus’ invitation to expand his service to God? (Mark 10:17-22) How much better it is for us to lead a simple life and spend our precious time and strength in doing God’s will! w19.11 17-18 ¶15-16

^ (1 Tim. 6:10) For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ (1 Tim. 6:9) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin.

^ (Mark 10:17-22) As he was going on his way, a man ran up and fell on his knees before him and put the question to him: “Good Teacher, what must I do to inherit everlasting life?” 18 Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good except one, God. 19 You know the commandments: ‘Do not murder, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not bear false witness, do not defraud, honor your father and your mother.’” 20 The man said to him: “Teacher, all these things I have kept from my youth on.” 21 Jesus looked at him and felt love for him and said, “One thing is missing about you: Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come be my follower.” 22 But he grew sad at the answer and went away grieved, for he had many possessions.

Sunday, July 25

Children are an inheritance from Jehovah.—[Ps. 127:3], ftn.

Parents may at times feel overwhelmed by the challenges they face, but children are a gift from Jehovah. He is always available to help. He willingly listens to the prayers of parents. And he answers those prayers by means of the Bible, our publications, and the example and advice of other mature parents in the congregation. It has been said that raising children is a 20-year project, but parents never really stop being parents. Among the very best things they can give their children are love, time, and Bible-based training. Each child will respond differently to the training. However, many of them who have been raised by parents who love Jehovah feel as does Joanna Mae, a sister in Asia: “I am so thankful that my parents disciplined me and taught me to love Jehovah. They did not just give me life, they gave me a meaningful life.” (Prov. 23:24, 25) Millions of Christians could express similar sentiments. w19.12 27 ¶21-22

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

^ (Prov. 23:24, 25) The father of a righteous one will surely be joyful; Whoever fathers a wise son will rejoice in him. 25 Your father and your mother will rejoice, And she who gave birth to you will be joyful.

Monday, July 26

Comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.—[2 Cor. 1:4].

We do not have to look far to find brothers and sisters who need comfort. We need, though, to take the initiative to act despite our fears. For instance, we may fear not knowing what to say or what to do for someone who is in a distressing situation. Yet we can be effective comforters if we show that we care. As we get closer to the end of this system of things, world conditions will deteriorate and life will become more challenging. ([2 Tim. 3:13]) And the problems that we bring on ourselves because of inherited sin and imperfection mean that we will continue to need comfort. The apostle Paul was able to endure faithfully to the end of his life, thanks, in part, to the comfort he received from fellow Christians. By following their example, we too can help our brothers and sisters to remain firm in the faith.—1 Thess. 3:2, 3. w20.01 12-13 ¶17-19

^ (2 Cor. 1:4) who comforts us in all our trials so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

^ (1 Thess. 3:2, 3) and we sent Timothy, our brother and God’s minister* in the good news about the Christ, to make you firm* and comfort you regarding your faith, 3 so that no one might be shaken* by these tribulations. For you yourselves know that we cannot avoid suffering such things.*

Or possibly, “and God’s fellow worker.”

Or “strengthen you.”

Lit., “swayed.”

Or “we are appointed to this.”

Tuesday, July 27

You put to the test those who say they are apostles.—[Rev. 2:2].

Anointed ones do not expect others to treat them in a special way. ([Phil. 2:2, 3]) They know that when Jehovah anointed them, he did not let everyone else know about it. So an anointed person is not surprised if some do not believe right away that he has been anointed. He realizes that the Bible tells us not to be quick to believe someone who says that God has given him a special responsibility. Not wanting to draw attention to himself, an anointed Christian would not tell those whom he meets for the first time that he is anointed. And he would certainly not boast about it. (1 Cor. 4:7, 8) Anointed Christians do not search out other anointed ones, hoping to discuss their anointing with them or to form private groups for Bible study. ([Gal. 1:15-17]) The congregation would not be united if anointed ones did so. They would be working against the holy spirit, which helps God’s people to have peace and unity.—Rom. 16:17, 18. w20.01 28 ¶6-7

^ (Rev. 2:2) ‘I know your deeds, and your labor and endurance, and that you cannot tolerate bad men, and that you put to the test those who say they are apostles, but they are not, and you found them to be liars.

^ (Phil. 2:2, 3) make my joy full by being of the same mind and having the same love, being completely united,* having the one thought in mind. 3 Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “being joined together in soul.”

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (1 Cor. 4:7, 8) For who makes you different from another? Indeed, what do you have that you did not receive? If, in fact, you did receive it, why do you boast as though you did not receive it? 8 Are you already satisfied? Are you already rich? Have you begun ruling as kings without us? I really wish that you had begun ruling as kings, so that we also might rule with you as kings.

^ (Gal. 1:15-17) But when God, who separated me from my mother’s womb and called me through his undeserved kindness, thought good 16 to reveal his Son through me so that I might declare the good news about him to the nations, I did not immediately consult with any human;* 17 nor did I go up to Jerusalem to those who were apostles before I was, but I went to Arabia, and then I returned to Damascus.

Lit., “with flesh and blood.”

^ (Rom. 16:17, 18) Now I urge you, brothers, to keep your eye on those who create divisions and causes for stumbling contrary to the teaching that you have learned, and avoid them. 18 For men of that sort are slaves, not of our Lord Christ, but of their own appetites, and by smooth talk and flattering speech they seduce the hearts of unsuspecting ones.

Wednesday, July 28

As these things start to occur, stand up straight and lift up your heads, because your deliverance is getting near.—[Luke 21:28].

At some point, the people whose religions were destroyed may resent the fact that Jehovah’s Witnesses keep practicing their religion. We can only imagine the uproar that this might create, including on social media. The nations and their ruler, Satan, will hate us for having the only surviving religion. They will not have attained their goal to eliminate all religion from the face of the earth. So we will become the center of their attention. At this point, the nations will take on the role of Gog of Magog. They will band together to make a vicious, all-out attack on Jehovah’s people. ([Ezek. 38:2,][14-16]) It can be somewhat unsettling to think about those possibilities when we cannot be certain of the exact details. However, one thing is sure: We do not need to fear the great tribulation. Jehovah will give us lifesaving instructions.—[Ps. 34:19]. w19.10 16-17 ¶10-11

^ (Luke 21:28) But as these things start to occur, stand up straight and lift up your heads, because your deliverance is getting near.”

^ (Ezek. 38:2) “Son of man, set your face against Gog of the land of Maʹgog, the head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal, and prophesy against him.

Or “chief prince.”

^ (Ezek. 38:14-16) “So prophesy, son of man, and say to Gog, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “On that day when my people Israel are dwelling in security, will you not know it? 15 You will come from your place, from the remotest parts of the north, you and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great assembly, a vast army. 16 Like clouds covering the land, you will come against my people Israel. In the final part of the days I will bring you against my land so that the nations may know me when I sanctify myself through you before their eyes, O Gog.”’

^ (Ps. 34:19) Many are the hardships* of the righteous one, But Jehovah rescues him from them all.

Or “calamities.”

Thursday, July 29

How many things you have done, O Jehovah my God, your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us.—[Ps. 40:5].

We do more than feel appreciative; we express our appreciation to Jehovah by our words and actions. This makes us stand out as different from many today. We live in a world where people do not appreciate all that God does for them. In fact, one indication that we are living in “the last days” is that people are unthankful. (2 Tim. 3:1, 2) May we never adopt that attitude! Jehovah wants all his children to get along well with one another. In fact, the love we have for one another identifies us as being true Christians. ([John 13:35]) We agree with the psalmist who wrote: “How good and how pleasant it is for brothers to dwell together in unity!” ([Ps. 133:1]) When we love our brothers and sisters, we prove to Jehovah that we love him. ([1 John 4:20]) How pleasant it is to be part of a family of brothers and sisters who are “kind to one another, tenderly compassionate”!—[Eph. 4:32]. w20.02 9 ¶6-7

^ (Ps. 40:5) How many things you have done, O Jehovah my God, Your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us. None can compare to you; If I were to try to tell and speak of them, They would be too numerous to recount!

^ (2 Tim. 3:1, 2) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal,

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Ps. 133:1) Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!

^ (1 John 4:20) If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar. For the one who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen.

^ (Eph. 4:32) But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

Monday, August 2

Quite a number of those who practiced magical arts brought their books together and burned them up before everybody.—[Acts 19:19].

These individuals were serious about resisting wicked spirits. Their books about magic cost a lot of money. But instead of giving those books away or selling them to others, they destroyed them. They were more concerned about pleasing Jehovah than about how much money the books were worth. How can we imitate the example of those first-century Christians? It would be wise to get rid of anything we may have that is connected with the occult. This includes amulets, charms, or other objects that people wear or own to try to protect themselves from wicked spirits. ([1 Cor. 10:21]) Examine your entertainment carefully. Ask yourself, ‘Does any of my entertainment involve spiritism?’ Be determined to make choices that will help you stay far away from anything Jehovah hates. We want to do our best to “maintain a clear conscience” before our God.—[Acts 24:16]. w19.04 22-23 ¶10-12

^ (Acts 19:19) Indeed, quite a number of those who practiced magical arts brought their books together and burned them up before everybody. And they calculated their value and found them worth 50,000 pieces of silver.

^ (1 Cor. 10:21) You cannot be drinking the cup of Jehovah and the cup of demons; you cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah” and the table of demons.

^ (Acts 24:16) Because of this I always strive to maintain a clear* conscience before God and men.

Or “blameless.”

Tuesday, August 3

Call the elders.—[Jas. 5:14].

The elders have a number of concerns when they receive a report of serious wrongdoing. They are primarily concerned with maintaining the sanctity of God’s name. (Lev. 22:31, 32;[Matt. 6:9]) They are also deeply concerned with the spiritual welfare of their brothers and sisters in the congregation and want to help any who have been victims of wrongdoing. In addition, if the wrongdoer is a part of the congregation, elders are concerned with trying to restore him if that is possible. (Jas. 5:14, 15) A Christian who gives in to wrong desire and commits a serious sin is spiritually sick. This means that he no longer has a healthy relationship with Jehovah. In a sense, the elders are spiritual physicians. They endeavor to make “the sick one [in this instance, the wrongdoer] well.” Their Scriptural counsel can help him to restore his relationship with God, but this is only possible if he is genuinely repentant.—[Acts 3:19;] 2 Cor. 2:5-10. w19.05 10 ¶10-11

^ (Jas. 5:14) Is there anyone sick among you? Let him call the elders of the congregation to him, and let them pray over him, applying oil to him in the name of Jehovah.*

See App. A5.

^ (Lev. 22:31, 32) “You must keep my commandments and carry them out. I am Jehovah. 32 You must not profane my holy name, and I must be sanctified in the midst of the Israelites. I am Jehovah, who is sanctifying you,

^ (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.

^ (Jas. 5:14, 15) Is there anyone sick among you? Let him call the elders of the congregation to him, and let them pray over him, applying oil to him in the name of Jehovah.* 15 And the prayer of faith will make the sick one* well, and Jehovah* will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.

See App. A5.

Or possibly, “tired one.”

See App. A5.

^ (Acts 3:19) “Repent, therefore, and turn around so as to get your sins blotted out, so that seasons of refreshing may come from Jehovah himself

^ (2 Cor. 2:5-10) Now if anyone has caused sadness, he has saddened, not me, but all of you to an extent—not to be too harsh in what I say. 6 This rebuke given by the majority is sufficient for such a man; 7 now you should instead kindly forgive and comfort him, so that he may not be overwhelmed by excessive sadness. 8 I therefore exhort you to confirm your love for him. 9 For this is also why I wrote to you: to determine whether you would give proof of your obedience in all things. 10 If you forgive anyone for anything, I do also. In fact, whatever I have forgiven (if I have forgiven anything) has been for your sake in Christ’s sight,

Wednesday, August 4

God . . . energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.—[Phil. 2:13].

Jehovah can give us the desire to act. Perhaps we learn of a particular need inside or outside our congregation. In response, we might ask ourselves, ‘How can I help to fill this need?’ Or maybe we have been invited to accept a challenging assignment, but we wonder if we can do it justice. Or after reading a portion of God’s Word, we may wonder, ‘How can I apply this Bible passage to help others?’ When Jehovah sees that we are willing to examine ourselves, he can give us the desire to follow through and act. Jehovah can also give us the power to act. ([Isa. 40:29]) He can enhance our natural abilities with his holy spirit. ([Ex. 35:30-35]) Through his organization, Jehovah may teach us how to perform certain tasks. If you are ever unsure about how to carry out an assignment, ask for help. Also, feel free to ask our generous heavenly Father for “power beyond what is normal.”—[2 Cor. 4:7;][Luke 11:13]. w19.10 21 ¶3-4

^ (Phil. 2:13) For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.

^ (Isa. 40:29) He gives power to the tired one And full might to those lacking strength.*

Or “dynamic energy.”

^ (Ex. 35:30-35) Then Moses said to the Israelites: “See, Jehovah has chosen Bezʹal·el the son of Uʹri the son of Hur of the tribe of Judah. 31 He has filled him with the spirit of God, giving him wisdom, understanding, and knowledge of every sort of craftsmanship 32 for making artistic designs, for working with gold, silver, and copper, 33 for cutting and setting stones, and for making all kinds of artistic wood products. 34 And he has put it into his heart to teach, he and O·hoʹli·ab the son of A·hisʹa·mach of the tribe of Dan. 35 He has filled them with skill* to do all the work of a craftsman, an embroiderer, and a weaver using blue thread, purple wool, scarlet material, and fine linen, and of a loom worker. These men will do every sort of work and prepare every sort of design.

Lit., “wisdom of heart.”

^ (2 Cor. 4:7) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels, so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us.

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

Monday, August 9

Happy are you whenever men hate you, and when they exclude you and reproach you and denounce your name as wicked for the sake of the Son of man.—[Luke 6:22].

What did Jesus mean? Jesus was not saying that Christians would enjoy being hated. Instead, he was being realistic. We are no part of the world. We live according to Jesus’ teachings and preach the message that he preached. As a result, the world hates us. (John 15:18-21) We want to please Jehovah. If men hate us because we love our Father, that is their problem. We must not make the mistake of measuring our worth by how popular we are. We do not know when a wave of persecution or even an outright ban will affect our worship of Jehovah. However, we do know that we can prepare now by strengthening our relationship with Jehovah, by building up our courage, and by learning to cope with hatred from men. The preparations that we make now will help us stand firm in the future. w19.07 6 ¶17-18; 7 ¶21

^ (Luke 6:22) “Happy are you whenever men hate you, and when they exclude you and reproach* you and denounce* your name as wicked for the sake of the Son of man.

Or “insult.”

Or “cast out.”

^ (John 15:18-21) If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before it hated you. 19 If you were part of the world, the world would be fond of what is its own. Now because you are no part of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, for this reason the world hates you. 20 Keep in mind the word I said to you: A slave is not greater than his master. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have observed my word, they will also observe yours. 21 But they will do all these things against you on account of my name, because they do not know the One who sent me.

Tuesday, August 10

Whoever approaches God must believe that he is.—[Heb. 11:6].

When we conduct Bible studies with people from nonreligious backgrounds, we must continually build up their belief in the existence of God. And we need to help them to build faith in the Bible. This might require that we repeat some points a number of times. During each study session, we may need to discuss evidence that the Bible is God’s Word by pointing to fulfilled prophecies, scientific and historical accuracy, or practical wisdom. We help people to become disciples of Christ by displaying love for them, whether they are religious or not. ([1 Cor. 13:1]) As we teach them, our goal is to show that God loves us and wants us to love him. Every year thousands who previously had little or no interest in religion get baptized because they have grown to love God. So be positive, and take a loving interest in all sorts of people. Listen to them. Try to understand them. By your example, teach them to be disciples of Christ. w19.07 24 ¶16-17

^ (Heb. 11:6) Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is* and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

Or “exists.”

^ (1 Cor. 13:1) If I speak in the tongues of men and of angels but do not have love, I have become a clanging gong or a clashing cymbal.

Wednesday, August 11

Do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.—[Heb. 13:16].

The daughters of Shallum were among those whom Jehovah used to share in repairing the walls of Jerusalem. ([Neh. 2:20;][3:12]) Although their father was a prince, Shallum’s daughters were willing to do that difficult and dangerous work. ([Neh. 4:15-18]) In our day, willing sisters are happy to help perform a special form of sacred service—the construction and maintenance of buildings that are dedicated to Jehovah. Their skill, enthusiasm, and loyalty are vital to the success of this work. Jehovah motivated Tabitha to abound in “good deeds and gifts of mercy,” particularly in behalf of widows. ([Acts 9:36]) Because of her outstanding generosity and kindness, many mourned when she died. But they were overjoyed when the apostle Peter resurrected her. ([Acts 9:39-41]) What do we learn from Tabitha? Whether young or old, male or female, we can all do practical things to help our brothers and sisters. w19.10 23 ¶11-12

^ (Heb. 13:16) Moreover, do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.

^ (Neh. 2:20) However, I replied: “The God of the heavens is the One who will grant us success, and we his servants will get up and build; but you have neither share nor claim nor memorial* in Jerusalem.”

Or “entitlement.”

^ (Neh. 3:12) And next to them Shalʹlum the son of Hal·loʹhesh, a prince of half the district of Jerusalem, did repair work, along with his daughters.

^ (Neh. 4:15-18) Now after our enemies heard that what they were doing had become known to us and that the true God had frustrated their plan, we all went back to work on the wall. 16 From that day forward, half of my men would do the work and half of them would hold the lances, the shields, the bows, and the coats of mail. And the princes stood behind the whole house of Judah 17 who were building the wall. Those who were carrying the loads did the work with one hand while holding a weapon* in the other hand. 18 And each of the builders had a sword strapped to his hip while building, and the one to blow the horn stood beside me.

Or “missile.”

^ (Acts 9:36) Now there was in Jopʹpa a disciple named Tabʹi·tha, which means, when translated, “Dorʹcas.” She abounded in good deeds and gifts of mercy that she was making.

^ (Acts 9:39-41) At that Peter got up and went with them. And when he arrived, they led him up into the upper room; and all the widows presented themselves to him, weeping and showing many garments and robes that Dorʹcas had made while she was with them. 40 Peter then put everyone outside, and kneeling down, he prayed. Then turning toward the body, he said: “Tabʹi·tha, rise!” She opened her eyes, and as she caught sight of Peter, she sat up. 41 Giving her his hand, he raised her up, and he called the holy ones and the widows and presented her alive.

Friday, August 13

I am the least of the apostles, and I am not worthy of being called an apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.—[1 Cor. 15:9].

People who appear confident or forthright are not necessarily proud. (John 1:46, 47) Yet, whether we are outgoing or not, all of us must work at developing a humble heart condition. Consider the example of the apostle Paul. He was used mightily by Jehovah to establish new congregations in one city after another. He may even have accomplished more in the ministry than any other apostle of Jesus Christ. Yet, Paul did not elevate himself among his brothers. He correctly attributed his fine standing with Jehovah, not to his own qualities or works, but to God’s undeserved kindness. ([1 Cor. 15:10]) What a fine lesson in humility Paul gave in his letter to the Corinthians—especially when we recall that some men in the congregation were seeking to prove themselves to be superior to Paul!—[2 Cor. 10:10]. w19.09 3 ¶5-6

^ (1 Cor. 15:9) For I am the least of the apostles, and I am not worthy of being called an apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.

^ (John 1:46, 47) But Na·thanʹa·el said to him: “Can anything good come out of Nazʹa·reth?” Philip said to him: “Come and see.” 47 Jesus saw Na·thanʹa·el coming toward him and said about him: “See, truly an Israelite in whom there is no deceit.”

^ (1 Cor. 15:10) But by God’s undeserved kindness I am what I am. And his undeserved kindness to me was not in vain, but I labored more than all of them; yet it was not I, but the undeserved kindness of God that is with me.

^ (2 Cor. 10:10) For they say: “His letters are weighty and forceful, but his presence in person is weak and his speech contemptible.”

Sunday, August 15

Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, . . . and come be my follower.—[Mark 10:21].

We must be realistic. Each of us has a certain amount of energy. So we must be careful about what we take on. For example, we could waste energy trying to gather material possessions. Note what Jesus said to a rich young man who asked him: “What must I do to inherit everlasting life?” He must have been a decent man because Mark’s Gospel account specifically states that Jesus “felt love for him.” Jesus presented the young ruler with the invitation above. The man was torn, but it appears that he could not let go of his “many possessions.” (Mark 10:17-22) As a result, he rejected the yoke that Jesus had offered him and continued to slave “for Riches.” ([Matt. 6:24]) What choice would you have made? From time to time, it is good for us to reassess our priorities in life. Why? So that we can make sure that we are using our energy wisely. w19.09 24 ¶17-18

^ (Mark 10:21) Jesus looked at him and felt love for him and said, “One thing is missing about you: Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come be my follower.”

^ (Mark 10:17-22) As he was going on his way, a man ran up and fell on his knees before him and put the question to him: “Good Teacher, what must I do to inherit everlasting life?” 18 Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good except one, God. 19 You know the commandments: ‘Do not murder, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not bear false witness, do not defraud, honor your father and your mother.’” 20 The man said to him: “Teacher, all these things I have kept from my youth on.” 21 Jesus looked at him and felt love for him and said, “One thing is missing about you: Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come be my follower.” 22 But he grew sad at the answer and went away grieved, for he had many possessions.

^ (Matt. 6:24) “No one can slave for two masters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. You cannot slave for God and for Riches.

Wednesday, August 18

Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

Whether we have little or much materially, we need to guard our heart. How? Do not develop a love for riches. And do not allow your secular work to take priority over your service to Jehovah. How can you know if that is happening to you? Some questions you could ask yourself are: ‘Do I often think about my secular work when I am at meetings or in the ministry? Do I constantly worry about being financially secure in the future? Are money and material possessions causing problems for me and my mate? Would I be willing to do secular work that others look down on if it allowed me to spend more time serving Jehovah?’ (1 Tim. 6:9-12) When considering those questions, let us remember that Jehovah loves us and makes this promise to those who are devoted to him: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.” That is why the apostle Paul wrote: “Let your way of life be free of the love of money.”—[Heb. 13:5, 6]. w19.10 29 ¶10

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (1 Tim. 6:9-12) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains. 11 However, you, O man of God, flee from these things. But pursue righteousness, godly devotion, faith, love, endurance, and mildness. 12 Fight the fine fight of the faith; get a firm hold on the everlasting life for which you were called and you offered the fine public declaration in front of many witnesses.

^ (Heb. 13:5, 6) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.” 6 So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

Sunday, August 22

Jehovah spoke to Moses face-to-face, just as one man would speak to another man.—[Ex. 33:11].

When Moses was asked to lead the nation of Israel out of captivity, he lacked confidence and repeatedly told Jehovah that he felt unqualified. God responded with real compassion, providing help for Moses. ([Ex. 4:10-16]) As a result, Moses was able to deliver powerful judgment messages to Pharaoh. Moses then saw Jehovah use His power as He saved the Israelites but destroyed Pharaoh and his forces in the Red Sea. (Ex. 14:26-31;[Ps. 136:15]) After Moses led the Israelites out of Egypt, they constantly found things to complain about. Even so, Moses observed Jehovah’s great patience in dealing with the people He had freed from slavery. ([Ps. 78:40-43]) Moses also saw Jehovah show remarkable humility when He changed His mind after Moses asked Him to do so. ([Ex. 32:9-14]) After the Exodus, Moses’ relationship with Jehovah became so close that it was as if he could see his heavenly Father.—[Heb. 11:27]. w19.12 17 ¶7-9

^ (Ex. 33:11) Jehovah spoke to Moses face-to-face, just as one man would speak to another man. When he returned to the camp, Joshua the son of Nun, his minister and attendant, would not depart from the tent.

^ (Ex. 4:10-16) Moses now said to Jehovah: “Pardon me, Jehovah, but I have never been a fluent speaker, neither in the past nor since you have spoken to your servant, for I am slow of speech* and slow of tongue.” 11 Jehovah said to him: “Who made a mouth for man, or who makes them speechless, deaf, clear-sighted, or blind? Is it not I, Jehovah? 12 So go now, and I will be with you as you speak,* and I will teach you what you should say.” 13 But he said: “Pardon me, Jehovah, please send anyone whom you want to send.” 14 Then Jehovah’s anger blazed against Moses, and he said: “What about your brother Aaron the Levite? I know that he can speak very well. And he is now on his way here to meet you. When he sees you, his heart will rejoice. 15 So you must speak to him and put the words in his mouth, and I will be with you and him as you speak, and I will teach you men what to do. 16 He will speak for you to the people, and he will be your spokesman, and you will serve as God to him.*

Lit., “heavy of mouth.”

Lit., “with your mouth.”

Or “will be representing God to him.”

^ (Ex. 14:26-31) Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Stretch out your hand over the sea so that the waters may come back over the Egyptians, their war chariots, and their cavalrymen.” 27 Moses at once stretched out his hand over the sea, and as morning approached, the sea returned to its normal condition. As the Egyptians fled from it, Jehovah shook the Egyptians off into the midst of the sea. 28 The returning waters covered the war chariots and the cavalrymen and all of Pharʹaoh’s army who had gone into the sea after them. Not so much as one among them was allowed to survive. 29 But the Israelites walked on dry ground in the midst of the seabed, and the waters formed a wall on their right hand and on their left. 30 Thus Jehovah saved Israel on that day from the hand of the Egyptians, and Israel saw the Egyptians dead on the seashore. 31 Israel also saw the great power* that Jehovah wielded against the Egyptians, and the people began to fear Jehovah and to put faith in Jehovah and in his servant Moses.

Lit., “hand.”

^ (Ps. 136:15) He shook off Pharʹaoh and his army into the Red Sea, For his loyal love endures forever.

^ (Ps. 78:40-43) How often they rebelled against him in the wilderness And made him feel hurt in the desert! 41 Again and again they put God to the test, And they grieved* the Holy One of Israel. 42 They did not remember his power,* The day that he rescued* them from the adversary, 43 How he displayed his signs in Egypt And his miracles in the region of Zoʹan,

Or “pained.”

Lit., “hand.”

Lit., “redeemed.”

^ (Ex. 32:9-14) Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “I have seen that this is an obstinate* people. 10 So now let me be, and I will exterminate them in my burning anger, and let me make a great nation from you instead.” 11 Then Moses appealed to* Jehovah his God and said: “Why, O Jehovah, should you turn your burning anger against your people after bringing them out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a mighty hand? 12 Why should the Egyptians say, ‘He had evil intentions when he led them out. He wanted to kill them in the mountains and exterminate them from the surface of the earth’? Turn from your burning anger and reconsider* your decision to bring this calamity on your people. 13 Remember your servants Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, to whom you swore by yourself and said: ‘I will multiply your offspring* like the stars of the heavens, and I will give all this land that I have designated to your offspring,* so that they may take it as a permanent possession.’” 14 So Jehovah began to reconsider* the calamity that he had spoken of bringing on his people.

Lit., “stiff-necked.”

Or “softened the face of.”

Or “feel regret over.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “felt regret over.”

^ (Heb. 11:27) By faith he left Egypt, but not fearing the anger of the king, for he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible.

Monday, August 23

He is going ahead of you into Galilee. You will see him there.—[Matt. 28:7].

Most of Jesus’ disciples were Galileans. So a mountain in Galilee—rather than a private home in Jerusalem—would be a reasonable place to gather with a large number of people. Also, the resurrected Jesus had already met with his 11 apostles in a private home in Jerusalem. If Jesus wanted to instruct only the apostles to preach and make disciples, he could have done that in Jerusalem instead of asking them and the women and others to meet him in Galilee. ([Luke 24:33,][36]) Jesus’ command to make disciples was not limited to Christians living in the first century. How do we know? Jesus concluded his instructions to his followers with the words: “I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.” (Matt. 28:19, 20) Today the disciple-making work is in full swing. Think of it! Nearly 300,000 people each year get baptized as Jehovah’s Witnesses and become disciples of Jesus Christ! w20.01 2 ¶1; 3 ¶5-6

^ (Matt. 28:7) Then go quickly and tell his disciples that he was raised up from the dead, for look! he is going ahead of you into Galʹi·lee. You will see him there. Look! I have told you.”

^ (Luke 24:33) And they got up in that very hour and returned to Jerusalem, and they found the Eleven and those assembled together with them,

^ (Luke 24:36) While they were speaking of these things, he himself stood in their midst and said to them: “May you have peace.”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Tuesday, August 24

He remembered us when we were low.—[Ps. 136:23].

Young, but diagnosed with a debilitating disease. Getting older and unable to find work. Being elderly and becoming increasingly limited in what you can do in Jehovah’s service. If you are experiencing something like one of the situations just mentioned, you may feel that you are not useful anymore. Those situations can rob you of joy, destroy your self-respect, and interfere with your relationships with other people. This world reflects Satan’s view of human life. Satan has always treated humans as if they were of little value. He heartlessly offered Eve a path to freedom, knowing full well that the penalty for disobeying God was death. Satan has always controlled this world. So it is not surprising that many of its leaders reflect his lack of respect for human life and dignity. Jehovah, on the other hand, wants us to feel good about ourselves, and he supports us when we face situations that could make us feel worthless.—[Rom. 12:3]. w20.01 14 ¶1-4

^ (Ps. 136:23) He remembered us when we were low, For his loyal love endures forever.

^ (Rom. 12:3) For through the undeserved kindness given to me, I tell everyone there among you not to think more of himself than it is necessary to think, but to think so as to have a sound mind, each one as God has given* to him a measure of faith.

Or “apportioned; distributed.”

Thursday, August 26

Whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.—[Matt. 23:12].

How should we treat anointed brothers and sisters? It would be wrong to admire a person too much, even if he is an anointed brother of Christ. (Matt. 23:8-11) When the Bible speaks of the elders, it encourages us to “imitate their faith,” but it does not tell us that we can make any human our leader. ([Heb. 13:7]) It is true that the Bible says that some are “worthy of double honor.” But this is because they “preside in a fine way” and “work hard in speaking and teaching,” not because they are anointed. ([1 Tim. 5:17]) If we give anointed ones too much praise and attention, we could embarrass them. Or even worse, we could cause them to become proud. ([Rom. 12:3]) None of us would want to do anything that might cause one of Christ’s anointed brothers to make such a serious mistake!—[Luke 17:2]. w20.01 29 ¶8

^ (Matt. 23:12) Whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.

^ (Matt. 23:8-11) But you, do not you be called Rabbi, for one is your Teacher, and all of you are brothers. 9 Moreover, do not call anyone your father on earth, for one is your Father, the heavenly One. 10 Neither be called leaders, for your Leader is one, the Christ. 11 But the greatest one among you must be your minister.

^ (Heb. 13:7) Remember those who are taking the lead among you, who have spoken the word of God to you, and as you contemplate how their conduct turns out, imitate their faith.

^ (1 Tim. 5:17) Let the elders who preside in a fine way be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who work hard in speaking and teaching.

^ (Rom. 12:3) For through the undeserved kindness given to me, I tell everyone there among you not to think more of himself than it is necessary to think, but to think so as to have a sound mind, each one as God has given* to him a measure of faith.

Or “apportioned; distributed.”

^ (Luke 17:2) It would be more advantageous for him if a millstone were hung from his neck and he were thrown into the sea than for him to stumble one of these little ones.

Friday, August 27

Besides those things of an external kind, there is . . . the anxiety for all the congregations.—[2 Cor. 11:28].

The apostle Paul had many reasons for feeling anxious. The problems his brothers and sisters faced weighed heavily on his mind. ([2 Cor. 2:4]) Opposers beat him and threw him in prison. He also had to endure hardships that caused anxiety, such as being “low on provisions.” ([Phil. 4:12]) And considering that he had been shipwrecked at least three times at that point in his life, we can only imagine the anxiety he experienced when traveling by boat. (2 Cor. 11:23-27) How did Paul deal with the anxiety? Paul felt anxious for his brothers and sisters when they faced challenges, but he did not try to fix all their problems by himself. Paul was modest. He arranged for others to help in caring for the congregation, trustworthy men such as Timothy and Titus. The work those brothers did no doubt helped to reduce Paul’s anxiety.—Phil. 2:19, 20;[Titus 1:1,][4, 5]. w20.02 23 ¶11-12

^ (2 Cor. 11:28) Besides those things of an external kind, there is what rushes in on me from day to day:* the anxiety for all the congregations.

Or “the daily pressure on me.”

^ (2 Cor. 2:4) For out of much tribulation and anguish of heart I wrote you with many tears, not to sadden you, but to let you know the depth of love I have for you.

^ (Phil. 4:12) I know how to be low on provisions and how to have an abundance. In everything and in all circumstances I have learned the secret of both how to be full and how to hunger, both how to have an abundance and how to do without.

^ (2 Cor. 11:23-27) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths. 24 Five times I received 40 strokes less one from the Jews, 25 three times I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, three times I experienced shipwreck, a night and a day I have spent in the open sea; 26 in journeys often, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from my own people, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers among false brothers, 27 in labor and toil, in sleepless nights often, in hunger and thirst, frequently without food, in cold and lacking clothing.

^ (Phil. 2:19, 20) Now I am hoping in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you shortly, so that I may be encouraged when I receive news about you. 20 For I have no one else of a disposition like his who will genuinely care for your concerns.

^ (Titus 1:1) Paul, a slave of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ according to the faith of God’s chosen ones and the accurate knowledge of the truth that is according to godly devotion

^ (Titus 1:4, 5) to Titus, a genuine child according to the faith we share: May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior. 5 I left you in Crete so that you would correct the things that were defective* and make appointments of elders in city after city, as I instructed you:

Or “deficient.”

Sunday, August 29

Let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl.—[1 Sam. 25:24].

Like Abigail, we need to have the courage to speak up if we see someone heading down a dangerous path. ([Ps. 141:5]) We must be respectful, but we must also be bold. When we lovingly offer a person necessary counsel, we prove that we are a true friend. ([Prov. 27:17]) Elders in particular must have the courage to speak to those in the congregation who take a false step. ([Gal. 6:1]) Elders humbly realize that they too are imperfect and may one day need counsel. But elders do not let that hold them back from reproving those who need discipline. ([2 Tim. 4:2;][Titus 1:9]) When counseling a person, they try to use their gift of speech to teach him skillfully and patiently. They love their brother, and that love moves them to action. ([Prov. 13:24]) But their primary concern is to honor Jehovah by upholding his standards and protecting the congregation from harm.—[Acts 20:28]. w20.03 20 ¶8-9

^ (1 Sam. 25:24) She then fell at his feet and said: “My lord, let the blame be on me; let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl.

^ (Ps. 141:5) Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love; Should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head, Which my head would never refuse. My prayer will continue even during their calamities.

^ (Prov. 27:17) As iron sharpens iron, So one man sharpens his friend.*

Lit., “the face of his friend.”

^ (Gal. 6:1) Brothers, even if a man takes a false step before he is aware of it, you who have spiritual qualifications try to readjust such a man in a spirit of mildness. But keep an eye on yourself, for fear you too may be tempted.

^ (2 Tim. 4:2) Preach the word; be at it urgently in favorable times and difficult times; reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all patience and art of teaching.

^ (Titus 1:9) holding firmly to the faithful word* as respects his art of teaching, so that he may be able both to encourage* by the teaching that is wholesome* and to reprove those who contradict.

Or “the trustworthy message.”

Or “exhort.”

Or “healthful; beneficial.”

^ (Prov. 13:24) Whoever holds back his rod* hates his son, But the one who loves him disciplines him diligently.*

Or “discipline; punishment.”

Or possibly, “promptly.”

^ (Acts 20:28) Pay attention to yourselves and to all the flock, among which the holy spirit has appointed you overseers, to shepherd the congregation of God, which he purchased with the blood of his own Son.

Monday, August 30

For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.—[Phil. 4:13].

Jehovah caused Moses to become a deliverer of the Israelites. But when did Jehovah use him? Was it when Moses felt qualified after being “instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians”? ([Acts 7:22-25]) No, Jehovah used Moses only after He had shaped him into a humble, mild-tempered man. ([Acts 7:30,][34-36]) Jehovah gave Moses the courage to stand before the most powerful ruler in Egypt. ([Ex. 9:13-19]) From this we see that Jehovah uses those who display godly qualities and who rely on him for strength. Throughout history, Jehovah has caused his servants to fulfill many different roles. What will he cause you to become? Much depends on how willing you are to exert yourself. ([Col. 1:29]) If you make yourself available, Jehovah can cause you to become a zealous evangelizer, an effective teacher, a capable comforter, a skilled worker, a supportive friend, or whatever else he needs to accomplish his will. w19.10 21 ¶5; 25 ¶14

^ (Phil. 4:13) For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^ (Acts 7:22-25) So Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians. In fact, he was powerful in his words and deeds. 23 “Now when he reached the age of 40, it came into his heart to make a visit on* his brothers, the sons of Israel. 24 When he caught sight of one of them being unjustly treated, he defended him and avenged the one being abused by striking down the Egyptian. 25 He thought that his brothers would grasp that God was giving them salvation by his hand, but they did not grasp it.

Or “to check the conditions of.”

^ (Acts 7:30) “After 40 years had passed, an angel appeared to him in the wilderness of Mount Siʹnai in the flame of a burning thornbush.

^ (Acts 7:34-36) I have certainly seen the oppression of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning, and I have come down to rescue them. Now come, I will send you off to Egypt.’ 35 This same Moses whom they had disowned, saying: ‘Who appointed you ruler and judge?’ is the very one God sent as both ruler and deliverer by means of the angel who appeared to him in the thornbush. 36 This man led them out, performing wonders and signs in Egypt and at the Red Sea and in the wilderness for 40 years.

^ (Ex. 9:13-19) Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Get up early in the morning and station yourself in front of Pharʹaoh, and say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has said: “Send my people away so that they may serve me. 14 For now I am directing all my blows to strike your heart, your servants, and your people, so that you may know that there is no one like me in all the earth. 15 For by now I could have thrust my hand out to strike you and your people with a devastating plague, and you would have been wiped out* from the earth. 16 But for this very reason I have kept you in existence: to show you my power and to have my name declared in all the earth. 17 Are you still behaving arrogantly against my people by not sending them away? 18 Here I will cause a very great hail to rain down tomorrow about this time, such as has never occurred in Egypt from the day it was founded until now. 19 Therefore, send word to bring all your livestock and all that is yours in the field under shelter. Every man and beast caught in the field and not brought into the house will die when the hail comes down on them.”’”

Or “effaced.”

^ (Col. 1:29) To this end I am indeed working hard, exerting myself with his strength that is operating powerfully within me.

Saturday, September 4

The wisdom of this world is foolishness with God.—[1 Cor. 3:19].

The Bible instructs the husband and wife to honor each other and their marriage vows. It encourages marriage mates to have a deep sense of commitment to each other, stating: “A man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to his wife, and they will become one flesh.” ([Gen. 2:24]) In contrast, those influenced by the wisdom of the world promote a different view, saying that each spouse should focus on his or her own needs. “In some ceremonies,” notes one book about divorce, “the traditional pledge to marry for ‘as long as we both shall live’ was replaced with the more limited promise to marry for ‘as long as we both shall love.’” Such a casual view of marriage has led to countless broken families and has caused immeasurable emotional harm. Without a doubt, the world’s disrespectful view of marriage is a foolish teaching. w19.05 23 ¶12

^ (1 Cor. 3:19) For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.”

^ (Gen. 2:24) That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and they will become one flesh.

Or “remain with.”

Wednesday, September 8

It is lawful to do a fine thing on the Sabbath.—[Matt. 12:12].

Jesus and his Jewish followers observed the Sabbath because they were under the Mosaic Law. But Jesus showed by word and deed that keeping the Sabbath was to be reasonable and that kind and helpful actions were allowable. (Matt. 12:9-11) He did not view performing kind and helpful actions as a violation of the Sabbath. Jesus’ actions highlighted a key feature of the Sabbath. Because God’s people rested from their daily labor, they were able to focus on spiritual things. Jesus grew up in a family that must have used the Sabbath for spiritual benefit. That is reflected in what we read about Jesus when he was in his hometown of Nazareth: “According to [Jesus’] custom on the Sabbath day, he entered the synagogue and stood up to read.” ([Luke 4:15-19]) Also, his disciples had so much respect for the Sabbath law that they stopped preparations for Jesus’ burial until the Sabbath day was over.—Luke 23:55, 56. w19.12 4 ¶10

^ (Matt. 12:12) How much more valuable is a man than a sheep! So it is lawful to do a fine thing on the Sabbath.”

^ (Matt. 12:9-11) After departing from that place, he went into their synagogue, 10 and look! there was a man with a withered* hand! So they asked him, “Is it lawful to cure on the Sabbath?” so that they might accuse him. 11 He said to them: “If you have one sheep and that sheep falls into a pit on the Sabbath, is there a man among you who will not grab hold of it and lift it out?

Or “paralyzed.”

^ (Luke 4:15-19) Also, he began to teach in their synagogues, and he was held in honor by all. 16 He then went to Nazʹa·reth, where he had been brought up, and according to his custom on the Sabbath day, he entered the synagogue and stood up to read. 17 So the scroll of the prophet Isaiah was handed to him, and he opened the scroll and found the place where it was written: 18 “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor. He sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away free, 19 to preach Jehovah’s acceptable year.”

^ (Luke 23:55, 56) But the women who had come with him from Galʹi·lee followed along and took a look at the tomb and saw how his body was laid, 56 and they went back to prepare spices and perfumed oils. But, of course, they rested on the Sabbath according to the commandment.

Thursday, September 9

You had no hope.—[Eph. 2:12].

Every Christian minister is involved in helping to find honesthearted ones. We could liken this work to finding a lost child. In what way? Consider the real-life example of a three-year-old boy who wandered away from home. About 500 people were involved in searching for him. Finally, some 20 hours after the child went missing, a volunteer discovered the little boy in a cornfield. That volunteer refused to take credit for locating the boy. He said: “It took hundreds of people to find him.” Many people are like that child. They feel lost. They have no hope, but they want help. Over eight million of us are involved in trying to find these deserving ones. You may not personally find someone who will study the Bible with you. However, other publishers working the same territory may find someone who wants to learn the truth found in God’s Word. When a brother or sister meets someone who becomes a disciple of Christ, everyone who shared in the search has good reason to rejoice. w19.07 16-17 ¶9-10

^ (Eph. 2:12) At that time you were without Christ, alienated from the state of Israel, strangers to the covenants of the promise; you had no hope and were without God in the world.

Friday, September 10

I am pressing on toward the goal.—[Phil. 3:14].

The apostle Paul reminded the Christians in Philippi of the need to keep running with endurance. The congregation faced hostility from the start. It all began when, in response to the divine invitation to “step over into Macedonia,” Paul and Silas arrived in Philippi about 50 C.E. ([Acts 16:9]) There they found a woman named Lydia, who “was listening, and Jehovah opened her heart wide” to the good news. ([Acts 16:14]) She soon got baptized along with her household. However, the Devil was not idle. Men of the city dragged Paul and Silas before the civil magistrates and falsely accused them of causing a disturbance. As a result, Paul and Silas were beaten, imprisoned, and later urged to leave the city. (Acts 16:16-40) Did they give up? Never! And what about the brothers and sisters in the newly formed congregation? Commendably, they too endured! No doubt they were greatly encouraged by the good example that Paul and Silas set for them. w19.08 2 ¶1-2

^ (Phil. 3:14) I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus.

^ (Acts 16:9) And during the night a vision appeared to Paul—a Mac·e·doʹni·an man was standing there urging him and saying: “Step over into Mac·e·doʹni·a and help us.”

^ (Acts 16:14) And a woman named Lydʹi·a, a seller of purple from the city of Thy·a·tiʹra and a worshipper of God, was listening, and Jehovah opened her heart wide to pay attention to the things Paul was saying.

Sunday, September 12

Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time.—[1 Pet. 5:6].

The most important reason for us to cultivate humility is that it pleases Jehovah. The apostle Peter made this clear when he wrote the words of today’s text. Commenting on Peter’s words, the book “Come Be My Follower” says in chapter 3, paragraph 23: “Haughtiness is like poison. The effects can be devastating. It is a quality that can render the most gifted human useless to God. Humility, on the other hand, can make even the least one very useful to Jehovah. . . . [He] will . . . delight in rewarding you for your humility.” Really, could we hope for anything better than to bring joy to Jehovah’s heart? ([Prov. 23:15]) Besides pleasing Jehovah, we receive many benefits when we cultivate humility. Humility draws other people to us. To understand why, put yourself in the shoes of others.—[Matt. 7:12]. w19.09 4 ¶8-9

^ (1 Pet. 5:6) Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time,

^ (Prov. 23:15) My son, if your heart becomes wise, Then my own heart will rejoice.

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

Tuesday, September 14

Take my yoke upon you.—[Matt. 11:29].

To find refreshment under Jesus’ yoke, we must keep the right perspective. We are doing Jehovah’s work, so it must be done Jehovah’s way. We are the workers, and Jehovah is the Master. ([Luke 17:10]) If we try to do his work our way, we will find ourselves fighting against the yoke. On the other hand, we can do extraordinary things and overcome any obstacle if we follow Jehovah’s guidance. Remember that nobody can stop his will from being accomplished! ([Rom. 8:31;][1 John 4:4]) Our goal is to bring glory to our loving Father, Jehovah. Those in the first century who were motivated by greed or self-interest soon became unhappy and abandoned Jesus’ yoke. (John 6:25-27,[51,][60,][66;] Phil. 3:18, 19) By contrast, those who were motivated by an unselfish love of God and love of neighbor happily carried that yoke throughout their life on earth, with the prospect of serving with Christ in heaven. Like them, we will remain happy by carrying Jesus’ yoke with the right motive. w19.09 20 ¶1; 24-25 ¶19-20

^ (Matt. 11:29) Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (Luke 17:10) Likewise, when you have done all the things assigned to you, say: ‘We are good-for-nothing slaves. What we have done is what we ought to have done.’”

^ (Rom. 8:31) What, then, are we to say about these things? If God is for us, who will be* against us?

Or “can be; is.”

^ (1 John 4:4) You originate with God, little children, and you have conquered them, because the one who is in union with you is greater than the one who is in union with the world.

^ (John 6:25-27) When they found him across the sea, they said to him: “Rabbi, when did you get here?” 26 Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to you, you are looking for me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate from the loaves and were satisfied. 27 Work, not for the food that perishes, but for the food that remains for everlasting life, which the Son of man will give you; for on this one the Father, God himself, has put his seal of approval.”

^ (John 6:51) I am the living bread that came down from heaven. If anyone eats of this bread he will live forever; and for a fact, the bread that I will give is my flesh in behalf of the life of the world.”

^ (John 6:60) When they heard this, many of his disciples said: “This speech is shocking; who can listen to it?”

^ (John 6:66) Because of this, many of his disciples went off to the things behind and would no longer walk with him.

^ (Phil. 3:18, 19) For there are many—I used to mention them often but now I mention them also with weeping—who are walking as enemies of the torture stake* of the Christ. 19 Their end is destruction, and their god is their belly, and their glory is really their shame, and they have their minds on earthly things.

See Glossary.

Wednesday, September 15

You will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.—[John 8:32].

Think of the blessings you enjoy because you have been liberated from long-held unscriptural beliefs. What a joy to have such freedom! You can expect greater freedom to come. In the near future, Jesus will act decisively to eliminate false religion and corrupt human rulership. God will protect “a great crowd” who serve him, and then he will allow them to enjoy blessings in an earthly paradise. ([Rev. 7:9,][14]) A vast number will be resurrected and will have the opportunity to be liberated from all the effects of Adam’s sin. ([Acts 24:15]) During the Thousand Year Reign, Jesus and his corulers will help to raise mankind to perfect physical and spiritual health. This time of restoration and liberation will be like the Jubilee in Israel. The result for all on earth who serve Jehovah loyally will be human perfection, free from sin. w19.12 12-13 ¶14-16

^ (John 8:32) and you will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.”

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

^ (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

Friday, September 17

Whoever forgives a transgression seeks love, but the one who keeps harping on a matter separates close friends.—[Prov. 17:9].

Sometimes when we work closely with our friends, we become aware not only of their strengths but also of their weaknesses. What can help us deal with this challenge? Realistically, we cannot expect perfection from our brothers and sisters. Therefore, once we have formed close friendships, we need to work hard at keeping those newly formed bonds alive. If our friends make a mistake, we may need to give kind but frank counsel based on God’s Word. ([Ps. 141:5]) And if they hurt us, we need to forgive them. Once we have forgiven them, we must avoid the temptation to bring the offense up again in the future. How vital it is during these critical times to focus on the strengths of our brothers and sisters rather than on their weaknesses! Doing so strengthens the bond we share with them, and we will need close friends during the great tribulation. w19.11 6 ¶13, 16

^ (Prov. 17:9) Whoever forgives* a transgression seeks love, But the one who keeps harping on a matter separates close friends.

Lit., “covers over.”

^ (Ps. 141:5) Should the righteous one strike me, it would be an act of loyal love; Should he reprove me, it would be like oil on my head, Which my head would never refuse. My prayer will continue even during their calamities.

Sunday, September 19

He will . . . put the incense on the fire before Jehovah.—[Lev. 16:13].

On the yearly Day of Atonement, the nation of Israel came together and animal sacrifices were offered up. Those sacrifices helped to remind the Israelites that they needed to be cleansed of sin! First, though, the high priest had the task of pouring holy incense onto fiery coals and filling the room with a sweet-smelling aroma. What can we learn from that? The Bible indicates that the acceptable prayers of Jehovah’s faithful worshippers are like incense. ([Ps. 141:2;][Rev. 5:8]) It was with great respect that the high priest brought the incense into the presence of Jehovah. Similarly, when we approach Jehovah in prayer, we do so with deep respect. We are in awe of him. We deeply appreciate that our Creator allows us to approach him and draw close to him, as a child to a father. ([Jas. 4:8]) He accepts us as his friends! ([Ps. 25:14]) We appreciate this privilege so much that we would never want to disappoint him. w19.11 20-21 ¶3-5

^ (Lev. 16:13) He will also put the incense on the fire before Jehovah, and the cloud of the incense will envelop the Ark cover, which is on the Testimony, so that he may not die.

^ (Ps. 141:2) May my prayer be as incense prepared before you, My uplifted hands like the evening grain offering.

^ (Rev. 5:8) When he took the scroll, the four living creatures and the 24 elders fell down before the Lamb, and each one had a harp and golden bowls that were full of incense. (The incense means the prayers of the holy ones.)

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Ps. 25:14) Close friendship with Jehovah belongs to those who fear him, And he makes his covenant known to them.

Monday, September 20

How many your works are, O Jehovah! You have made all of them in wisdom. The earth is full of what you have made.—[Ps. 104:24].

How do most people where you live view work? In many countries, people are working harder and longer than ever before. Overworked people are often too busy to rest, to spend time with their families, or to satisfy their spiritual need. ([Eccl. 2:23]) On the other hand, some people do not like to work at all and make excuses for not working. (Prov. 26:13, 14) In contrast with the world’s unbalanced attitudes, consider the way that Jehovah and Jesus view work. There is no question that Jehovah is a worker. Jesus made that clear, saying: “My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.” ([John 5:17]) Think of all the work God did as he created countless spirit creatures and the vast universe. We also see ample evidence of God’s creative works on the beautiful earth where we live. w19.12 2 ¶1-2

^ (Ps. 104:24) How many your works are, O Jehovah! You have made all of them in wisdom. The earth is full of what you have made.

^ (Eccl. 2:23) For during all his days, his occupation brings pain and frustration, and even at night his heart does not rest. This too is futility.

^ (Prov. 26:13, 14) The lazy one says: “There is a young lion in the road, A lion in the public square!” 14 A door keeps turning on its hinges,* And the lazy one on his bed.

Or “pivot.”

^ (John 5:17) But he answered them: “My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.”

Wednesday, September 22

By faith Moses, when grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh’s daughter.—[Heb. 11:24].

Moses acted on what he learned. When he was about 40 years old, Moses chose to associate with God’s people, the Hebrews, rather than to be known as “the son of Pharaoh’s daughter.” Moses gave up a prominent position. By siding with the Hebrews, who were slaves in Egypt, he risked the wrath of Pharaoh, a powerful ruler who was viewed as a god. What an outstanding act of faith! Moses trusted in Jehovah. Such trust is a foundation stone of a lasting relationship. ([Prov. 3:5]) What is the lesson for us? Like Moses, all of us have a decision to make: Will we choose to serve God and associate with his people? We may have to make sacrifices to serve God, and we risk being opposed by those who do not know Jehovah. But if we trust in our heavenly Father, we can count on his support! w19.12 17 ¶5-6

^ (Heb. 11:24) By faith Moses, when grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharʹaoh’s daughter,

^ (Prov. 3:5) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.

Lit., “lean.”

Saturday, September 25

Become imitators of God, as beloved children.—[Eph. 5:1].

As Jehovah’s “beloved children,” we do our best to imitate him. We imitate his qualities by being loving, kind, and forgiving in our dealings with others. When those who do not know God see our fine conduct, they may be motivated to learn more about him. ([1 Pet. 2:12]) Christian parents have good reason to imitate Jehovah in the way they treat their children. When they do, their children may want to form their own friendship with our loving Father. We are proud of our heavenly Father, Jehovah, and want others to come to know him. In our heart, we all feel as did King David, who wrote: “I will boast in Jehovah.” ([Ps. 34:2]) What, though, if we are timid? How can we become bold? We grow bold when we focus on how happy we can make Jehovah and how much others will benefit from learning about him. Jehovah will give us the courage we need. He helped our first-century brothers to become bold, and he will help us too.—[1 Thess. 2:2]. w20.02 11 ¶12-13

^ (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

^ (1 Pet. 2:12) Maintain your conduct fine among the nations, so that when they accuse you of being wrongdoers, they may be eyewitnesses of your fine works and, as a result, glorify God in the day of his inspection.

^ (Ps. 34:2) I* will boast in Jehovah; The meek will hear and rejoice.

Or “My soul.”

^ (1 Thess. 2:2) For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness* by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.*

Or “courage.”

Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

Sunday, September 26

Go, therefore, and make disciples . . . , baptizing them.—[Matt. 28:19].

Many who study the Bible progress to baptism. However, some who regularly study the Bible with us seem reluctant to become disciples. They enjoy their studies, but they are not progressing to baptism. If you are conducting a Bible study, we are sure that you want to help your student to apply what he learns and to become a disciple of Christ. Jehovah wants people to serve him because they love him. So our goal is to help our students to understand that Jehovah cares deeply about them as individuals and that he loves them very much. We want to help them to see Jehovah as “a father of the fatherless and a protector of widows.” ([Ps. 68:5]) As your students come to appreciate God’s love for them, their heart will likely be touched and their own love for him will grow. So help your students to understand that our loving God wants them to gain everlasting life, and he is ready to help them to achieve that goal. w20.01 3 ¶7-8

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Ps. 68:5) A father of the fatherless and a protector* of widows Is God in his holy dwelling.

Lit., “judge.”

Monday, September 27

I received much joy and comfort on hearing of your love.—[Philem. 7].

The apostle Paul was humble, so he sought and received encouragement from his friends. He did not worry about being viewed as a weak person if he acknowledged that he had been comforted by others during times of distress. ([Col. 4:7-11]) When we humbly acknowledge that we need encouragement, our brothers and sisters will gladly give us the support we need. Paul knew that the Scriptures would comfort him. ([Rom. 15:4]) They would also give him wisdom to face any trial. (2 Tim. 3:15, 16) When imprisoned in Rome for the second time, Paul felt that his death was near. He asked Timothy to come to him quickly and bring “the scrolls.” (2 Tim. 4:6, 7,[9,][13]) Why? Because those scrolls were likely portions of the Hebrew Scriptures that Paul could use in his personal Bible study. When we imitate Paul by regularly studying God’s Word, Jehovah will use the Scriptures to soothe us—no matter what trials we face. w20.02 23-24 ¶14-15

^ (Philem. 7) For I received much joy and comfort on hearing of your love, because the hearts* of the holy ones have been refreshed through you, brother.

Or “tender affections.”

^ (Col. 4:7-11) Tychʹi·cus, my beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will tell you all the news about me. 8 I am sending him to you so that you will know how we are and that he may comfort your hearts. 9 He is coming along with O·nesʹi·mus, my faithful and beloved brother, who is from among you; they will tell you all the things happening here. 10 Ar·is·tarʹchus, my fellow captive, sends you his greetings, and so does Mark, the cousin of Barʹna·bas (concerning whom you received instructions to welcome him if he comes to you), 11 and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort* to me.

Or “a strengthening aid.”

^ (Rom. 15:4) For all the things that were written beforehand were written for our instruction, so that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope.

^ (2 Tim. 3:15, 16) and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus. 16 All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness,

Or “correcting.”

^ (2 Tim. 4:6, 7) For I am already being poured out like a drink offering, and the time for my releasing is imminent. 7 I have fought the fine fight, I have run the race to the finish, I have observed the faith.

^ (2 Tim. 4:9) Do your utmost to come to me shortly.

^ (2 Tim. 4:13) When you come, bring the cloak I left at Troʹas with Carpus, and the scrolls, especially the parchments.*

That is, the leather scrolls.

Tuesday, September 28

Stop judging that you may not be judged.—[Matt. 7:1].

Eliphaz, Bildad, and Zophar did not spend their time thinking about how they could help Job. Instead, they were thinking about how they could prove that Job had done something wrong. They made some accurate statements, but much of what they said about Job and about Jehovah was either unkind or untrue. They judged Job harshly. ([Job 32:1-3]) How did Jehovah respond? His anger burned hot against those three men. He called them foolish and made them ask Job to pray for them. ([Job 42:7-9]) We learn a number of lessons from the bad examples set by Eliphaz, Bildad, and Zophar. First, we should not judge our brothers. ([Matt. 7:2-5]) Instead, we should listen carefully to them before we speak. Only then will we be able to understand their situation. ([1 Pet. 3:8]) Second, when we do speak, we must make sure that our words are kind and our statements accurate. ([Eph. 4:25]) And third, Jehovah takes a keen interest in what we say to one another. w20.03 22-23 ¶15-16

^ (Matt. 7:1) “Stop judging that you may not be judged;

^ (Job 32:1-3) So these three men stopped trying to answer Job, because he was convinced of his own righteousness.* 2 But E·liʹhu the son of Barʹa·chel the Buzʹite of the family of Ram had become very angry. His anger blazed against Job for trying to prove himself* right rather than God. 3 He was also very angry with Job’s three companions because they could not find an answer but had declared God wicked.

Or “because he was righteous in his own eyes.”

Or “his soul.”

^ (Job 42:7-9) After Jehovah had spoken these words to Job, Jehovah said to Elʹi·phaz the Teʹman·ite: “My anger burns against you and your two companions, for you have not spoken the truth about me as my servant Job has. 8 Now take seven bulls and seven rams and go to my servant Job, and offer up a burnt sacrifice for yourselves. And my servant Job will pray for you. I will surely accept his request* not to deal with you according to your foolishness, for you have not spoken the truth about me as my servant Job has.” 9 So Elʹi·phaz the Teʹman·ite, Bilʹdad the Shuʹhite, and Zoʹphar the Naʹa·ma·thite went and did what Jehovah had told them to do. And Jehovah accepted Job’s prayer.

Lit., “Surely I will lift up his face.”

^ (Matt. 7:2-5) for with the judgment you are judging, you will be judged, and with the measure that you are measuring out, they will measure out to you. 3 Why, then, do you look at the straw in your brother’s eye but do not notice the rafter in your own eye? 4 Or how can you say to your brother, ‘Allow me to remove the straw from your eye,’ when look! a rafter is in your own eye? 5 Hypocrite! First remove the rafter from your own eye, and then you will see clearly how to remove the straw from your brother’s eye.

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (Eph. 4:25) Therefore, now that you have put away deceit, each one of you speak truth with his neighbor, because we are members belonging to one another.

Wednesday, September 29

Carry on prayer on every occasion.—[Eph. 6:18].

It is often when we are teaching others about Jehovah that we ourselves come to know him better. For example, we see direct evidence of Jehovah’s compassion when he guides us to those who have the right heart condition. ([John 6:44;][Acts 13:48]) We see the power of God’s Word at work as we watch those with whom we study break free from bad habits and begin to put on the new personality. ([Col. 3:9, 10]) And we see proof of God’s patience as he gives many in our territory numerous opportunities to learn about him and be saved. (Rom. 10:13-15) However, no matter how long we have been serving Jehovah, we should never take our relationship with him for granted. One of the most obvious ways we can prove that we value our friendship with God is by talking to him in prayer. Good communication is the lifeblood of a strong relationship. So draw close to God by praying often, never being afraid to express your innermost thoughts to him. w19.12 19 ¶11, 13-14

^ (Eph. 6:18) while with every form of prayer and supplication you carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit. And to that end stay awake, constantly making supplication in behalf of all the holy ones.

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (Col. 3:9, 10) Do not lie to one another. Strip off the old personality* with its practices, 10 and clothe yourselves with the new personality, which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it,

Lit., “man.”

^ (Rom. 10:13-15) For “everyone who calls on the name of Jehovah will be saved.” 14 However, how will they call on him if they have not put faith in him? How, in turn, will they put faith in him about whom they have not heard? How, in turn, will they hear without someone to preach? 15 How, in turn, will they preach unless they have been sent out? Just as it is written: “How beautiful are the feet of those who declare good news of good things!”

Thursday, September 30

Your sins have been forgiven.—[1 John 2:12].

What relief that thought brings to us! As King of God’s Kingdom, Jesus will undo any damage Satan and his system may inflict on us. ([Isa. 65:17;][1 John 3:8;] Rev. 21:3, 4) What hope that inspires in us! And even though Jesus has given us a challenging assignment, he is with us, supporting us through the last days of this system. (Matt. 28:19, 20) What courage that builds in us! Relief, hope, and courage—these are some of the solid foundation stones on which our peace of mind is built. How, then, can you retain your peace of mind when you are shaken by severe trials? You can do so by imitating the things Jesus did. First, pray and persist in prayer. Second, obey Jehovah and preach zealously even when it is difficult to do so. And third, look to your friends to help you through trials. Then the peace of God will guard your mind and heart. ([Phil. 4:6, 7]) And like Jesus, you will conquer any trial.—[John 16:33]. w19.04 13 ¶16-17

^ (1 John 2:12) I am writing you, little children, because your sins have been forgiven you for the sake of his name.

^ (Isa. 65:17) For look! I am creating new heavens and a new earth; And the former things will not be called to mind,* Nor will they come up into the heart.

Or “be remembered.”

^ (1 John 3:8) The one who practices sin originates with the Devil, because the Devil has been sinning from the beginning.* For this purpose the Son of God was made manifest, to break up* the works of the Devil.

Or “from when he began.”

Or “destroy.”

^ (Rev. 21:3, 4) With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ (John 16:33) I have said these things to you so that by means of me you may have peace. In the world you will have tribulation, but take courage! I have conquered the world.”

October

Friday, October 1

The eyes of Jehovah are roving about through all the earth to show his strength in behalf of those whose heart is complete toward him.—2 Chron. 16:9.

We see abundant evidence that Jehovah protects his people today. Consider: We are preaching and teaching the truth in all parts of the earth. (Matt. 28:19, 20) As a result, we expose the evil works of the Devil. Surely, if Satan were able to, he would stop all our activity, but he cannot. So we do not need to be terrified of wicked spirits. If we are faithful to Jehovah, the demons cannot cause us lasting harm. However, all of us need to resist wicked spirits and trust in Jehovah. If we do that, we will receive many blessings and we will avoid being misled by Satan’s lies. Also, we will not be paralyzed by fear of the demons. Above all, we will strengthen our friendship with Jehovah. “Oppose the Devil,” wrote the disciple James, “and he will flee from you. Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you.”—[Jas. 4:7, 8]. w19.04 24 ¶15; 25 ¶18

^ (2 Chron. 16:9) For the eyes of Jehovah are roving about through all the earth to show his strength* in behalf of those whose heart is complete toward* him. You have acted foolishly in this matter; from now on there will be wars against you.”

Or “support.”

Or “completely devoted to.”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Jas. 4:7, 8) Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you. 8 Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

Saturday, October 2

The fruit of the womb is a reward.—[Ps. 127:3].

Your children are a sacred trust, “an inheritance from Jehovah.” It is your responsibility to safeguard that trust. What can you do to protect your children from abuse? First, educate yourself about abuse. Learn about the kind of individuals who abuse children and the tactics they use to deceive them. Be alert to potential dangers. ([Prov. 22:3;][24:3]) Remember that in most cases, the abuser is someone the child already knows and trusts. Second, maintain good communication with your children. (Deut. 6:6, 7;[Jas. 1:19]) Remember that children are often reluctant to report abuse. They may fear that they will not be believed, or they may have been threatened by the abuser to keep the abuse secret. If you sense that something is wrong, kindly draw them out with questions and then patiently listen to their answers. Third, educate your children. Teach them what to say and do if someone tries to touch them in an inappropriate way. w19.05 13 ¶19-22

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

^ (Prov. 22:3) The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*

Or “penalty.”

^ (Prov. 24:3) By wisdom a house* is built up, And by discernment it is made secure.

Or “household.”

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

Tuesday, October 5

You, O Jehovah, are my helper and comforter.—[Ps. 86:17].

When stressed, we can regain strength by attending congregation meetings. When we are at the meetings, we give Jehovah additional opportunities to be our “helper and comforter.” There he strengthens us by means of his holy spirit, his Word, and his people. Meetings provide us with an opportunity to enjoy “an interchange of encouragement.” (Rom. 1:11, 12) A sister named Sophia said: “Jehovah and our brotherhood kept me going. Most important for me were our congregation meetings. I have found that the more involved I am in the ministry and my congregation, the better I am able to deal with stress and worry.” When we feel discouraged, let us remember that Jehovah not only promises permanent relief in the future but also offers to help us deal with stress now. He gives us “the desire and the power” to overcome feelings of discouragement and hopelessness.—[Phil. 2:13]. w19.06 19 ¶17-18

^ (Ps. 86:17) Show me a sign* of your goodness, So that those who hate me may see it and be put to shame. For you, O Jehovah, are my helper and comforter.

Or “evidence.”

^ (Rom. 1:11, 12) For I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; 12 or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

^ (Phil. 2:13) For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.

Saturday, October 9

Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, I am pressing on toward the goal.—Phil. 3:13, 14.

The apostle Paul did not allow himself to be distracted, either by past accomplishments or by past mistakes. In fact, he said that “forgetting the things behind” was essential to “stretching forward to the things ahead,” that is, to completing the race successfully. What were some of the things that could have distracted Paul? First, his accomplishments in Judaism were impressive. Yet, he viewed those things as “a lot of refuse.” ([Phil. 3:3-8]) Second, he did not allow guilt over his earlier persecution of Christians to paralyze him. And third, he did not reason that he had already done enough for Jehovah. Paul had a productive ministry despite being imprisoned, beaten, stoned, and shipwrecked, as well as lacking food and clothing. (2 Cor. 11:23-27) However, regardless of what he had already accomplished and suffered, Paul knew that he must press on. The same is true of us. w19.08 3 ¶5

^ (Phil. 3:13, 14) Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having taken hold of it; but one thing is certain: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, 14 I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus.

^ (Phil. 3:3-8) For we are those with the real circumcision, we who are rendering sacred service by God’s spirit and boasting in Christ Jesus and who do not base our confidence in the flesh, 4 though I, if anyone, do have grounds for confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinks he has grounds for confidence in the flesh, I have more: 5 circumcised the eighth day, of the nation of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew born from Hebrews; regarding law, a Pharisee; 6 regarding zeal, persecuting the congregation; regarding righteousness based on law, one who proved himself blameless. 7 Yet, the things that were gains to me, I have considered loss* on account of the Christ. 8 What is more, I do indeed also consider all things to be loss on account of the excelling value of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord. For his sake I have taken the loss of all things and I consider them as a lot of refuse,* that I may gain Christ

Or possibly, “have willingly abandoned.”

Or “garbage; rubbish.”

^ (2 Cor. 11:23-27) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths. 24 Five times I received 40 strokes less one from the Jews, 25 three times I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, three times I experienced shipwreck, a night and a day I have spent in the open sea; 26 in journeys often, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from my own people, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers among false brothers, 27 in labor and toil, in sleepless nights often, in hunger and thirst, frequently without food, in cold and lacking clothing.

Sunday, October 10

I am sending you out as sheep among wolves.—[Matt. 10:16].

Many of our brothers and sisters live in countries where they cannot preach openly or from door to door, so they find other ways to declare the good news. (Matt. 10:17-20) In one such country, a circuit overseer suggested that each publisher cover his own preaching “territory” made up of relatives, neighbors, schoolmates, workmates, and acquaintances. Within two years, the number of congregations in that circuit increased significantly. We may not live in a country where we cannot preach openly. However, we can learn a valuable lesson from the example of our resourceful brothers and sisters: Always look for ways to have a full share in the ministry, confident that Jehovah will give you the power you need to overcome any obstacle. ([Phil. 2:13]) At this momentous time, may we make sure of the more important things, be flawless, avoid stumbling others, and bear righteous fruit. Then we will abound in love and bring honor to our caring Father, Jehovah. w19.08 13 ¶17-18

^ (Matt. 10:16) “Look! I am sending you out as sheep among wolves; so prove yourselves cautious as serpents and yet innocent as doves.

^ (Matt. 10:17-20) Be on your guard against men, for they will hand you over to local courts and they will scourge you in their synagogues. 18 And you will be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a witness to them and the nations. 19 However, when they hand you over, do not become anxious about how or what you are to speak, for what you are to speak will be given you in that hour; 20 for the ones speaking are not just you, but it is the spirit of your Father that speaks by you.

^ (Phil. 2:13) For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.

Monday, October 11

I have seen servants on horseback but princes walking on foot just like servants.—[Eccl. 10:7].

Few of us enjoy dealing with people who always insist on their own way and who refuse to accept suggestions from others. By contrast, we find it refreshing to deal with our fellow believers when they show “fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.” ([1 Pet. 3:8]) If we are drawn to such people, they will likely be drawn to us—as long as we are humble. Humility also makes our life easier. Realistically, we may observe things in life that do not seem to be right or fair. Those who have great ability do not always receive recognition. And those with less ability sometimes receive more honor. Even so, Solomon acknowledged that it is wise for us to face reality rather than to be obsessed with negative circumstances. ([Eccl. 6:9]) If we are humble, we will find it easier to accept life as it is—not as we think it should be. w19.09 4-5 ¶9-10

^ (Eccl. 10:7) I have seen servants on horseback but princes walking on foot just like servants.

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

Tuesday, October 12

Fathers, . . . go on bringing [your children] up in the discipline and admonition of Jehovah.—[Eph. 6:4].

Those who have a measure of authority, such as fathers, have the opportunity to benefit other people. Jehovah has assigned the father as head of the family, and God expects him to train and discipline his children. ([1 Cor. 11:3]) But a father’s authority is limited—he must answer to Jehovah, the one to whom every family owes its name. (Eph. 3:14, 15) Fathers show their submission to Jehovah by using their authority in a way that pleases God. Do not abuse the authority that Jehovah has given you. Admit your mistakes, and accept Bible-based counsel from others. If you do, your family will respect you for your humility. When praying with your family, pour your heart out to Jehovah—let them hear how much you depend on him. And above all, build your life around your service to Jehovah. ([Deut. 6:6-9]) Your good example is one of the most valuable gifts that you can give to your family. w19.09 15 ¶8; 17 ¶14; 18 ¶16

^ (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (1 Cor. 11:3) But I want you to know that the head of every man is the Christ; in turn, the head of a woman is the man; in turn, the head of the Christ is God.

^ (Eph. 3:14, 15) For this reason I bend my knees to the Father, 15 to whom every family in heaven and on earth owes its name.

^ (Deut. 6:6-9) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. 8 Tie them as a reminder on your hand, and they must be like a headband on your forehead.* 9 Write them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

Lit., “between your eyes.”

Thursday, October 14

Come to me.—[Matt. 11:28].

We have chosen a life of self-sacrifice and hard work. Jesus warned us that we would be persecuted. But we can expect that Jehovah will give us the strength to endure any challenge. The more we endure, the stronger we will become. ([Jas. 1:2-4]) We can also expect that Jehovah will provide for us, that Jesus will shepherd us, and that our brothers and sisters will encourage us. (Matt. 6:31-33;[John 10:14;] 1 Thess. 5:11) The woman whom Jesus cured from her “flow of blood” was refreshed on the very day that she was healed. ([Luke 8:43-48]) But she would receive lasting refreshment only if she became a loyal disciple of Christ. What do you think she did? If she did choose to come under Jesus’ yoke, imagine the reward—serving with Jesus in heaven! Any sacrifices she had made to follow Christ would pale in comparison with that blessing. No matter what our hope is—living forever in heaven or on earth—how thankful we can be that we have accepted Jesus’ invitation: “Come to me!” w19.09 25 ¶21-22

^ (Matt. 11:28) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

^ (Jas. 1:2-4) Consider it all joy, my brothers, when you meet with various trials, 3 knowing as you do that this tested quality of your faith produces endurance. 4 But let endurance complete its work, so that you may be complete and sound in all respects, not lacking in anything.

^ (Matt. 6:31-33) So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (John 10:14) I am the fine shepherd. I know my sheep and my sheep know me,

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

^ (Luke 8:43-48) Now there was a woman who had a flow of blood for 12 years, and she had not been able to get a cure from anyone. 44 She approached from behind and touched the fringe* of his outer garment, and immediately her flow of blood stopped. 45 So Jesus said: “Who touched me?” When they were all denying it, Peter said: “Instructor, the crowds are hemming you in and pressing against you.” 46 But Jesus said: “Someone touched me, for I know* that power went out of me.” 47 Seeing that she had not escaped notice, the woman came trembling and fell down before him and declared before all the people why she touched him and how she was healed immediately. 48 But he said to her: “Daughter, your faith has made you well.* Go in peace.”

Or “edge; border; tassel.”

Or “perceived.”

Or “has saved you.”

Saturday, October 16

Get out of her, my people, if you do not want to share with her in her sins, and if you do not want to receive part of her plagues.—[Rev. 18:4].

All true Christians must maintain a clear distinction between themselves and Babylon the Great. Before learning the truth, a Bible student may have been a member of a false religion. He may have attended its religious services and shared in its activities. Or he may have contributed money to such an organization. Before a Bible student can be approved as an unbaptized publisher, he must break all ties with false religion. He should submit a letter of resignation or otherwise completely sever his membership in his former church and in any other organization that has ties to Babylon the Great. A true Christian must make sure that his secular employment has nothing to do with Babylon the Great. (2 Cor. 6:14-17) Why do we take such a firm stand? Because we do not want to share in the works and sins of religious organizations that are unclean in God’s eyes.—[Isa. 52:11]. w19.10 12 ¶16-17

^ (Rev. 18:4) And I heard another voice out of heaven say: “Get out of her, my people, if you do not want to share with her in her sins, and if you do not want to receive part of her plagues.

^ (2 Cor. 6:14-17) Do not become unevenly yoked with unbelievers. For what fellowship do righteousness and lawlessness have? Or what sharing does light have with darkness? 15 Further, what harmony is there between Christ and Beʹli·al? Or what does a believer share in common with an unbeliever? 16 And what agreement does God’s temple have with idols? For we are a temple of a living God; just as God said: “I will reside among them and walk among them, and I will be their God, and they will be my people.” 17 “‘Therefore, get out from among them, and separate yourselves,’ says Jehovah, ‘and quit touching the unclean thing’”; “‘and I will take you in.’”

^ (Isa. 52:11) Turn away, turn away, get out of there, touch nothing unclean! Get out from the midst of her, keep yourselves clean, You who are carrying the utensils of Jehovah.

Tuesday, October 19

Come . . . into an isolated place and rest up a little.—[Mark 6:31].

Regarding work, balance is important. King Solomon was inspired to write: “There is an appointed time for . . . every activity.” He mentioned planting, building, weeping, laughing, dancing, and other activities. ([Eccl. 3:1-8]) Clearly, two fundamental aspects of life are work and rest. Jesus had a balanced view of work and rest. On one occasion, the apostles returned from a preaching tour. They were so busy that “they had no leisure time even to eat a meal.” Jesus told them the words of today’s text. ([Mark 6:30-34]) Even though he and his disciples were not always able to get the rest they wanted, Jesus knew that they all needed to rest. At times, some rest or some change truly is needed. We can see that from an arrangement that God made for his ancient people—the weekly Sabbath. We are not under the Mosaic Law, yet we can benefit from considering what it said about the Sabbath. w19.12 3 ¶6-7

^ (Mark 6:31) And he said to them: “Come, you yourselves, privately into an isolated place and rest up a little.” For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal.

^ (Eccl. 3:1-8) There is an appointed time for everything, A time for every activity under the heavens:  2 A time for birth and a time to die; A time to plant and a time to uproot what was planted;  3 A time to kill and a time to heal; A time to tear down and a time to build up;  4 A time to weep and a time to laugh; A time to wail and a time to dance;*  5 A time to throw stones away and a time to gather stones together; A time to embrace and a time to refrain from embracing;  6 A time to search and a time to give up as lost; A time to keep and a time to throw away;  7 A time to rip apart and a time to sew together; A time to be silent and a time to speak;  8 A time to love and a time to hate; A time for war and a time for peace.

Lit., “leap; skip about.”

^ (Mark 6:30-34) The apostles gathered around Jesus and reported to him all the things they had done and taught. 31 And he said to them: “Come, you yourselves, privately into an isolated place and rest up a little.” For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal. 32 So they set off in the boat for an isolated place to be by themselves. 33 But people saw them going and many got to know it, and from all the cities they ran together on foot and got there ahead of them. 34 Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

Wednesday, October 20

Never be anxious.—[Matt. 6:31].

Jehovah has given his word that he will care for his loyal servants, and he feels obligated to fulfill that promise. ([Ps. 31:1-3]) In addition, Jehovah knows that we would be devastated if he did not care for those who are part of his family. He promises to provide for us both materially and spiritually, and nothing will stop him from fulfilling that promise! (Matt. 6:30-33;[24:45]) When we remember why Jehovah keeps his promises, we can face economic challenges with confidence. Consider the example of the first-century Christians. When great persecution arose against the congregation in Jerusalem, “all except the apostles were scattered.” ([Acts 8:1]) Think what that would have meant. Economic hardship! Christians likely lost their homes and businesses. Yet, Jehovah did not abandon them; neither did they lose their joy. ([Acts 8:4;] Heb. 13:5, 6;[Jas. 1:2, 3]) Jehovah supported those faithful Christians, and he will support us.—Ps. 37:18, 19. w20.01 17-18 ¶14-15

^ (Matt. 6:31) So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’

^ (Ps. 31:1-3) In you, O Jehovah, I have taken refuge. May I never be put to shame. Rescue me because of your righteousness.  2 Incline your ear* to me. Come quickly to my rescue. Become for me a mountain stronghold, A fortified place to save me.  3 For you are my crag and my stronghold; For the sake of your name, you will lead me and guide me.

Or “Bend down and listen.”

^ (Matt. 6:30-33) Now if this is how God clothes the vegetation of the field that is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much rather clothe you, you with little faith? 31 So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

^ (Acts 8:1) Saul, for his part, approved of his murder. On that day great persecution arose against the congregation that was in Jerusalem; all except the apostles were scattered throughout the regions of Ju·deʹa and Sa·marʹi·a.

^ (Acts 8:4) However, those who had been scattered went through the land declaring the good news of the word.

^ (Heb. 13:5, 6) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.” 6 So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

^ (Jas. 1:2, 3) Consider it all joy, my brothers, when you meet with various trials, 3 knowing as you do that this tested quality of your faith produces endurance.

^ (Ps. 37:18, 19) Jehovah is aware of what the blameless go through,* And their inheritance will last forever. 19 They will not be put to shame in the time of disaster; In the time of famine they will have plenty.

Lit., “the days of the blameless.”

Friday, October 22

Those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, just as a father does a son in whom he delights.—[Prov. 3:12].

We have many reasons for believing that Jehovah values us. He has drawn us to him and taken notice of how we responded to the good news. ([John 6:44]) As we began to draw close to Jehovah, he drew closer to us. ([Jas. 4:8]) Jehovah also invests time and effort in educating us, showing that we are precious to him. He knows the kind of individuals we are now and the kind we can become. And he disciplines us because he loves us. What powerful evidence that Jehovah values us! Some considered King David to be worthless, but he knew that Jehovah loved and supported him. That thought affected David’s view of his situation. (2 Sam. 16:5-7) When we feel low or face challenges, Jehovah can help us see things differently and he can help us climb over any obstacle. ([Ps. 18:27-29]) When we have Jehovah’s backing, nothing can stop us from serving him with joy.—[Rom. 8:31]. w20.01 15 ¶7-8

^ (Prov. 3:12) For those whom Jehovah loves he reproves, Just as a father does a son in whom he delights.

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (2 Sam. 16:5-7) When King David reached Ba·huʹrim, a man of the family of Saul’s house named Shimʹe·i, the son of Geʹra, came out shouting curses as he approached. 6 He was throwing stones at David and at all the servants of King David, as well as at all the people and the mighty men on his right and on his left. 7 Shimʹe·i said as he cursed: “Get out, get out, you bloodguilty man! You worthless man!

^ (Ps. 18:27-29) For you save those who are lowly* But you abase the haughty.* 28 For it is you who light my lamp, O Jehovah, My God who lights up my darkness. 29 With your help I can charge against a marauder band; By God’s power I can scale a wall.

Or “afflicted.”

Lit., “haughty eyes.”

^ (Rom. 8:31) What, then, are we to say about these things? If God is for us, who will be* against us?

Or “can be; is.”

Monday, October 25

My servants will shout joyfully.—[Isa. 65:14].

Jehovah wants his family to be happy. There are many reasons why we can be cheerful right now, even though we may be facing difficulties. For example, we are certain that our heavenly Father loves us dearly. We have an accurate knowledge of God’s Word, the Bible. ([Jer. 15:16]) And we are part of a unique family made up of people who love Jehovah, love his high moral standards, and love one another. ([Ps. 106:4, 5]) We can remain happy because we have the sure hope that life will get even better in the future. We know that soon Jehovah will remove all the wicked and that under the direction of his Kingdom, the earth will be restored to Paradise. We also have the wonderful hope that those who have died will be raised to life and reunited with their loved ones. (John 5:28, 29) What a joy that will be! And most important, we are sure that soon everyone in heaven and on earth will give our loving Father the honor, praise, and devotion that he deserves. w20.02 13 ¶15-16

^ (Isa. 65:14) Look! My servants will shout joyfully because of the good condition of the heart, But you will cry out because of the pain of heart And you will wail because of a broken spirit.

^ (Jer. 15:16) Your words were found, and I ate them; And your word became to me the exultation and the rejoicing of my heart, For your name has been called on me, O Jehovah God of armies.

^ (Ps. 106:4, 5) Remember me, O Jehovah, when you show favor* toward your people. Take care of me with your acts of salvation,  5 So that I may enjoy the goodness you show your chosen ones, That I may rejoice along with your nation, That I may proudly praise* you along with your inheritance.

Or “goodwill.”

Or “may boast about.”

^ (John 5:28, 29) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice 29 and come out, those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced vile things to a resurrection of judgment.

Friday, October 29

We distinguish the inspired statement of truth from the inspired statement of error.—[1 John 4:6].

Satan, “the father of the lie,” has deceived people since the start of human history. ([John 8:44]) Some of his lies include false teachings about death and about life after death. Those teachings form the basis for many popular customs and superstitions. Why are so many humans deceived? Satan’s lies about death exploit the way we naturally feel about death. Because we were created to live forever, we do not want to die. ([Eccl. 3:11]) We consider death an enemy. ([1 Cor. 15:26]) Despite Satan’s efforts, the truth about death has not been kept hidden. In fact, more people than ever now know and proclaim what the Bible teaches about the condition of the dead and the hope for the dead. ([Eccl. 9:5,][10;][Acts 24:15]) These truths comfort us, sparing us needless fear and uncertainty. w19.04 14 ¶1; 15 ¶5-6

^ (1 John 4:6) We originate with God. Whoever comes to know God listens to us; whoever does not originate with God does not listen to us. By this we distinguish the inspired statement of truth from the inspired statement of error.

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Eccl. 3:11) He has made everything beautiful* in its time. He has even put eternity in their heart; yet mankind will never find out the work that the true God has made from start to finish.

Or “well-arranged; proper; appropriate.”

^ (1 Cor. 15:26) And the last enemy, death, is to be brought to nothing.

^ (Eccl. 9:5) For the living know* that they will die, but the dead know nothing at all, nor do they have any more reward,* because all memory of them is forgotten.

Or “are conscious.”

Or “wages.”

^ (Eccl. 9:10) Whatever your hand finds to do, do with all your might, for there is no work nor planning nor knowledge nor wisdom in the Grave,* where you are going.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

Saturday, October 30

Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.—[Gal. 6:2].

Jehovah God loves his worshippers. He always has, and he always will. He also loves justice. ([Ps. 33:5]) So we can be sure of two things: (1) It pains Jehovah when his servants are treated unfairly. (2) He will make sure that justice is served. The Law that God gave Israel through Moses was built on love. It promoted justice—justice for all, even vulnerable ones. ([Deut. 10:18]) That Law reveals how deeply Jehovah cares about his worshippers. The Mosaic Law ended in 33 C.E. when the Christian congregation was established. Would Christians be without the benefits of a law that is built on love and promotes justice? By no means! Christians had a new law—“the law of the Christ.” Jesus did not write down a law code for his followers, but he did give them instructions, commands, and principles to live by. “The law of the Christ” includes everything Jesus taught. w19.05 2 ¶1-3

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (Ps. 33:5) He loves righteousness and justice. The earth is filled with Jehovah’s loyal love.

^ (Deut. 10:18) He executes justice for the fatherless child* and the widow and loves the foreign resident, giving him food and clothing.

Or “the orphan.”

Sunday, October 31

The God of all comfort . . . comforts us in all our trials.—2 Cor. 1:3, 4.

Humans have a natural need for comfort and a remarkable ability to provide it. For instance, when a little child falls and skins his knee while playing, he may run to Mommy or Daddy, crying. The parents cannot heal the wound, but they can comfort the child. They may ask what happened, wipe away his tears, offer soothing words and affection, and perhaps apply some medicine or a bandage. Before long, the child stops crying and may even resume playing. In time, the wound will heal. Sometimes, though, children are hurt in far worse ways. Some are sexually abused. The abuse can be inflicted on a single occasion, or it may go on for years. In either case, the abuse can leave deep emotional scars. In some cases, the offender is caught and punished. In others, the abuser may seem to escape justice. But even if justice is swift, the harmful effects of the abuse may last well into adulthood. w19.05 14 ¶1-2

^ (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts us in all our trials so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial with the comfort that we receive from God.

November

Monday, November 1

Consider others superior to you.—[Phil. 2:3].

Today, many people who are considered wise would ridicule the Bible’s counsel about self-importance. They would say that considering others superior to you would make you vulnerable and that others would take advantage of you. But what fruitage has the self-centered attitude promoted by Satan’s world produced? Are selfish people happy? Do they have happy families and genuine friends? Do they have a close friendship with God? From what you have seen, which produces the best results—following the wisdom of this world or the wisdom found in God’s Word? ([1 Cor. 3:19]) People who follow the advice of those whom the world views as wise are like a tourist who asks a fellow tourist for directions when both of them are lost. Jesus said regarding the “wise” men of his day: “Blind guides is what they are. If, then, a blind man guides a blind man, both will fall into a pit.” ([Matt. 15:14]) Truly, the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. w19.05 24-25 ¶14-16

^ (Phil. 2:3) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (1 Cor. 3:19) For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.”

^ (Matt. 15:14) Let them be. Blind guides is what they are. If, then, a blind man guides a blind man, both will fall into a pit.”*

Or “ditch.”

Tuesday, November 2

They will gather his chosen ones together.—[Matt. 24:31].

In recent years, the number of those partaking at the Memorial has been going up. Do we need to worry about this? No. “Jehovah knows those who belong to him.” ([2 Tim. 2:19]) Unlike Jehovah, the brothers who count the number of those partaking at the Memorial do not know who truly is anointed. So the number includes those who think that they are anointed but are not. For example, some who used to partake later stopped. Others may have mental or emotional problems that make them believe that they will rule with Christ in heaven. Clearly, we do not know exactly how many anointed ones are left on earth. There will be anointed ones in many parts of the earth when Jesus comes to take them to heaven. The Bible does say that during the last days, there will be a small number of anointed ones left on earth. ([Rev. 12:17]) But it does not say how many of them will be left when the great tribulation begins. w20.01 29-30 ¶11-13

^ (Matt. 24:31) And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

^ (2 Tim. 2:19) Despite that, the solid foundation of God remains standing, having this seal, “Jehovah* knows those who belong to him,” and, “Let everyone calling on the name of Jehovah* renounce unrighteousness.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Rev. 12:17) So the dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her offspring,* who observe the commandments of God and have the work of bearing witness concerning Jesus.

Lit., “seed.”

Wednesday, November 3

God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son.—[John 3:16].

Jesus illustrated the depth of Jehovah’s fatherly care with the story of the son who was lost. (Luke 15:11-32) The father in that illustration never stopped hoping that his son would return. When the son made his way home, the father eagerly welcomed him back. If we have strayed from Jehovah but are repentant, we can be sure that our loving Father is ready and willing to welcome us back. Our Father will repair all the damage caused by Adam. After Adam’s rebellion, Jehovah purposed to adopt 144,000 individuals from among mankind who will serve as kings and priests in heaven with his Son. Jesus and those associate rulers will help obedient humans to come to perfection in the new world. After they pass a final test of obedience, God will grant them everlasting life. Our Father will then have the satisfaction of seeing the earth filled with his perfect sons and daughters. What a glorious time that will be! w20.02 6-7 ¶17-19

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

Thursday, November 4

Continue to be made new in your dominant mental attitude.—[Eph. 4:23].

All of us need to ask ourselves, ‘Are the changes I am making to become a Christian only skin-deep, or am I truly becoming a Christian deep within?’ The difference is important. In his words recorded at Matthew 12:43-45, Jesus indicated what needs to be done. The idea behind those words highlights this important truth: It is not enough to get rid of wrong thoughts; we need to fill the void with godly thinking. Is it possible to change our basic inclinations or who we really are inside? God’s Word answers: “Put on the new personality that was created according to God’s will in true righteousness and loyalty.” ([Eph. 4:24]) Yes, it is possible to change what we are inside, but it is not easy to do. We need to do more than just suppress wrong desires and actions. We need to change our “dominant mental attitude.” That involves changing our desires, our tendencies, and our motivations. This requires continuous action. w19.06 9-10 ¶6-7

^ (Eph. 4:23) And you should continue to be made new in your dominant mental attitude,*

Or “in the force actuating your mind.” Lit., “to the spirit of your mind.”

^ (Matt. 12:43-45) “When an unclean spirit comes out of a man, it passes through waterless places in search of a resting-place and finds none. 44 Then it says, ‘I will go back to my house from which I moved,’ and on arriving, it finds the house unoccupied but swept clean and adorned. 45 Then it goes and takes along with it seven different* spirits more wicked than itself, and after getting inside, they dwell there; and the final circumstances of that man become worse than the first. That is how it will be also with this wicked generation.”

Or “other.”

^ (Eph. 4:24) and should put on the new personality that was created according to God’s will in true righteousness and loyalty.

Tuesday, November 9

Pray constantly.—1 Thess. 5:17.

We can respectfully approach our God at any time, no matter where we are. He is never too busy to listen to us; he is always available and attentive. When we appreciate that Jehovah listens to our prayers, we are drawn to him. “I love Jehovah,” said the psalmist, “because he hears my voice.” ([Ps. 116:1]) Our Father not only listens to our prayers but also answers them. The apostle John assures us: “No matter what we ask according to [God’s] will, he hears us.” (1 John 5:14, 15) Of course, Jehovah may not answer our prayers in the way that we expect. He knows what is best for us, so sometimes his answer is no or he wants us to wait. (2 Cor. 12:7-9) Jehovah provides for us. He does what he requires all fathers to do. ([1 Tim. 5:8]) He cares for the material needs of his children. He does not want us to be anxious about our food, clothing, or shelter. (Matt. 6:32, 33;[7:11]) As a loving parent, Jehovah has even arranged to satisfy all our future needs. w20.02 5 ¶10-12

^ (1 Thess. 5:17) Pray constantly.

^ (Ps. 116:1) I love Jehovah Because he hears* my voice, my pleas for help.

Or possibly, “I love because Jehovah hears.”

^ (1 John 5:14, 15) And this is the confidence* that we have toward him, that no matter what we ask according to his will, he hears us. 15 And if we know that he hears us concerning whatever we are asking, we know that we are to have the things we ask for, since we have asked them of him.

Or “freeness of speech.”

^ (2 Cor. 12:7-9) just because of receiving such extraordinary revelations. To keep me from becoming overly exalted, I was given a thorn in the flesh, an angel of Satan, to keep slapping me, so that I might not be overly exalted. 8 Three times I begged the Lord about this, that it would depart from me. 9 But he said to me: “My undeserved kindness is sufficient for you, for my power is being made perfect in weakness.” Most gladly, then, I will boast about my weaknesses, in order that the power of the Christ may remain over me like a tent.

^ (1 Tim. 5:8) Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^ (Matt. 6:32, 33) For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (Matt. 7:11) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will your Father who is in the heavens give good things to those asking him!

Wednesday, November 10

They will become one flock, one shepherd.—[John 10:16].

Not all who have the hope of living in heaven are part of “the faithful and discreet slave.” (Matt. 24:45-47) Just as in the first century, Jehovah and Jesus today are using a few brothers to feed, or teach, many. Only a few anointed Christians in the first century were used to write the Christian Greek Scriptures. Today, only a few anointed Christians have the responsibility to give God’s people “food at the proper time.” Jehovah has decided to give everlasting life on earth to the vast majority of his people and life in heaven to those few who will rule with Jesus. Jehovah rewards all his servants—the “Jew” as well as the “ten men”—and he requires them to obey the same laws and remain faithful. ([Zech. 8:23]) All must stay humble. All must serve him together and be united. And all must work to keep the peace in the congregation. As we get closer to the end, let us all keep serving Jehovah and following Christ as “one flock.” w20.01 31 ¶15-16

^ (John 10:16) “And I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; those too I must bring in, and they will listen to my voice, and they will become one flock, one shepherd.

^ (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

^ (Zech. 8:23) “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘In those days ten men out of all the languages of the nations will take hold, yes, they will take firm hold of the robe* of a Jew,* saying: “We want to go with you, for we have heard that God is with you people.”’”

Or “extremity of the garment.”

Lit., “a Jewish man.”

Thursday, November 11

If any are not obedient to the word, they may be won without a word . . . because of having been eyewitnesses of your chaste conduct together with deep respect.—1 Pet. 3:1, 2.

We cannot force our relatives to accept the good news, but we can encourage them to open their minds and hearts to the Bible’s message. (2 Tim. 3:14, 15) Let your conduct speak for you. Often, what we do makes a bigger impression on our relatives than what we say. Persevere in trying to help your relatives. Jehovah sets the example for us. “Again and again” he gives people the opportunity to respond to the good news and gain life. ([Jer. 44:4]) And the apostle Paul told Timothy to persevere in helping others. Why? Because by doing so, he would save himself and those who listened to him. ([1 Tim. 4:16]) We love our relatives, so we want them to know the truths found in God’s Word. w19.08 14 ¶2; 16-17 ¶8-9

^ (1 Pet. 3:1, 2) In the same way, you wives, be in subjection to your husbands, so that if any are not obedient to the word, they may be won without a word through the conduct of their wives, 2 because of having been eyewitnesses of your chaste conduct together with deep respect.

^ (2 Tim. 3:14, 15) You, however, continue in the things that you learned and were persuaded to believe, knowing from whom you learned them 15 and that from infancy you have known the holy writings, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.

^ (Jer. 44:4) I kept sending all my servants the prophets to you, sending them again and again,* saying: “Please do not do this detestable thing that I hate.”

Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

Friday, November 12

Open reproof is better than concealed love.—[Prov. 27:5].

We do well to remember that if someone takes the time to offer us correction, we have likely strayed more than we realize. At such times, we may find that our first inclination is to reject the counsel. We might criticize the person who gave it or the way he said it. But if we are humble, we will strive to regain our balance. A humble person appreciates counsel. To illustrate: Imagine that you are at a Christian meeting. After talking with several fellow believers, you are pulled aside by one of them who discreetly mentions that you have some food on your teeth. No doubt, you would feel embarrassed. But would you not also appreciate that he or she let you know? In fact, you might wish that someone else had told you sooner! Likewise, we should humbly appreciate a fellow believer who has the courage to offer us counsel when we need it. We view that person as our friend, not our enemy.—[Prov. 27:6;][Gal. 4:16]. w19.09 5 ¶11-12

^ (Prov. 27:5) Open reproof is better than concealed love.

^ (Prov. 27:6) The wounds inflicted by a friend are faithful, But an enemy’s kisses are plentiful.*

Or possibly, “insincere; forced.”

^ (Gal. 4:16) So, then, have I become your enemy because I tell you the truth?

Saturday, November 13

Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, and do not forsake the instruction of your mother.—[Prov. 6:20].

Jehovah has assigned the mother an honorable role in the family, and he has given her a measure of authority over her children. In fact, a mother’s influence on her children can be profound and lifelong. ([Prov. 22:6]) Note what mothers can learn from Mary, the mother of Jesus. Mary knew the Scriptures very well. She had developed a deep respect for Jehovah and had formed a strong personal friendship with him. She was willing to submit to Jehovah’s direction, even though it involved changing her entire life course. (Luke 1:35-38,[46-55]) Mothers, you can imitate Mary in a number of ways. How? First, by maintaining your own friendship with Jehovah through personal Bible study and private prayers. Second, by being willing to make changes in your life to please Jehovah. w19.09 18 ¶17-19

^ (Prov. 6:20) Observe, my son, the commandment of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother.

Or “law.”

^ (Prov. 22:6) Train a boy* in the way he should go; Even when he grows old he will not depart from it.

Or “child; youth.”

^ (Luke 1:35-38) In answer the angel said to her: “Holy spirit will come upon you, and power of the Most High will overshadow you. And for that reason the one who is born will be called holy, God’s Son. 36 And look! Elizabeth your relative has also conceived a son, in her old age, and this is the sixth month for her, the so-called barren woman; 37 for no declaration will be impossible for God.” 38 Then Mary said: “Look! Jehovah’s slave girl! May it happen to me according to your declaration.” At that the angel departed from her.

^ (Luke 1:46-55) And Mary said: “My soul magnifies Jehovah, 47 and my spirit cannot keep from being overjoyed at God my Savior, 48 because he has looked upon the low position of his slave girl. For look! from now on all generations will declare me happy, 49 because the powerful One has done great deeds for me, and holy is his name, 50 and for generation after generation his mercy is upon those who fear him. 51 He has acted mightily with his arm; he has scattered those who are haughty in the intention of their hearts. 52 He has brought down powerful men from thrones and has exalted lowly ones; 53 he has fully satisfied hungry ones with good things and has sent away empty-handed those who had wealth. 54 He has come to the aid of Israel his servant, remembering his mercy, 55 just as he spoke to our forefathers, to Abraham and to his offspring,* forever.”

Lit., “seed.”

Sunday, November 14

Look! a great crowd.—[Rev. 7:9].

The apostle John received an exciting prophetic vision. In it, angels are told to hold back the destructive winds of the great tribulation until the final sealing of a group of slaves. ([Rev. 7:1-3]) That group is made up of 144,000 who will rule with Jesus in heaven. ([Luke 12:32;][Rev. 7:4]) Then John mentions another group, so vast that he exclaims: “Look!”—an expression that may indicate his surprise at seeing something unexpected. What does John see? “A great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues, standing before the throne and before the Lamb.” ([Rev. 7:9-14]) Imagine how happy John must have been to learn about myriads of people practicing true worship in the future! That vision no doubt strengthened John’s faith. How much more should it strengthen our faith, since we live in the time of the fulfillment of the vision! We have seen the gathering of millions whose hope is to survive the great tribulation and live forever on earth. w19.09 26 ¶2-3

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Rev. 7:1-3) After this I saw four angels standing on the four corners of the earth, holding tight the four winds of the earth, so that no wind could blow on the earth or on the sea or on any tree. 2 And I saw another angel ascending from the sunrise,* having a seal of the living God; and he called with a loud voice to the four angels to whom it was granted to harm the earth and the sea, 3 saying: “Do not harm the earth or the sea or the trees, until after we have sealed the slaves of our God in their foreheads.”

Or “east.”

^ (Luke 12:32) “Have no fear, little flock, for your Father has approved of giving you the Kingdom.

^ (Rev. 7:4) And I heard the number of those who were sealed, 144,000, sealed out of every tribe of the sons of Israel:

^ (Rev. 7:9-14) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.” 11 All the angels were standing around the throne and the elders and the four living creatures, and they fell facedown before the throne and worshipped God, 12 saying: “Amen! Let the praise and the glory and the wisdom and the thanksgiving and the honor and the power and the strength be to our God forever and ever. Amen.” 13 In response one of the elders said to me: “These who are dressed in the white robes, who are they and where did they come from?” 14 So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

Or “languages.”

Tuesday, November 16

Diotrephes, who likes to have the first place among them, does not accept anything from us with respect.—[3 John 9].

In the first century, Diotrephes envied those who took the lead in the Christian congregation. He wanted “to have the first place” among congregation members, so he spread malicious talk to discredit the apostle John and other responsible brothers. ([3 John 10]) Although not going as far as Diotrephes, we too could begin to envy a fellow Christian who receives an assignment that we had hoped to get—especially if we feel that we are just as qualified as he is to care for that responsibility. Envy is like a poisonous weed. Once the seed of envy takes root in our heart, it can be difficult to destroy. Envy feeds on other negative feelings, such as improper jealousy, pride, and selfishness. Envy can choke the development of good qualities, such as love, compassion, and kindness. As soon as we see envy starting to sprout, we need to uproot it from our heart. w20.02 15 ¶6-7

^ (3 John 9) I wrote something to the congregation, but Di·otʹre·phes, who likes to have the first place among them, does not accept anything from us with respect.

^ (3 John 10) That is why if I come, I will call attention to the works he is doing in spreading malicious talk about us.* Not being content with this, he refuses to welcome the brothers with respect; and those who want to welcome them, he tries to hinder and to throw out of the congregation.

Lit., “chattering about us with wicked words.”

Friday, November 19

A true friend shows love at all times and is a brother who is born for times of distress.—[Prov. 17:17].

Today, our brothers and sisters face a variety of challenges. For instance, many suffer from natural or man-made disasters. When that happens, some of us may be able to welcome these friends into our home. Others may be able to help financially. But all of us can ask Jehovah to help our brothers and sisters. If we learn that a brother or sister is discouraged, we may not know what to say or how to react. But all of us have much to offer. For example, we can make time to be with our friend. We can listen sympathetically when he or she speaks. And we can share our favorite comforting scripture. ([Isa. 50:4]) What matters most is that you are there with your friends when they need you. We must be determined to build and maintain strong relationships with our brothers and sisters now. Those friendships will last not only through the end of this system but for eternity! w19.11 7 ¶18-19

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (Isa. 50:4) The Sovereign Lord Jehovah has given me the tongue of those taught,* So that I may know how to answer* the tired one with the right word.* He awakens me morning by morning; He awakens my ear to listen like the taught ones.

Or “a well-trained tongue.”

Or possibly, “strengthen.”

Lit., “with a word.”

Saturday, November 20

This is the law of the communion sacrifice that one may present to Jehovah.—[Lev. 7:11].

This was a voluntary offering that the individual made because he loved his God, Jehovah. The person making the offering, his family, and the priests would eat the meat of the sacrificed animal. But certain parts of the animal sacrifice were offered up exclusively to Jehovah. Which parts? Jehovah viewed the fat as the best part of an animal. He also specified that vital organs, including the kidneys, were of special value. ([Lev. 3:6,][12,][14-16]) So Jehovah was especially pleased when an Israelite voluntarily offered vital organs and the fat to him. The Israelite who made such an offering demonstrated his deep desire to offer the very best to God. In a similar way, Jesus willingly offered up to Jehovah his very best by serving Him whole-souled out of love for Him. ([John 14:31]) For Jesus, doing God’s will was a delight. ([Ps. 40:8]) How pleasing it must have been for Jehovah to see Jesus serve him so willingly! w19.11 22-23 ¶9-10

^ (Lev. 7:11) “‘Now this is the law of the communion sacrifice that one may present to Jehovah:

^ (Lev. 3:6) “‘If his offering is from the flock for a communion sacrifice to Jehovah, he will present a sound male or a female animal.

^ (Lev. 3:12) “‘If his offering is a goat, then he will present it before Jehovah.

^ (Lev. 3:14-16) The part he will present as his offering made by fire to Jehovah is the fat that covers the intestines, all the fat that surrounds the intestines, 15 and the two kidneys with the fat on them that is near the loins. He will also remove the appendage of the liver along with the kidneys. 16 The priest will make them smoke on the altar as food,* an offering made by fire for a pleasing* aroma. All the fat belongs to Jehovah.

Lit., “bread,” that is, as God’s share of the communion sacrifice.

Or “appeasing; soothing.” Lit., “restful.”

^ (John 14:31) But for the world to know that I love the Father, I am doing just as the Father has commanded me to do. Get up, let us go from here.

^ (Ps. 40:8) To do your will, O my God, is my delight,* And your law is deep within me.

Or “desire.”

Friday, November 26

Do not imitate what is bad, but imitate what is good.—[3 John 11].

Isaac was a wealthy man, and the Philistines envied Isaac’s prosperity. (Gen. 26:12-14) They even stopped up the wells that Isaac depended on in order to water his flocks and herds. (Gen. 26:15, 16,[27]) Like the Philistines, some people today become envious of those who have more material possessions than they do. They not only want the things others have but also want to deprive them of what they have. The Jewish religious leaders envied Jesus because he was much appreciated by the common people. (Matt. 7:28, 29) Jesus was God’s representative, and he was teaching the truth. Even so, these religious leaders spread wicked lies and slander to ruin Jesus’ good name. ([Mark 15:10;] John 11:47, 48;[12:12, 13,][19]) What warning lesson can we learn from this account? We must fight any tendency to envy those who have qualities that endear them to the congregation. Instead, we should try to imitate their loving ways.—[1 Cor. 11:1]. w20.02 15 ¶4-5

^ (3 John 11) Beloved one, do not imitate what is bad, but imitate what is good. The one who does good originates with God. The one who does bad has not seen God.

^ (Gen. 26:12-14) And Isaac began to sow seed in that land, and in that year he reaped 100 times what he sowed, for Jehovah was blessing him. 13 The man became wealthy, and he continued to prosper until he became very wealthy. 14 He acquired flocks of sheep and herds of cattle and a large body of servants, and the Phi·lisʹtines began to envy him.

^ (Gen. 26:15, 16) So the Phi·lisʹtines took soil and stopped up all the wells that his father’s servants had dug in the days of Abraham. 16 A·bimʹe·lech then said to Isaac: “Move from our neighborhood, for you have grown far stronger than we are.”

^ (Gen. 26:27) At this Isaac said to them: “Why have you come to me, seeing that you hated me and sent me away from your neighborhood?”

^ (Matt. 7:28, 29) When Jesus finished these sayings, the effect was that the crowds were astounded at his way of teaching, 29 for he was teaching them as a person having authority, and not as their scribes.

^ (Mark 15:10) For Pilate was aware that out of envy the chief priests had handed him over.

^ (John 11:47, 48) So the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered the Sanʹhe·drin together and said: “What are we to do, for this man performs many signs? 48 If we let him go on this way, they will all put faith in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation.”

^ (John 12:12, 13) The next day the large crowd that had come to the festival heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem. 13 So they took branches of palm trees and went out to meet him, and they began to shout: “Save, we pray you! Blessed is the one who comes in Jehovah’s name, the King of Israel!”

^ (John 12:19) So the Pharisees said among themselves: “You see that you are not getting anywhere. Look! The whole world has gone after him.”

^ (1 Cor. 11:1) Become imitators of me, just as I am of Christ.

Sunday, November 28

Make disciples.—[Matt. 28:19].

Our goal is to help our Bible student to grow spiritually. ([Eph. 4:13]) When someone agrees to a study of the Bible, he may mainly be interested in how the study will benefit him personally. As his love for Jehovah grows, however, he will likely begin to think about how he can help others, including those who are already part of the congregation. (Matt. 22:37-39) When the time is right, do not hold back from mentioning the privilege of supporting the Kingdom work financially. Teach your Bible student what to do when problems arise. Suppose, for example, that your student, an unbaptized publisher, tells you that he has been offended by someone in the congregation. Rather than take sides, why not explain what his Scriptural options are? He can either forgive the brother or, if he cannot let the matter go, approach the person kindly and lovingly with the goal of ‘gaining the brother.’ (Compare Matthew 18:15.) Help your student to prepare what he is going to say. w20.01 5-6 ¶14-15

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Eph. 4:13) until we all attain to the oneness* of the faith and of the accurate knowledge of the Son of God, to being a full-grown* man, attaining the measure of stature that belongs to the fullness of the Christ.

Or “unity.”

Or “mature.”

^ (Matt. 22:37-39) He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’

^ (Matt. 18:15) “Moreover, if your brother commits a sin, go and reveal his fault* between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother.

Lit., “go reprove him.”

Tuesday, November 30

All Scripture is inspired of God.—[2 Tim. 3:16].

The Greek word translated “inspired of God” literally means “God-breathed.” God used his spirit to “breathe” his thoughts into the minds of Bible writers. When we read the Bible and meditate on what we read, God’s instructions enter our mind and heart. Those inspired thoughts move us to bring our life in line with God’s will. ([Heb. 4:12]) But to benefit fully from holy spirit, we must set aside time to study the Bible regularly and to think deeply about what we read. Then God’s Word will influence all that we say and do. Also, we must worship God together. ([Ps. 22:22]) Jehovah’s spirit is present at meetings. ([Rev. 2:29]) When we meet for worship with fellow Christians, we pray for holy spirit, we sing Kingdom songs based on God’s Word, and we listen to Bible-based instruction presented by brothers who have been appointed by holy spirit. To benefit fully from holy spirit, however, we need to come prepared to participate in the meetings. w19.11 11 ¶13-14

^ (2 Tim. 3:16) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness,

Or “correcting.”

^ (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ (Ps. 22:22) I will declare your name to my brothers; In the midst of the congregation I will praise you.

^ (Rev. 2:29) Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

December

Wednesday, December 1

There is . . . a time to be silent.—[Eccl. 3:1,][7].

If we fail to control our speech, it can cause a lot of damage. For example, if you meet someone who lives in a land where our work is banned, are you tempted to ask him to give details about how our work is carried out in that country? No doubt your motives are good. We love our brothers and are interested in what is happening to them. We also want to be specific when praying for them. However, this is a time when we should hold back from speaking. If we put pressure on someone who has confidential information, we show a lack of love—both to that person and to the brothers and sisters who are relying on him to keep quiet about their activity. Certainly, none of us would want to add to the difficulties of our brothers and sisters who live in countries where our work is under ban. Similarly, no brother or sister serving in such a land would want to reveal details about how Witnesses living there conduct their ministry or Christian activities. w20.03 21 ¶11-12

^ (Eccl. 3:1) There is an appointed time for everything, A time for every activity under the heavens:

^ (Eccl. 3:7) A time to rip apart and a time to sew together; A time to be silent and a time to speak;

Thursday, December 2

You certainly will not die.—[Gen. 3:4].

God did not intend for humans to die. But in order to live forever, Adam and Eve had to obey Jehovah, who gave them a simple command: “As for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.” (Gen. 2:16, 17) Then Satan came on the scene. Speaking through a serpent, he said the words of today’s text to Eve. Sadly, she believed the lie and ate the fruit. Later, her husband too ate the fruit. ([Gen. 3:6]) In this way, sin and death entered the human family. ([Rom. 5:12]) Adam and Eve died, just as God had said they would. But Satan did not stop lying about death. At some point in time, he began to introduce other lies. One of those lies is the teaching that the physical body dies but that some part of the person lives on, perhaps in the spirit realm. Variations of that lie have deceived countless humans right down to our day.—[1 Tim. 4:1]. w19.04 14-15 ¶3-4

^ (Gen. 3:4) At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die.

^ (Gen. 2:16, 17) Jehovah God also gave this command to the man: “From every tree of the garden you may eat to satisfaction. 17 But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.”

^ (Gen. 3:6) Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (1 Tim. 4:1) However, the inspired word* clearly says that in later times some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to misleading inspired statements* and teachings of demons,

Lit., “the spirit.”

Lit., “misleading spirits.”

Saturday, December 4

In this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.—[Gal. 6:2].

In what ways did Jesus teach? First, he taught people by what he said. His words had power because they conveyed the truth about God, taught the real meaning of life, and pointed to God’s Kingdom as the remedy for all human suffering. ([Luke 24:19]) Jesus also taught by example. By how he lived, he showed his followers how they should live. ([John 13:15]) When did Jesus teach? He taught during his ministry on earth. ([Matt. 4:23]) He also taught his followers shortly after he was resurrected. For example, he appeared to a group of disciples—perhaps numbering over 500—and gave them the command to “make disciples.” (Matt. 28:19, 20;[1 Cor. 15:6]) As head of the congregation, Jesus continued to instruct his disciples after he returned to heaven. For instance, about 96 C.E., Christ directed the apostle John to give encouragement and counsel to anointed Christians.—[Col. 1:18;][Rev. 1:1]. w19.05 3 ¶4-5

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (Luke 24:19) He asked them: “What things?” They said to him: “The things concerning Jesus the Naz·a·reneʹ, who proved to be a prophet powerful in deed and word before God and all the people;

^ (John 13:15) For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do.

^ (Matt. 4:23) Then he went throughout the whole of Galʹi·lee, teaching in their synagogues and preaching the good news of the Kingdom and curing every sort of disease and every sort of infirmity among the people.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (1 Cor. 15:6) After that he appeared to more than 500 brothers at one time, most of whom are still with us, though some have fallen asleep in death.

^ (Col. 1:18) and he is the head of the body, the congregation. He is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead, so that he might become the one who is first in all things;

^ (Rev. 1:1) A revelation* by Jesus Christ, which God gave him, to show his slaves the things that must shortly take place. And he sent his angel and presented it in signs through him to his slave John,

Or “A disclosure; An uncovering.”

Thursday, December 9

Warn the disorderly, . . . support the weak, be patient toward all.—1 Thess. 5:14.

Jehovah sent angels not only to warn Lot but also to help him escape the disaster brought on Sodom. (Gen. 19:12-14,[17]) Likewise, we may need to warn our brother if we see that he is heading for trouble. Even if he is slow to apply the Bible-based counsel he receives, we need to be patient. Be like the two angels. Rather than give up and draw away from our brother, we should look for practical ways to assist him. ([1 John 3:18]) We may need to offer to take him by the hand, figuratively speaking, and help him apply the good advice he is given. Jehovah could have focused on Lot’s imperfections. Instead, he later inspired the apostle Peter to refer to Lot as a righteous man. ([Ps. 130:3]) Can we imitate the way that Jehovah viewed Lot? If we focus on the good qualities of our brothers and sisters, we will be more patient with them. They, in turn, will be more likely to accept the help we offer. w19.06 21 ¶6-7

^ (1 Thess. 5:14) On the other hand, we urge you, brothers, to warn* the disorderly, speak consolingly to those who are depressed,* support the weak, be patient toward all.

Or “admonish.”

Or “those who are discouraged.” Lit., “those of little soul.”

^ (Gen. 19:12-14) Then the men said to Lot: “Do you have anyone else here? Sons-in-law, your sons, your daughters, and all your people in the city, bring out of this place! 13 For we are going to destroy this place, because the outcry against them has indeed grown great* before Jehovah, so that Jehovah sent us to destroy the city.” 14 So Lot went out and began to speak to his sons-in-law who were to marry his daughters, and he kept saying: “Get up! Get out of this place, because Jehovah will destroy the city!” But to his sons-in-law, he seemed to be joking.

Or “loud.”

^ (Gen. 19:17) As soon as they had brought them to the outskirts, he said: “Escape for your life!* Do not look behind you and do not stand still in any part of the district! Escape to the mountainous region so that you may not be swept away!”

Or “soul.”

^ (1 John 3:18) Little children, we should love, not in word or with the tongue, but in deed and truth.

^ (Ps. 130:3) If errors were what you watch,* O Jah,* Then who, O Jehovah, could stand?

Or “keep track of.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Thursday, December 16

Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble.—[Ps. 138:6].

A Christian man could begin to think that he is the one who is most qualified for a certain assignment. Or a Christian wife might think, ‘My husband is much more qualified than so-and-so!’ However, if we are truly humble, we will avoid such a prideful spirit. We can learn from the way that Moses reacted when others received privileges. Moses appreciated his assignment of leading the nation of Israel. How did Moses react when Jehovah permitted others to serve alongside him? He was not jealous. (Num. 11:24-29) As to judging the people, he humbly allowed others to share some of his workload. (Ex. 18:13-24) This meant better service for the Israelites whom he was appointed to judge. In that sense, Moses did not put his privileges ahead of the welfare of others. What a good example for us! We remember that if we are to be truly useful to Jehovah, our humility should exceed our ability. w19.09 5-6 ¶13-14

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (Num. 11:24-29) So Moses went out and spoke the words of Jehovah to the people. And he gathered 70 men from the elders of the people and had them stand around the tent. 25 Then Jehovah came down in a cloud and spoke to him and took away some of the spirit that was on him and put it on each of the 70 elders. And as soon as the spirit settled down on them, they began to behave as prophets,* but they did not do it again. 26 There were two of the men still in the camp. Their names were Elʹdad and Meʹdad. And the spirit began to settle down on them, as they were among those whose names had been written down, but they had not gone out to the tent. So they began to behave as prophets in the camp. 27 And a young man ran and reported to Moses: “Elʹdad and Meʹdad are behaving as prophets in the camp!” 28 Then Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses from his youth, responded and said: “My lord Moses, restrain them!” 29 But Moses said to him: “Are you jealous for me? No, I wish that all of Jehovah’s people were prophets and that Jehovah would put his spirit on them!”

Or “began to prophesy.”

Sunday, December 19

No one can slave for two masters.—[Matt. 6:24].

A person who worships Jehovah while also spending excessive time and effort trying to gain this world’s riches would, in a sense, be trying to serve two masters. He would not be giving Jehovah exclusive devotion. Near the end of the first century C.E., members of the congregation in the city of Laodicea boasted: “I am rich and have acquired riches and do not need anything at all.” But in the eyes of Jehovah and Jesus, they were “miserable and pitiful and poor and blind and naked.” Jesus counseled them, not because they were wealthy, but because their love of riches was damaging their relationship with Jehovah. ([Rev. 3:14-17]) If we detect that a desire to pursue riches is growing in our heart, we must act quickly to correct our thinking. (1 Tim. 6:7, 8) If we do not, our heart will be divided and Jehovah will not accept our worship. He “requires exclusive devotion.”—[Deut. 4:24]. w19.10 27 ¶5-6

^ (Matt. 6:24) “No one can slave for two masters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. You cannot slave for God and for Riches.

^ (Rev. 3:14-17) “To the angel of the congregation in La·o·di·ceʹa write: These are the things that the Amen says, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation by God: 15 ‘I know your deeds, that you are neither cold nor hot. I wish you were cold or else hot. 16 So because you are lukewarm and neither hot nor cold, I am going to vomit you out of my mouth. 17 Because you say, “I am rich and have acquired riches and do not need anything at all,” but you do not know that you are miserable and pitiful and poor and blind and naked,

^ (1 Tim. 6:7, 8) For we have brought nothing into the world, and neither can we carry anything out. 8 So, having food* and clothing,* we will be content with these things.

Or “sustenance.”

Or “shelter.” Lit., “covering.”

^ (Deut. 4:24) For Jehovah your God is a consuming fire, a God who requires exclusive devotion.

Monday, December 20

Men spoke from God as they were moved by holy spirit.—[2 Pet. 1:21].

The Greek word translated “moved” literally means “carried along; borne along.” A similar form of the same Greek word was used by Luke, the writer of Acts, to describe a ship that is “driven along” by the wind. ([Acts 27:15]) So when the apostle Peter wrote that Bible writers were “borne along,” he used “a fascinating maritime metaphor,” as one Bible scholar put it. Peter said, in effect, that just as a ship is carried along by the wind to accomplish its journey, so Bible prophets and writers were borne along by holy spirit to accomplish their task. The same scholar said: “The prophets raised their sails, so to speak.” Jehovah did his part. He provided “the wind,” or holy spirit. The Bible writers did their part. They worked in harmony with the direction of that spirit. And today, like a favorable wind on a stormy sea, holy spirit moves us forward through stormy trials to the haven of God’s promised new world. w19.11 9 ¶7-9

^ (2 Pet. 1:21) For prophecy was at no time brought by man’s will, but men spoke from God as they were moved* by holy spirit.

Lit., “carried along; borne along.”

^ (Acts 27:15) As the ship was violently seized and was not able to keep its head against the wind, we gave way to it and were driven along.

Wednesday, December 22

The trustworthy person keeps a confidence.—[Prov. 11:13].

Elders in particular must apply this Bible principle. An elder realizes that he must not reveal the “confidential talk” of those in the congregation. If he did, he would lose their trust and ruin his reputation. Those who are appointed to a position of trust in the congregation cannot be “double-tongued,” or deceitful. ([1 Tim. 3:8]; ftn.) That is, they cannot be devious or inclined to gossip. If an elder loves his wife, he will not burden her with information that she does not need to know. A wife can help her husband maintain a good reputation by not pressuring him to talk about matters that should be kept confidential. When a wife applies this advice, she not only supports her husband but also shows honor to those who have confided in him. And most important, she makes Jehovah happy because she is contributing to the peace and unity of the congregation.—[Rom. 14:19]. w20.03 22 ¶13-14

^ (Prov. 11:13) A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk, But the trustworthy person* keeps a confidence.*

Lit., “the one faithful in spirit.”

Lit., “covers over a matter.”

^ (1 Tim. 3:8) Ministerial servants should likewise be serious, not double-tongued,* not indulging in a lot of wine, not greedy of dishonest gain,

Or “not deceitful in speech.”

^ (Rom. 14:19) So, then, let us pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.

Friday, December 24

We were working night and day so as not to impose an expensive burden on any one of you.—[2 Thess. 3:8].

While in Corinth, the apostle Paul stayed with Aquila and Priscilla and “worked with them, for they were tentmakers by trade.” That Paul worked “night and day” did not mean that he worked nonstop. He took breaks from tentmaking, such as on the Sabbath. That day provided him with opportunities to witness to Jews, who also were not working on the Sabbath. (Acts 13:14-16,[42-44;][16:13;][18:1-4]) Paul had to do secular work; still, he made sure to share regularly “in the holy work of the good news of God.” ([Rom. 15:16;] 2 Cor. 11:23) He urged others to do likewise. Consequently, Aquila and Priscilla were his “fellow workers in Christ Jesus.” ([Rom. 12:11;][16:3]) Paul urged the Corinthians to have “plenty to do in the work of the Lord.” (1 Cor. 15:58;[2 Cor. 9:8]) Jehovah even inspired the apostle Paul to write: “If anyone does not want to work, neither let him eat.”—2 Thess. 3:10. w19.12 5 ¶12-13

^ (2 Thess. 3:8) nor did we eat anyone’s food free.* On the contrary, by labor and toil we were working night and day so as not to impose an expensive burden on any one of you.

Or “without paying.”

^ (Acts 13:14-16) However, they went on from Perga and came to Antioch in Pi·sidʹi·a. And going into the synagogue on the Sabbath day, they took a seat. 15 After the public reading of the Law and the Prophets, the presiding officers of the synagogue sent word to them, saying: “Men, brothers, if you have any word of encouragement for the people, tell it.” 16 So Paul stood up, and motioning with his hand, he said: “Men, Israelites and you others who fear God, listen.

^ (Acts 13:42-44) Now when they were going out, the people pleaded with them to speak about these matters on the following Sabbath. 43 So after the synagogue assembly was dismissed, many of the Jews and the proselytes who worshipped God followed Paul and Barʹna·bas, who, as they spoke to them, urged them to remain in the undeserved kindness of God. 44 The next Sabbath nearly all the city gathered together to hear the word of Jehovah.

^ (Acts 16:13) On the Sabbath day we went outside the gate beside a river, where we thought there was a place of prayer, and we sat down and began speaking to the women who had assembled.

^ (Acts 18:1-4) After this he departed from Athens and came to Corinth. 2 And he found a Jew named Aqʹui·la, a native of Ponʹtus who had recently come from Italy with Pris·cilʹla his wife, because Claudius had ordered all the Jews to leave Rome. So he went to them, 3 and because he had the same trade, he stayed at their home and worked with them, for they were tentmakers by trade. 4 He would give a talk in the synagogue every sabbath and would persuade Jews and Greeks.

^ (Rom. 15:16) for me to be a public servant of Christ Jesus to the nations. I am engaging in the holy work of the good news of God, so that these nations might be an acceptable offering, sanctified with holy spirit.

^ (2 Cor. 11:23) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths.

^ (Rom. 12:11) Be industrious, not lazy.* Be aglow with the spirit. Slave for Jehovah.

Or “Do not loiter at your business.”

^ (Rom. 16:3) Give my greetings to Prisʹca and Aqʹui·la, my fellow workers in Christ Jesus,

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

^ (2 Cor. 9:8) Moreover, God is able to cause all his undeserved kindness to abound toward you so that you are always completely self-sufficient in everything, as well as having plenty for every good work.

^ (2 Thess. 3:10) In fact, when we were with you, we used to give you this order: “If anyone does not want to work, neither let him eat.”

Saturday, December 25

Children are an inheritance from Jehovah.—[Ps. 127:3], ftn.

Jehovah created the first couple with the desire to have children. But who should decide if and when a married couple will have children? In some cultures, newly married couples are expected to start having children as soon as possible. They may even feel pressure from their family and others to follow that custom. Jethro, a brother in Asia, says, “In the congregation, some who have children pressure the childless couples to start a family.” Jeffrey, another brother in Asia, observes, “Some tell childless couples that they will have no one to take care of them when they grow old.” However, each couple should decide for themselves whether to have children. That is for them to decide; it is their responsibility. ([Gal. 6:5], ftn.) Understandably, friends and family want a newly married couple to be happy. But all need to remember that the decision whether to have children or not belongs to the couple.—1 Thess. 4:11. w19.12 22 ¶1-3

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

^ (Gal. 6:5) For each one will carry his own load.*

Or “load of responsibility.”

^ (1 Thess. 4:11) Make it your aim to live quietly and to mind your own business and to work with your hands, just as we instructed you,

Wednesday, December 29

Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching.—[1 Tim. 4:16].

Dedication is a vow that Jehovah expects you to keep. So stay close to your congregation. Your brothers and sisters in the congregation are your spiritual family. By regularly attending the meetings, you will strengthen your bond with them. Read God’s Word and meditate on it every day. ([Ps. 1:1, 2]) Take some time to think deeply about what you have read. Then the words will reach your heart. “Pray continually.” ([Matt. 26:41]) Your sincere prayers will draw you closer to Jehovah. “Keep on . . . seeking first the Kingdom.” ([Matt. 6:33]) You can do that by making the preaching work a priority in your life. By sharing regularly in the ministry, you will keep your faith strong. Any hardships you may face in this old world are “momentary and light.” ([2 Cor. 4:17]) In contrast, your dedication and baptism will open the way to a more satisfying life now and “the real life” to come. Is it worth the expense? Absolutely!—[1 Tim. 6:19]. w20.03 13 ¶19-21

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ (Ps. 1:1, 2) Happy is the man who does not walk according to the advice of the wicked And does not stand on the path of sinners And does not sit in the seat of scoffers.  2 But his delight is in the law of Jehovah, And he reads His law in an undertone* day and night.

Or “he meditates on His law.”

^ (Matt. 26:41) Keep on the watch and pray continually, so that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager,* but the flesh is weak.”

Or “willing.”

^ (Matt. 6:33) “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (2 Cor. 4:17) For though the tribulation is momentary and light, it works out for us a glory that is of more and more surpassing greatness* and is everlasting;

Lit., “weight.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:19) safely treasuring up for themselves a fine foundation for the future, so that they may get a firm hold on the real life.

Thursday, December 30

The time left is reduced.—[1 Cor. 7:29].

If your Bible student is not making steady progress, at some point you will have to ask yourself, ‘Should I stop the study?’ In analyzing the situation, ask yourself: ‘Is my student progressing at a reasonable pace for his situation?’ ‘Is he beginning “to observe,” or apply, the things he is learning?’ ([Matt. 28:20]) Sad to say, some students are like the Israelites of Ezekiel’s day. Of them, Jehovah told Ezekiel: “Look! You are to them like a romantic love song, sung with a beautiful voice and skillfully played on a stringed instrument. They will hear your words, but no one will act on them.” ([Ezek. 33:32]) We may find it hard to tell a person that we will stop studying with him. However, “the time left is reduced.” Rather than spend more time conducting an unproductive study, we need to find someone who gives evidence that he is “rightly disposed for everlasting life.”—[Acts 13:48]. w20.01 6 ¶17; 7 ¶20

^ (1 Cor. 7:29) Moreover, this I say, brothers, the time left is reduced. From now on, let those who have wives be as though they had none,

^ (Matt. 28:20) teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Ezek. 33:32) Look! You are to them like a romantic love song, sung with a beautiful voice and skillfully played on a stringed instrument. They will hear your words, but no one will act on them.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

Friday, December 31

Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.—[Matt. 6:10].

Christendom generally does not teach the Scriptural truth that one day obedient humans will live forever on earth. (2 Cor. 4:3, 4) Today, most religions in Christendom teach that all good people go to heaven when they die. It was different, however, with the small group of Bible Students who were publishing the Watch Tower in the late 1800’s. They understood that God would restore Paradise on earth and that millions of obedient humans would live here on earth—not in heaven. However, it took time for them to discern clearly who these obedient humans would be. Of course, the Bible Students also discerned from the Scriptures that some would be “bought from the earth” to rule with Jesus in heaven. ([Rev. 14:3]) That group would be made up of 144,000 zealous and dedicated Christians who had served God faithfully while on earth. w19.09 27 ¶4-5

^ (Matt. 6:10) Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ (2 Cor. 4:3, 4) If, in fact, the good news we declare is veiled, it is veiled among those who are perishing, 4 among whom the god of this system of things has blinded the minds of the unbelievers, so that the illumination* of the glorious good news about the Christ, who is the image of God, might not shine through.

Or “light.”

^ (Rev. 14:3) And they are singing what seems to be a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders, and no one was able to master that song except the 144,000, who have been bought from the earth.